<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Equipment on Large Format Photography</title>
    <link>http://lflf.surge.sh/equipment/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Equipment on Large Format Photography</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://lflf.surge.sh/equipment/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>http://lflf.surge.sh/equipment/11x14/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lflf.surge.sh/equipment/11x14/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Large Format Photography: On the 11x14 format&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;on-the-11x14-format&#34;&gt;On the 11x14 format&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Compiled by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.terragalleria.com/&#34;&gt;Q.-Tuan Luong&lt;/a&gt; for &lt;a href=&#34;.&#34;&gt;the
Large Format Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;Wisner, Phillips and maybe Canham make 11x14 cameras.  A number of older
11x14&#39;s were available and can be found used (Kodak, Deardorff and others).
 (John Sparks)


Since you are not enlarging the film, just about any lens you can find
that will cover 11x14 is sharp enough.  I have a lens I bought for $75
(without a shutter) that will cover it and have two others that I
bought for 8x10 that would work as well (though not exactly cheap).
 There are several new lenses from each manufacturer that will cover
the format and many older ones including quite a few in the 12&amp;quot;-14&amp;quot;
range that often sell for less than $200.  One that is convertable
might be all you really need (the single cells of a 12&amp;quot; lens are
probably in the 18&amp;quot;-28&amp;quot; range).  Long lenses for 11x14 are pretty rare
and rather expensive (24&amp;quot; Artars are about the longest commonly found
which is about like a 210mm on 4x5 and they go for about $1200 these
days).  Besides the 800mm Apo- Tele-Xenar, there are some Zeiss
Apo-Germinars in 450mm, 600mm, 750mm and 1000mm that would cover
11x14.  The 750mm is about $3000 or less than half the price of the
Schneider :-).  Even the 600mm is supposed to cover 20x24.
 (John Sparks)


Which b&amp;amp;w-films for 11x14&amp;quot;?

1.Kodak Ektapan
2.Kodak T-Max
3.Ilford HP5
4.Ilford FP4
(Burkhardt Kiegeland)

The fidelity holders are quite good and there are at least 4 other
producers that I know of (Wisner, Hoffman,Brubaker,Great Basin)
(Richard Kuzniak)

Actually you need to know a bit about the holders and the camera. Not all
holders (old and new) are designed to fit all cameras -- 11x14 and above, we
are talking about both physical size (x,y dimensions) but more importantly--
the distance from the front surface of the holder to the film plane is
critical and VARIES WITH EACH MAKE OF HOLDER. (This isn&#39;t the mass production
and standardized world of 4x5-5x7 and 8x10). Just because that new film
holder fits in your camera does not ensure the dimensions are correct...
Have the holder and the camera measured to assure that the holder puts the
film at the same location as the ground glass surface for focusing.
Fidelity 11x14 follows the ANSI standard....  (but does your F&amp;amp;S or Corona or
whatever camera. expecially if it is really old??).
Alan Brubaker (AWB enterprises) makes outstanding holders for 11x14 and
up. I know you won&#39;t be disappointed. Great Basin also makes holders, but IMHO
not at the same quality level. We&#39;ll leave the Wisner holder discussion to
those that have already converted their Wisner 4x10 cameras to Keith Canham&#39;s
4x10 Fidelity holders....
(Don Nelson)

Nikkor 360 W, Schneider 355 G Claron,19&amp;quot; Red
Dots and  alot of Dagors cover the format beautifully and are
available used at a decent price.
(Richard Kuzniak)

Lenses:  They&#39;re out there.  I missed a fabulous opportunity to pick up
a 14&amp;quot; tessar-formula Wollensack for _$100_ at a swap I didn&#39;t think I
needed to go to.  This would&#39;ve come close to covering.  Also, I passed
on an 18&amp;quot; HugoMeyers WITH Packard shutter for $250 this past fall.
(Chris Perez)

&amp;gt;Theres a guy in Florida name of Clyde Butcher who shoots (I believe
&amp;gt;20x24).  He made a camera from an old process camera.  He shoots
&amp;gt;exclusively huge format i.e. &amp;gt;8x10 and makes all his own equipment.  I
&amp;gt;have wanted to take a workshop with him but have not yet done so.

Mailing address:
        Big Cypress Gallery
        52388 Tamiami Trail (Rte. 41)
        Ochopee, FL 33943.

You can buy his books from:
        Shade Tree Press,
        5647 Shaddelee Lane, West
        Fort Myers FL 33919 Phone 813-433-0222
(Robert Hudyman)



----------------------------------------------------------------------------
kuzniak@inforamp.net (Richard Kuzniak)

                  I worked with a 12x20 for a year and sold it because
I was frustrated by the limitations of a 60 year old banquet camera
(mostly bellows draw,also problems with film holders etc.) I did
learn a lot though and agree that the big negs are addictive...
I am hoping to win a lottery and buy a NEW camera either
a Wisner or Canham (his ideas for 16x20 are different from Wisner&#39;s
and intriguing...) I would like nothing better than a 20x24 but first
I want to research how to assure absolute film registration and
also film flatness (this is not adequately dealt with except maybe
by the Phillips 12x20 which uses a magnetic strip around the
perimeter of the film  to hold it down-I rented this camera and that
system worked fine) . As far as I know Wisner&#39;s 20x24 does not
have any special provision to ensure film flatness.I think that
one would almost have to have a Phillips type system or a vacuum
holder.A big piece of film like that is bound to sag just from its own
weight...
Also I would like to acquire good lenses that would cover that format
(probably 19,24&amp;quot; Dagors)Gary Adams worked with that format but
had focus problems.Doug Busch has worked with formats up to 40x50
(I would love to see some of THOSE prints!)  and could probably advise
on the film problem.With the disappearance of XX and possibly Azo I
think that maybe we fanatics should organize and get a few runs of
these materials to last us till we (gulp) die...but first I&#39;ve got to
win  that damn lottery, come up with foolproof film
flatness/registration and then 20x24 here I come!!


sanking@hubcap.clemson.edu (s carl king)


I guess you must first decide whether you want to spend $5k plus on
a new model (Wisner, and others) or about $2k on one of the older
banquet cameras, of which there were four I believe (Burke James,
Deardorff, Folmer &amp;amp; Schwing, and Gundlach Korona. There is an
interesting article on the banquet cameras in the November/December
issue of View Camera (1990). This issue also has some
good information about lenses for these cameras. If you can
not locate the article send me a dollar bill and I will be happy to
make you a copy and send it to you.
For your information, I have a Gundlach Korona 12X20 and am very pleased
with it, though I think the Former and Schwing is a tad better.

&amp;gt;I&#39;d love to move to 11x14 (eventually) but I work exclusively in
&amp;gt;the field. Are these things pratical to lug around on the trail ?
&amp;gt;I&#39;m a backpacker/hiker but try to limit my loads to about 30 to
&amp;gt;35 pounds. It seems to me that an old wooden 11x14 and a good
&amp;gt;tripod that could support the camera would exceed 30 pounds.

An 11x14 Deardorff weighs about 28 lbs.  I&#39;d guess a Kodak or B&amp;amp;J 11x14
would be a bit lighter, but probably still around 24 lbs.  Phillips
makes new 11x14 cameras that are the lightest available but still 17.5
lbs (ignoring their horizontal only version that probably weighs 12-15
lbs).  Holders weigh about 2 or 3 lbs, most lenses in shutter that cover
11x14 probably weigh at least 1.5-2 lbs (a #3 Copal or #4 Ilex shutter
weighs 1 lb without a lens and most 11x14 lenses will be in a shutter at
least this big).  A tripod that can hold a camera this large and heavy
weighs at least 10-12 lbs with a head but sturdy tripods this light are
not cheap.  So starting with a 24 lbs camera, you are at about 38 lbs
minimum with only one holder and one lens and that doesn&#39;t count
darkcloth, light meter, filters, etc.  You could make 35lbs with a
Phillips, one lens, tripod, one or two holders, lightweight darkcloth
though this still doesn&#39;t count the backpack (5 lbs?).


&amp;gt;I don&#39;t have the money for a new technical field
&amp;gt;(if Wisner makes one).

Wisner&#39;s literature says their 11x14 weighs 30 lbs!  This is their old
brass construction so there is a possibility of an aluminum design at
about 22-25 lbs.  Canham also makes an 11x14 that&#39;s probably between the
weight of the Phillips and the Wisner a maybe 20-22 lbs.  I think the Phillips
was about $2500 in 1993, the others are probabably twice as much.

(John Sparks)

The best choice would be a new (or used) 11x14 Phillips view - compact
and very light weight. If you could find a used older 11x14 Improved
Empire State view, this would a good alternative for probably a lot less
money. It&#39;s not as stable, not as many movements, BUT extremely compact
and lightweight. They&#39;re getting hard to find though. As for
backpacking, the biggest hurdle might be the filmholders - they just
might take up more space than the camera itself.

(Gregory A Kriss)

KBCanham&#39;s 11x14, of which 4 are under construction as we speak, is specified
to be 16.5 lbs with 48&amp;quot; bellows (max).

(DON NELSON)

        If you can find an older 11x14 they weigh in at 10 to 15
        lbs. My Rochester Universal weighs 14.5 lbs and it has a
        laminated bed.
        Street photographers tripods were made of thin aluminum
        and were fairly sturdy with large columns and big
        platform clam heads. Mine weighs in at 9 1/2 lbs.
        I do B&amp;amp;W landscapes so I get along with barrel lenses
        Protar Series 4 WA , 14&amp;quot; Dagor and one lens board with
        a adjustable len flange holder. The three weigh in at
        3 lbs...................

(William Franko)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;view-or-add-comments-http-www-greenspun-com-com-qtluong-photography-lf-11x14-html&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.greenspun.com/com/qtluong/photography/lf/11x14.html&#34;&gt;View or add comments&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>http://lflf.surge.sh/equipment/4x10/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lflf.surge.sh/equipment/4x10/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Large format photography: about the 4x10 and film holders&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;about-the-4x10-format-and-film-holders&#34;&gt;About the 4x10 format and film holders&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;By &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.thalmann.com/&#34;&gt;Kerry Thalmann&lt;/a&gt; for
&lt;a href=&#34;http://lflf.surge.sh/&#34;&gt;largeformatphotography.info&lt;/a&gt; (compiled by QTL)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-4x10-format&#34;&gt;The 4x10 format&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I shoot 4x10 and love the format. I shoot color transparency film in two
different fashions. The first is &amp;ldquo;true 4x10&amp;rdquo; - meaning I cut the film in
half in the dark prior to exposure, load it into 4x10 holders and shoot
it with a 4x10 camera. The second is to shoot two 4x10 images on a
single sheet of 8x10 film using conventional 8x10 holders, a split
darkslide, and an older 8x10 camera (Eastman Commercial All-Metal).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like the aspect ratio of the format, and I also like the fact that
many lenses I already had covered the format. It&amp;rsquo;s possible to assemble
a very wide range of lenses that cover this format, and still avoid the
heavy, bulky #3 shutter necessary for many 8x10 lenses (much like 5x7
in this regard). Like I said above, there are many very good, reasonably
compact lenses, both new and old, that barely or don&amp;rsquo;t quite cover 8x10.
These make wonderful choices for use on the 4x10 format.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For prints, I &amp;ldquo;enlarge&amp;rdquo; to either 8x20 or 12x30 digitally using a
flatbed scanner and an Epson 2200 printer. One nice thing about the 4x10
format is that you can get rather large prints using a relatively
affordable desktop inkjet printer. On the other hand, I&amp;rsquo;ve seen a number
of 4x10 contact prints from other photographers. With the right subject
and materials, the results can be exquisite. A print doesn&amp;rsquo;t always have
to be huge to hold one&amp;rsquo;s attention.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Drawbacks: with light leaks (see next section), a lack of a market for
my stock images (6x17 is BY FAR the preferred format for panoramic stock
sales), a lack of supporting products (4x10 transparency sleeves,
Quickmounts, etc.), at one point I gave up on the format in favor of
6x17.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;*4x10 &amp;ldquo;sees&amp;rdquo; the same way that 8x10 does. David Fokos. That is to say,
if you use a 210mm. lens for 8x10 (I use a Rodenstock Sironar-S, which
just barely covers), your 4x10 shots will have the same wide-angle
perspective. A 90mm lens would be *incredibly* wide-angle on the 4x10,
roughly the equivalent of a 45mm lens on a 4x5. &lt;strong&gt;David Fokos&lt;/strong&gt;*&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;David makes a very good point. I bought the 115mm Grandagon specifically
for 4x10 (even before I bought the camera). This decision was made based
on the mentality prevelant on many panaorama cameras: stick the widest
lens on the camera that will cover the film format and call it a
panorama. Once I actually started using the camera, I found that in most
situations, the 115mm on 4x10 was just too wide for my tastes. Although
in some situations, it was the only lens that would work (when you need
it, you NEED it). A 115mm or 120mm would probably be a good 4x10 focal
length for architectural interiors or large group photos in the banquet
tradition, but I found that I didn&amp;rsquo;t use it as much as I thought I would
for 4x10 landscapes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On a related note, compositionally, 4x10 (or any panoramic format) is
much different than the traditional 4x5 or 8x10 formats. In 4x5, I like
to use wide angle lenses (75mm or 90mm) to emphasize the foreground to
draw the viewer into the photograph. This is especially effective in
vertical compositions. In 4x10, the main compositional elements tend to
lie in middle third vertically acrossed the entire 10&amp;rdquo; width of the
film. In my experience, strong leading foregrounds just don&amp;rsquo;t work well
in a panoramic format. Therefore, I found myself using the ultrawide
focal lengths less that I do in 4x5, and found myself using the less
radical wide angles (165mm and 210mm) along with the more normal 300mm
focal length. The 450mm focal length was especially interesting. I use
my 210mm lens a lot on 4x5 (probably my most used focal length in that
format along with the 135mm). The 450 gave similar horizontal coverage
in the panoramic format. It provided some interesting compositions in
4x10, but I didn&amp;rsquo;t rely on it as much as I do the 210mm in 4x5. It is
interesting to note that if I was limited to one focal length in the
4x10 format I would choose the 210mm, the same focal length I would
choose for 4x5. Although the 210mm Nikkor W I had for 4x5 was adaquate
for 4x10, I would recommend something with a larger image circle (210mm
Super Symmar HM, 210mm Sironar W if you can afford it, 210mm Fujinon W,
210mm Angulon or 210mm f9 Computar or even 190mm Wide Field Ektar if you
are on a more modest budget) if you plan to shoot a lot of 4x10.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;4x10 is a wonderful, neglected format. Unfortunately, there are two
competing standards for the film holders and that adds to the confusion
(can you imagine what it would be like if different brands of 4x5 or
8x10 cameras required custom made holders of differing dimensions).
There aren&amp;rsquo;t a lot of us out there shooting in this beautiful size - so
you can consider yourself part of an exclusive, elite group of
photographers determined to do something just a little bit different
than most.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;4x10-vs-split-8x10-vs-4x5-stitched&#34;&gt;4x10 vs split 8x10 vs 4x5 stitched&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;8x10 holders and a lot easier to find and cheaper than 4x10 holders.
There are plenty of used 8x10 holders available on eBay at reasonable
prices. To me, that&amp;rsquo;s the key to shooting 4x10 is getting holders. The
Canham 4x10 holders are well made and the most reasonably priced new
holders (about \$95 each). For comparison, new 8x10 Fidelity holders are
about \$60 each - and you only need half as many for the same number of
shots. Of course, if you can get an ultralight 8x10, like the Phillips
Explorer, you can have the best of both worlds - a lightweight camera
and affordable holders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Split darkslides are sold by
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.benderphoto.com/4x10pa.htm&#34;&gt;Bender&lt;/a&gt; and
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.toho-machine.co.jp/Panorama.htm&#34;&gt;Toho&lt;/a&gt;, but &lt;a href=&#34;http://largeformatphotography.info/lfforum/topic/497643.html&#34;&gt;it is easy to
make it
yourself&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The procedure would be more lengthy but not more complicated than
normal:&lt;br /&gt;
For image 1:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;frame the scene using the top 4x10 half of the 8x10 ground glass
(assuming horizontal panorama),&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Put in 8x10 film holder.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pull dark slide and replace with special half fram dark slide with
the openning at the top.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make exposure.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Replace normal dark slide.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For image 2:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;frame the scene using the bottom half of the 8x10 ground glass&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Put in the same 8x10 film holder with the same side to the lens.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pull dark slide and replace with special half fram dark slide with
the openning at the bottom.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make exposure.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Replace normal dark slide.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This way you get two 4x10 exposures on each 8x10 sheet of film (both
will likely be processed the same, though you could cut the film after
exposure and before processing). A single holder gives you 4 exposures.
All equipment is standard except for the extra homemade cut darkslide.
&lt;strong&gt;Sandor&lt;/strong&gt;. Todd Caudle (spliting 4x5 into 2x5), recommends &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.photo.net/bboard/q-and-a-fetch-msg?msg_id=003xgh&#34;&gt;rotating
the back&lt;/a&gt;
instead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Deardorff also made 4x10 slider boards for their 8x10 camera backs. In
fact, that&amp;rsquo;s how I got started shooting 4x10. When I sold my Deardorff,
I kept the 4x10 slider board. I still have it. It also fits some 8x10
Kodak backs. It&amp;rsquo;s a very simple piece of wood, painted black with a
simple rabbet joint on each end, and two recessed &amp;ldquo;thumb holes&amp;rdquo; (not
really holes, as they don&amp;rsquo;t go all the way through the board) for
sliding it back and forth. If you have a Deardorff camera and are even
slightly handy, you could make one yourself. If I remember correctly,
the grooves for the 4x10 slider are offset from the grooves for the 5x8
slider. This would allow using one of each to shoot four 4x5 images
(minus margins) on a single sheet of 8x10 film. Kind of a poor man&amp;rsquo;s
reducing back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found two minor, but irritating problem with this method. First, 8x10
cameras ARE bigger, bulkier and heavier. Granted the Deardorff at about
13 - 14 lbs. isn&amp;rsquo;t exacty a lightweight 8x10, but still, given
comparable designs, a 4x10 camera will save you a few pounds and a fair
amount of bulk. The dedicated 4x10 I had was a Wisner Technical. The
basic chassis was the same as a 4x5 Technical (actually, I bought the
camera as a 4x5 Technical and bought the 4x10 back/bellows as an
accessory). Again, the Wisner Technical isn&amp;rsquo;t exactly a lightweight 4x5
by current standards, but in the 4x10 configuration weighed about 7 lbs.
I believe Wisner now has 4x10 converstion kits for his lighter weight
models (Expedition and/or Pocket expedition). These models, in 4x10
configuration should be a couple pounds lighter than a 4x10 Technical
(the Technical is Wisner&amp;rsquo;s heaviest 4x5). By building around a 4x5 base,
and having a back that&amp;rsquo;s &lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; the size, a 4x10 camera can be
significantly smaller and lighter than an 8x10. Not important for
everyone, but an issue for those who hike (I ONCE did a 23 mile day hike
with my 4x10 Wisner, big heavy tripod, holders, lenses, etc. It was hard
enough with the 4x10, I wouldn&amp;rsquo;t wanted to attempt it with an 8x10).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second issue I had was that it was necessary to shift the lens up
and down to center the image on the &lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; of the 8x10 film I was using.
This then limits the amount of effective front rise you have left. If
you have lenses with huge coverage, you can probably just shoot both
halves with the lens in its normal neutral position. Or, if you have a
camera with gobs of front rise, this isn&amp;rsquo;t an issue. I was using lenses
that didn&amp;rsquo;t quite, or just barely, covered 8x10 (115mm Granadgon-N,
165mm Angulon, 210mm Nikkor W, 300mm Nikkor M), so it was always
important that I recentered the lens for each shot to avoid vignetting.
Not a show stopper, just a little convenient.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In spite of these issues, for me, the dedicated 4x10 solution was even
more of a hassle. At the time, the only 4x10 film holders I could get to
fit my Wisner were the Mido II type. These were small and light, but
were very prone to light leaks (some operator induced, most due to
manufacturing defects in the holders). I sent my holders back twice to
have them repaired/replaced. Each time the problem got better, but was
still unacceptable. Cutting my own film was a hassle I was prepared to
live with, but cutting my own film and then having &lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; the exposures
ruined by light leaks, was not. Of course, now there are better 4x10
holders on the market, so this is probably a non-issue for anyone
entering this format these days. BTW, the 4x10 Wisner was a fine camera,
it was just the hodlers I disliked. The Canham 4x10 holders were MUCH
better, but bulkier and heavier. The current wooden Wisner holders
should be much better than the old Mido IIs I was using.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, cutting the film WAS a hassle. Not impossible, not even
difficult, just tedious. And, it exposed the film to a much greater
likelyhood that dust would settle on it during the cutting, notching,
loading process. At the time I entered the 4x10 format, Ilford sold
pre-cut FP4 and HP5 film, but I was shooting color transparencies, so I
had to cut my own Velvia. When I bought my camera, I was hopeful that
4x10 was an emerging standard (Wisner had just entered the market as the
second major manufacturer to offer a 4x10 camera, Ilford was selling
precut 4x10 film&amp;hellip;). I hoped the format would catch on and Fuji, Kodak,
etc, would start offering precut 4x10 film. Well, history tells us I was
naively optimistic in this regard. I don&amp;rsquo;t believe Ilford still offers
precut film in the 4x10 size (or maybe they do, but it&amp;rsquo;s special order
only). If not, and you don&amp;rsquo;t want to cut your own, Photo Warehouse will
do it for you at prices that are quite reasonable (at least they are in
other oddball sizes like 6 &lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; x 8 &lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;*I&amp;rsquo;ve done stiched panoramas before, and they are fun. The main problem
is ensuring that the pivot point is centered on the nodal point of the
lens. Not too many view cameras have a mounting point below the lens. If
this isn&amp;rsquo;t done, close objects in the scene will not stich together
well. If the camera has rear shift, this would be a better option,
assuming the lens can cover the new virtual format. &lt;strong&gt;George Steward&lt;/strong&gt;*&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I contemplated getting back into 4x10, I seriously considered this
method. As I already had a 4x5 camera with rear shifts and a number of
lenses that cover 4x10. The initial investment would be relatively small
(the cost of the stitching SW, and either a new desktop scanner - which
I&amp;rsquo;ll probably get anyway - or the price of paying someone else to do the
scans). However, I happened to get a great deal on some slightly used
4x10 holders. I then assembled my own hybrid 4x10 camera from bits and
pieces I picked up from a number of sources. So, the method of using
rear shift and stitching got put on the back burner. George&amp;rsquo;s reply
jogged my memory and got me thinking (always dangerous) about this
again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although I have a 4x10 camera and holders, there are times when I want
to go lighter (backpacking). My 4x10 camera and lenses are reasonably
light, but the weight and bulk of the holders can add up quickly
compared to 4x5 Quickloads or Readyloads. For that reason, I have
considered using rear shift to shoot two 4x5 images and stitch them
together to produce something close to a 4x10 image (maybe 4x9 with the
overlap between the two frames). This would allow me to carry an
ultralight camera, like the Toho, leave the 4x10 holders at home and use
Quick/Readyloads. This would be the ideal set-up for backpacking. I
could also use this same method with my ARCA-SWISS if I&amp;rsquo;m out in the
field and don&amp;rsquo;t have any 4x10 holders with me (or run out of loaded
holders and don&amp;rsquo;t have time to reload).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You need to use lenses capable of covering 4x10, but I have a number of
reasonably lightweight lenses with ample coverage. One possible issue I
see is asymmetric light fall-off when using wide angle lenses. If this
does show up, I assume it can be evened out in SW. Anybody have any
experience they can share?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, since there should be little distortion using this method
(compared to rotating the camera), I would think the amount of overlap
between the two frames would be small. In general, I prefer working with
a camera in my intended format. I prefer composing the entire image on
the ground glass and exposing it on a single sheet of film. There are
certainly advantages to this method. However, for times when it&amp;rsquo;s
impractical or impossible, using rear shift and stitching two images
together seems to be a viable alternative. As my interest in 4x10 has
been rekindled, I&amp;rsquo;ll probably give it a try in the next couple months
and see how well it works. In the mean time, if anybody else has tried
it, please share what you&amp;rsquo;ve learned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;holder-standards&#34;&gt;Holder standards&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I highly recommend you consider the holders first. IMHO, in
non-mainstream formats, the availability of affordable (or at least
attainable) holders is of paramount importance. For me, while choosing a
camera may be more exciting, getting the holders is far more important.
I learned that the hard way the first time I tried 4x10. The second time
around, I bought the holders first, before I even started looking for a
camera. The most beautiful camera in the world is useless without
holders for your film.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;BTW, in 4x10, there are TWO different &amp;ldquo;standard&amp;rdquo; sizes for the holders.
The Wisner 4x10 cameras use holders based on the older 4x10 X-Ray
holders (made by Lisco, Fidelity and Kodak more than 30 years ago). It
can be REAL hard to find holders in this size. The most common are the
Mido II holders (that are not the best holders ever made) that were sold
for the Wisner cameras about 10 years ago. While the concept is good,
the quality of construction wasn&amp;rsquo;t the best and light leaks can be a big
problem (I speak from experience). The Mido holders were discontinued
several years ago after the death of their maker. Ron Wisner does have
4x10 wooden holders listed on his website, but I haven&amp;rsquo;t seen any in
person, nor have I talked to anybody who has. So, I can&amp;rsquo;t comment on the
quality or availability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All the other commercially available 4x10 cameras (Canham, Lotus and
Altview) use holders that are wider than the Wisner X-Ray style holders.
Holders in this size are readily available from Keith Canham (as
mentioned above ~\$95 each and very well made) and
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lotusviewcamera.at/accessories/sheetfilmholder_e.html&#34;&gt;Lotus&lt;/a&gt;
(wooden, beautiful, well-made and expensive), &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.filmholders.com&#34;&gt;AWB Alan
Brubaker&lt;/a&gt; (check out Alan&amp;rsquo;s web site for
some nice photos of his holders in various sizes) and S&amp;amp;S (Sandy King
and Sam Wang) will custom make wooden holders in a variety of formats.
Such custom made holders are justifiably expensive (the labor involved
in making 4x10 or 5x12 holders is the nearly the same as making 11x14 or
12x20 holders). I was fortunate to purchase several used Lotus 4x10
holders at a very reasonable price. If I was looking to buy new holders
today, I&amp;rsquo;d buy the Canham holders as they are readily available and
represent the best value.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;more-on-options-available-to-wisner-camera-owners&#34;&gt;More on options available to Wisner camera owners&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;4x10 Fidelity/Kodak/Lisco X-Ray Holders - Evidently these were popular
at one time in the ancient past for x-raying animal paws and infant
limbs. The medical/veterinary industry switched to a different style
x-ray cassette decades ago. I spent YEARS trying to track some of these
down, calling all my local vets, x-ray supply houses, manufacturers,
begging another photographer to sell me his, etc. Finally, someone at
Fidelity searched through some old catalogs and said they&amp;rsquo;d discontinued
their 4x10 x-ray holders over 30 years ago. In over 14 years of looking,
I&amp;rsquo;ve only seen three of these for sale (4x10 Lisco X-Ray Holders).
Unfortunately, this was the standard Ron Wisner chose to use when he
introduced his 4x10 camera. As you are aware, this makes the Wisner 4x10
cameras uniquely incompatible with the Canham style holders that
everybody else uses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;4x10 Mido II Holders and Clamshell - When I bought my 4x10 Wisner
Technical Field in early 1992, these were the holders Wisner was selling
with the camera. I bought the camera, five holders and a clamshell. The
holders leaked light like a sieve. I was losing more shots to light
leaks than not. I sent the holders back to Mido multiple times to be
reworked/repaired/replaced. Each time they came back, there were
incremental improvements in the failure rate - but it was still too high
to be acceptable. Mr. Mido seemed determined to make the holders work.
His concept was a good one, but quality and consistency of the
construction of the holders was lacking. In August 1996, I gave up and
sold my entire 4x10 outfit (4x5/4x10 Wisner Tech Field, Mido holders and
several lenses). The Mido II holders do occasionally show up on the used
market. They may have improved the quality after I sold mine, or with
some patience and skill, it may be possible to rework the holders and/or
clamshell to improve the success rate. Unfortunately, I learned a year
or two after selling my camera that Mr. Mido had become ill and
eventually passed away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oddly, B&amp;amp;H still lists 4x10 Mido holders and clamshells on their web
site. They are listed as a special order item. I wonder if that means
there are some new, old stock 4x10 Mido holders still in existence
somewhere, or if they have just neglected to update their web site in
the last six or seven years. They list the clamshell (focus spacer) with
one holder at \$159.95 and additional holders at \$79.95. I&amp;rsquo;ve been
curious what would happen if someone attempted to order some 4x10 Mido
holders from B&amp;amp;H (but not curious enough to try placing an order as I no
longer have the Wisner 4x10 camera).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;4x10 Lotus Holders (Wisner Form Factor or Canham form factor) - I sold
my 4x10 Wisner outfit to a gentleman from Austria named Burkhardt
Kiegeland. He immediately shared my frustration with the Mido II
holders. Mr Kiegeland had the resources and commitment to do something
about it. He had a craftsman make some 4x10 holders to fit the Wisner
camera and formed a new company, Lotus View Camera to manufacture and
sell these holders. Lotus immediately became a supplier of holders to
Wisner. In November, 1996 I saw one of these Lotus 4x10 holders at a
Wisner dealer in Sacramento. The quality appeared to be quite good. and
at \$95 the price was competitive. Lotus also began manufacturing 4x10
holders in the Canham form factor, as well as other banquet and ULF
sizes. Soon thereafter, Lotus also introduced their own line of cameras
from 4x5 - 20x24. I&amp;rsquo;m not sure when the official Lotus/Wisner holder
relationship dissolved, but if you can find some of the Lotus holders in
the Wisner size, they should serve you well. Lotus will still custom
make 4x10 holders in the Wisner form factor, but the price is
considerably more than the original \$95 retail price. The dollar is
much weaker now than it was in the late 1990s, and this would now be
considered a special custom made item, not something normally in stock.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wisner 4x10 Holders - I have not used any of the Wisner wooden holders,
but the ones I&amp;rsquo;ve seen did not look nearly as well made at the wooden
holders I&amp;rsquo;ve seen from S&amp;amp;S, Lotus or AWB (Alan Brubaker). Of course,
thay also cost a LOT less. The Wisner holders have the advantage of
being, by far, the least expensive of the wooden 4x10 holders. If Emile
can get them for you without delay at \$95 each, it may be worth a try.
As I haven&amp;rsquo;t used them, I can&amp;rsquo;t specifically recommend them one way or
the other. Perhaps somebody who has used Wisner holders could chime in
with their experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Custom Made Holders - As I mentioned above, Lotus will still custom make
4x10 holders in the Wisner form factor. As they were once an official
supplier to Wisner, you are assured the holders will fit your camera
properly. I haven&amp;rsquo;t used any 4x10 Lotus holders in the Wisner size, but
I am fortunate to have fifteen of their holders in the Canham form
factor and can attest that they are light tight, beautifully made, and
smooth to operate. Others have mentioned the S&amp;amp;S holders supplied by
Sandy King and Sam Wang. I have seen these holders in person, but not
used them. They appear to be of excellent quality, and other
photographers I know who&amp;rsquo;ve used them are very satisfied. The nice thing
about S&amp;amp;S is they seem very willing to make custom made holders in any
size you desire at a reasonble (for custom made holders) price. I have
also not used the AWB holders, but they also come highly recommended.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you do get custom made holders, I&amp;rsquo;d recommend getting them made in
the Canham form factor and getting your camera modified to match. The
Canham standard is the more common of the two. In addition to the Canham
4x10 camera, cameras in this format from Lotus and Patrick Alt also use
the Canham style holders. Holders in this size are more readily
available, both new and used. The cost of getting your Wisner camera
back modified will be, IMHO money well spent. The REAL key to shooting a
non-mainstream format, like 4x10, is the availability and cost of
holders. Getting your Wisner modified to accept Canham style holders
will increase your options.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;4x10 Canham Holders - This is probably the most practical option. Canham
holders are made from parts he gets from Fidelity. They look and feel
just like regular Fidelity holders. At \$95 each, they cost considerably
more than standard, off-the-shelf 8x10 Fidelity holders, but in the
oddball world that is 4x10, they are a relative bargain. I have never
heard of any problems with light leaks from anybody using 4x10 Canham
holders. If you&amp;rsquo;re looking for the lowest cost, least hassle option,
this would be the way to go. Some people may prefer the elegant look and
feel of fine wooden holders over the plastic and aluminum of the Canham
holders. I can&amp;rsquo;t say I blame them - like a fine wooden camera, fine
wooden holders are pleasing to the eye and to the touch. However, if
you&amp;rsquo;re just looking for holders that are reliable, attainable, durable
and affordable, it&amp;rsquo;s tough to beat the Canhams. I have no idea what it
would cost today, but 8 years ago before I sold my 4x10 Wisner, Keith
Canham quoted me a price of \$100 to modify my Wisner camera to accept
his holders. Even if the price has tripled in the last 8 years, I still
think it would be worth it in the long run.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m now on my second go around with 4x10. My first attempt ended in
frustration over the lack of quality holders to fit my camera. I got
tired of sending my holders back to Mido for &amp;ldquo;tune-up&amp;rdquo;, wating a few
weeks for them to come back and still losing a large percentage of my
best shots to light leaks. It just wasn&amp;rsquo;t worth it. In hindsight, I
should have taken Keith Canham up on his offer to modify my camera,
bought five or ten of his holders and gone happily about my business.
Rather than face the same frustration, this time around, I bought the
holders FIRST, before I even started looking for a 4x10 camera. I told
myself I didn&amp;rsquo;t care what camera they fit, I was going to snap up the
first quality 4x10 holders I found at a reasonable price, and then buy a
camera to match. This strategy worked much better. I was fortunate to
find fifteen 4x10 Lotus holders at an extremely agreeable price. I
snapped them up, and haven&amp;rsquo;t looked back. They happened to be the Canham
form factor - all the better. If I need additional holders to fit my
camera at some time in the future, I know I can get them from Canham at
a reasonable price.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I owned my 4x10 Wisner Tech Field, I never had a single complaint
about the quality or usability of the camera. It was actually a
beautiful camera that was a joy to use (except for the Mido holders). It
is also the most affordable of the full-featured 4x10 cameras - by a
fair margin. Don&amp;rsquo;t let the holder situation scare you off. Bite the
bullet and get some good holders (even if it means modifying the back of
your camera). You&amp;rsquo;ll be glad you did. Welcome to the 4x10 format.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;more-info-and-comments&#34;&gt;More info and comments&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This article was put together by QTL using Kerry Thalmann&amp;rsquo;s replies in
the following Q&amp;amp;A threads with minor editing:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://lflf.surge.sh/lfforum/topic/498501.html&#34;&gt;Fishing for long and skinny&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://lflf.surge.sh/lfforum/topic/189903.html&#34;&gt;4x10 format questions&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://lflf.surge.sh/lfforum/topic/498002.html&#34;&gt;Poor Man&amp;rsquo;s 4x10&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://lflf.surge.sh/lfforum/topic/498926.html&#34;&gt;Need 4x10 film holders for Wisner TF&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>http://lflf.surge.sh/equipment/8x10/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lflf.surge.sh/equipment/8x10/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Large Format Photography: 8x10 cameras&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;8x10-cameras&#34;&gt;8x10 cameras&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;By John Sparks for &lt;a href=&#34;.&#34;&gt;the Large Format Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For new cameras, there are about 3 field cameras that make sense.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Phillips makes some really interesting cameras that are very light
weight but have somewhat limited bellows extension. If you are not into
long lenses, they are one of the best choices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Canham makes a really good camera (I have one) that is also very light
(slightly heavier than Phillips) but had much longer bellows extension.
There are some things I don&amp;rsquo;t really like about it (mostly that it&amp;rsquo;s not
as rigid as I would like for long bellows extensions but it&amp;rsquo;s hard to
have great rigidity and low weight at the same time, I also get pinched
at times with the lever locks, I generally prefer knobs). It is
unfortunately very expensive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The third good choice is the Wisner Traditional L. It&amp;rsquo;s about \$900 less
than the Canham. It weighs about 1 lb more. I don&amp;rsquo;t know about it&amp;rsquo;s
rigidity at large extensions, but suspect it might be better because of
it&amp;rsquo;s construction. It wasn&amp;rsquo;t available when I bought my Canham, but I&amp;rsquo;d
probably buy it instead if I were doing it over now (mostly because of
the lower price for a very similar camera).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;view-or-add-comments-http-www-greenspun-com-com-qtluong-photography-lf-8x10-html&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.greenspun.com/com/qtluong/photography/lf/8x10.html&#34;&gt;View or add comments&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>http://lflf.surge.sh/equipment/black-jacket/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lflf.surge.sh/equipment/black-jacket/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h2 id=&#34;black-jacket-focus-cloth-from-quietworks-user-review&#34;&gt;Black Jacket Focus Cloth from Quietworks - User Review&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;By &lt;a href=&#34;mailto:paulowen_2000@yahoo.com&#34;&gt;Paul Owen&lt;/a&gt; © 2005 for
&lt;a href=&#34;%20.&#34;&gt;largeformatphotography.info&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Along with the majority of large format photographers, I have spent a
great deal of time scouring the internet looking for a focus cloth that
does one simple thing - work!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a complete fool with needle and thread, making one was not an option!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;d tried different types of &amp;ldquo;horse blankets&amp;rdquo; but found that despite
various materials used in their construction, they all suffered from
more than one &amp;ldquo;problem&amp;rdquo; for me personally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Firstly if you want anything decent then you need to be prepared to
carry something large and (surprisingly) heavy. The major drawback I
came across was that unless the material was large enough to wrap
completely around the camera AND had Velcro strips to secure it, then it
was often difficult to compose the image on the ground glass as a large
amount of light &amp;ldquo;bounced&amp;rdquo; off the floor and did a merry dance on the
screen!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I thought I had found a &amp;ldquo;good&amp;rdquo; cloth in the Harrison-made &amp;ldquo;Classic&amp;rdquo;
cloth. Plenty big enough, mandatory Velcro strips, weatherproof,
light-tight and &amp;hellip;heavy! But it had to be (or so I thought) to get the
combination of size and light proofing! So I persevered with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I then came across the Ebony focus cloth. Rubberised silk, emblazoned
with the &amp;ldquo;Ebony&amp;rdquo; logo, weatherproof, very (very) lightweight, mandatory
Velcro strips &amp;hellip; by Jove I think I found it &amp;hellip; the &amp;ldquo;holy grail&amp;rdquo; of
focus cloths! However, a few outings revealed that it needed improving.
I convinced my wife to assist with converting the Ebony cloth into an
Ebony tube! Elasticated drawstring sewn into one end, Velcro strips and
there I had it - nothing to this sewing lark!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I quite happily used my Ebony-hybrid and it still serves me well.
However, recent threads on this forum mentioned a new addition to the
list of contenders. &amp;ldquo;Quietworks&amp;rdquo; was now producing a focus jacket!! I
had to take a look at this!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found their web site and was quite amazed at the ingenuity of this
design. It seemed to do everything - and doubled up as a rather nifty
silver rain jacket too &amp;hellip; for me not the camera!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Around this time I began tentative enquiries on another matter - trying
to establish free large format workshop-type gatherings here in the UK.
Surprisingly the response was overwhelming and a hastily arranged first
meeting took place in the Lake District of England. As is usual when a
group of photographers get together, there is the customary discussions
about equipment - more so with large format users!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was clear that a great many of us had yet to find an ideal focus
cloth. I must add that on previous F32 workshops that I assisted on I
saw some amazing sights - from Dracula-impersonators (one cloth trailed
behind its user who wore it tied around his shoulders like the Count
himself) to those who had sewn together a couple of black t-shirts for a
double-thickness &amp;ldquo;tube&amp;rdquo; (with short sleeves!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their owners seemed happy enough - but I thought that this may have been
simply due to the fact that there wasn&amp;rsquo;t anything commercially available
that was much better!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, despite the fact that they &amp;ldquo;worked&amp;rdquo; for their owners (especially
the t-shirt) they looked, well, ridiculous! I&amp;rsquo;m sorry but I for one find
that I become something of a novelty act when the &amp;ldquo;old wooden camera&amp;rdquo;
comes out! Disappear under a cloak or t-shirt and the Weirdo-factor is
multiplied by a bout 10. One reason the Ebony &amp;ldquo;tube&amp;rdquo; worked for me - it
was fairly discreet!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, back to the plot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the Lake District gathering and when it became clear that this was
to become a regular meeting - I decided to give Keith at Quietworks a
call (well an email actually). The result - demo 5x4 &amp;ldquo;Original&amp;rdquo; and 10x8
&amp;ldquo;Hybrid&amp;rdquo; blackjackets in the post from the good old US of A to me here
in dear old &amp;lsquo;Blighty, for our group to try out and report back!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First impression? Lightweight. In fact, super-lightweight! These things
weighed next to nothing - what it actually weighs (to me) is not
important - what is important is how easy it is to stuff in a pack and
that it doesn&amp;rsquo;t add to the bulk or weight of the (already heavy)
backpack! But for those who count the ounces the 5x4 weighs in at 8
ounces and the 10x8 weighs a mere 23 ounces!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How do they fare? Well the next workshop is scheduled for October 15-16,
2005, but I couldn&amp;rsquo;t wait that long to try them out! So a quick dash one
Saturday morning found me on a deserted beach in sunny South Wales.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Camera and tripod set up, it was time to try them both out. The 5x4
version was tried first. Problem! The fit around the camera back was
very tight - a struggle to actually get it around the frame. The Ebony
45SU I was using does have a large rear frame and this was obviously the
cause of the problem! However, a bit of jiggling and with the neck of
the cloth around the bellows of the camera it was time to try it out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;WOW! It actually worked! Nice and dark but the real boon was the fact
that I could rummage around to my hearts content with my arms in the
sleeves and it STAYED dark! There was so much room inside that I was
able to move my head way back from the screen to get the &amp;ldquo;big picture&amp;rdquo;
with room to spare. I have done this in the past with other cloths and
ended up catching the camera and tripod as I dragged it backwards!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another problem! The design of my camera means that the frame is raised
above the bed by a good inch when in the neutral position. Result - a
shaft of light across the bed of the camera and into the jacket.
Certainly nowhere near as distracting as the blanket-type cloth but
easily solved by the use of my free hand simply stuffing some of the
material under the frame!! DARKNESS!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second impression? I REALLY like this!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Onto the 10x8 version. It&amp;rsquo;s BIG!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I tried it with the Ebony and found that it was swamped by the jacket.
Not surprised really as it&amp;rsquo;s designed for 10x8 cameras! But once back at
home I fitted it to a 10x8 Deardorff and it was a perfect fit!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Likewise, at home I also tried the 5x4 Original on a Cambo Wide -
beautiful fit!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What else is there to mention?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nothing really apart from the fact that, at last, there seems to be a
focus cloth that does what it&amp;rsquo;s supposed to do - create a darkened
environment in which we can experience the beauty of the scene on a
ground glass screen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From a user point of view the Black Jackets fit the bill and they are
also surprisingly cheap for such a well-made and functional product.
They are roomy, dark and have none of the claustrophobia I found with
the regular tube-type cloths I had tried.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;What exactly makes this focus cloth so different from the competition?
I hear you ask! Well, for me its greatest benefit is the fact that at
last, here is a focus cloth that does the job we want. Unlike the
blanket type cloth the BlackJacket doesn&amp;rsquo;t suffer from those annoying
light-leaks that make focusing tricky - it really does provide the right
environment for working with a ground glass screen. Another plus is that
it doesn&amp;rsquo;t wrap itself around you with every gust of wind a problem
inherent with the blanket-type cloth - in fact I reckon EVERY LF user
must have struggled in this situation at some time or another.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, unlike the blanket-type cloth (with the exception of the Ebony),
the BlackJacket is extremely lightweight, waterproof and very compact.
Being able to stuff it into a pocket or space in your pack is a real
boon - no more trying to fold a focus cloth in windy/wet conditions!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The design of the BlackJacket shares similarities with the tube-type
cloths but with a few real advantages over this design. For one, it is
incredibly roomy inside and being able to access the screen and camera
controls through the sleeves is, for me, a very natural way of working.
I also found that regular tube-type cloths were claustrophobic - shoving
my head down a tunnel was never my idea of fun but the added space
inside this cloth is very beneficial.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One benefit that photographers in much warmer climates will appreciate
is the nature of the material used by Keith in his designs. The
&amp;ldquo;Original&amp;rdquo; version is waterproof and very light but the &amp;ldquo;Hybrid&amp;rdquo;
version, depsite being a bit heavier is actually made using a breathable
fabric. Whilst this will be of little benefit in the UK I&amp;rsquo;m sure it will
be much appreciated in warmer countries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, Keith has not forgotten us living in wetter climes, and his
web-site clearly shows the benefit that actually wearing the BlackJacket
can have in sudden downpours!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In short, the design of this cloth combines the advantages of the
blanket and tube-types rolled into one and I for one hope that
&amp;ldquo;Quietworks&amp;rdquo; sell plenty of them! This company is continually making
steps at improving and developing their line of products. At the moment
Keith is developing BlackJackets for ULF photographers using a variety
of formats and is obviously customer-driven.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All in all I found it to be a well-made and very useful product and in
my opinion a necessity rather than an accessory - although I doubt if I
would be seen &amp;ldquo;wearing&amp;rdquo; it - well not in public anyway!&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can heartily recommend either of these. The 5x4 version will fit most
field cameras but it may be worth checking out the 5x7 version as this
will offer slightly more room to fit large rear frames.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m looking forward to October when I can share this revelation with
fellow LF&amp;rsquo;ers as we do battle with the Northumberland Coast!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;link-to-the-manufacturer-s-site-with-photos&#34;&gt;Link to the manufacturer&amp;rsquo;s site (with photos)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;view-or-add-comments-20http-largeformatphotography-info-lfforum-topic-502725-html&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;%20http://largeformatphotography.info/lfforum/topic/502725.html&#34;&gt;View or add comments&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[](mailto:paulowen_2000@yahoo.com)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;paulowen_2000@yahoo.com&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>http://lflf.surge.sh/equipment/classic-experts/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lflf.surge.sh/equipment/classic-experts/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Large Format Photography:more on classic lenses&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;more-on-classic-lenses&#34;&gt;More on classic lenses&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Most is from &lt;a href=&#34;mailto:dickburk@ix.netcom.com&#34;&gt;Richard Knoppow&lt;/a&gt; for &lt;a href=&#34;.&#34;&gt;the
Large Format Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Contents:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ektars&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Goertz (Red Dot) Artar&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dagor&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tessars,Xenars,Heliar&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;shutters&#34;&gt;Shutters&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;shutters.html#apertures&#34;&gt;A table of older aperture systems&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Compound is an old type shutter using an air-brake to control the
speeds. When clean they are quite reliable and have the advantage over
the older Ilex shutters of having a time setting independant of the
speed setting so that you can focus without resetting the exposure time.
They are also quite easily modified to provide for X-synch for strobe
flash.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The old Ilex shutters are often found on older commercial lenses. If
really clean they are acceptable shutters but should be exercised a
couple of times before making exposures. They were intended to run
without any lubrication. When they are lubricated they tend to be
erratic. The cure is a carful cleaning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;ektars&#34;&gt;Ektars&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ektar was used by Kodak as a trade name for its premium lenses. There
were a number of generic designs used for them. Ektars were all very
high quality lenses. The ones made for press and view cameras were
mostly Tessar types. Exceptions are the Wide Field Ektars, which are
four element air-spaced lenses of the &amp;ldquo;Double Gause&amp;rdquo; type, and the 203mm
f/7.7 Ektar which is a four-element air-spaced Dialye type, made
slightly non-symetrical to improve its correction for distant objects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of these lenses are completely corrected for lateral color and were
intended for color photography. Some Ektars were coated as early as
1940. These include the series of f/6.3 lenses marked &amp;ldquo;Eastman Ektar&amp;rdquo;,
which are the predicessors of the Commerical Ektar series. The early
coatings were soft and applied only to inside surfaces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other early coated Ektars were the lenses made for the Ektra camera and
for the Medallist. Other Ektar lenses were not coated until after about
1946.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kodak had a very advanced glass plant and made their own optical glass.
They developed commercially the rare-earth glasses discovered at the
National Bureau of Standards and were one of the first manufacturers to
use Lanthanum Crown glass.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ektars are also among the earliest lenses to be cemented with
thermo-setting synthetic adhesives rather than the traditional Canada
Balsam.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Generally, an Ektar in good condition will have excellent performance
even by current standards. Kodak quality control after about 1938, when
Rudolph Kingslake took over the optical department, was excellent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kodak lenses from about this date on can be dated by the two letters
preceding the serial number. They are a code for the last two digits of
the years of manufacture. The code word is C A M E R O S I T Y standing
for 1,2,3,4,etc. e.g. a lens marked ES-413 was built in 1947.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Commerical Ektar was a series of f/6.3 Tessar type lenses intended
for use on view cameras. Tessars have somewhat better performance at
f/6.3 than when faster.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;_All_ lenses sold under the Ektar name were highly corrected for
color, especially for lateral color, which is sometimes known as
chromatic magnification. In other words, the size of the images from
different colors are the same size.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Commerical Ektar series was sold as Eastman Ektars prior to about
1946. The earlier version was soft coated on insided surfaces, the
Commercial Ektar is hard coated on all surfaces and bears the &amp;ldquo;circle-L&amp;rdquo;
mark for coating standing for Kodak&amp;rsquo;s trade-mark &amp;ldquo;Luminized&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not all Ektars are coated. Most of the f/4.5 series, for use on press
cameras, etc., were not coated until after about 1946 (I don&amp;rsquo;t know the
exact date Kodak started coating all its lenses).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most Ektars for medium and large format are Tessar types, but Ektar was
used as a trade-mark for a quality level rather than a specific design.
For example, the f/1.9 lens for the Ektra and the Aero-Ektar are both
seven element Biotar types, the 45mm f/2 lens for the Bantam Special is
a six element Biotar. At least four other prototipical designs were used
for Ektar lenses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Undoubtedly, the quality of the coatings varied over the fifteen or so
year period that Kodak continued to make lenses after coating was
adopted. Unfortunately, according to my contact at Kodak, the historical
material which would clarify this sort of issue has been buried away
somewhere and is not accessible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My statement about the coating of Eastman Ektars is based on statements
made in a 1940 or 1941 Kodak lens handbook. This states that this series
and the also the lenses for the Ektra camera were soft coated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;some-specific-ektars&#34;&gt;Some specific Ektars&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;By Michael Liczbanski&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;The quality varies depending on the vintage &amp;amp; purpose of Ektars...
I realize that the original post was most likely about the LF Ektars, but
many MF Ektars are on the market as well (sometimes sans their original
cameras so one cannot tell without testing whether or not they cover
4x5...)  Here is a brief description of just a few Ektars:

Kodak Ektar 2/45 (for Bantam Special)
6 elements in 4 groups, covers 28x40mm negatives

Kodak Ektar 3.5/100 (for Kodak Medalist)
5 elements in 3 groups, covers 2 1/4 x 3  1/4  (and 6.5x9 cm)

Kodak Ektar 3.7/105
4 elements in 3 groups, covers 2 1/4 x 3  1/4
*** A very good lens, also used on the Precision enlarger.  Sharp and
contrasty.

Kodak Ektar 4.5/101 and 4.7/127
4 elements in 3 groups, covers  2 1/4 x 3  1/4  and 3 1/4 x 4  1/4
respectively
*** Also a great lens, esp. for 6x9

Eastman Ektar 6.3/8 1/2in; 6.3/10in; 6.3/12in; 6.3/14in
4 elements in 3 groups, these lenses cover 5x7 to 8x10in.  The 14 inch
covers also 11x14 at f/16 and below, but without much room for movements.
*** Great, fully corrected lenses (coated!)  Expensive, big and still very
useful
even today.  All have a great circle of coverage and a very &amp;quot;sweet&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;full
bodied&amp;quot; shadow detail.  The minimum f stop is f/45, whereas I&#39;d prefer f/64
or even smaller for 8x10.

Kodak Ektar 1.9/50; 3.5/50; 3.3/35; 3.5/90; 3.8/105; 4.5/135 (for Kodak
Ektra)
All cover (some barely) 24x36mm.
Come in a variety of designs (even a nice triplet at 3.5/90) and their
quality varies from lousy (1.9/50 esp. wide open) to superb 3.5/50, 3.3/35.

Well, the Anastigmat was a separate line of lenses  - essentially Tessars
with the exception of the 6.3/105, 6.3/130 and 7.7/8in.
Some notable Anastigmats were:
7.7/8in
Covers 5x7 &amp;quot;process&amp;quot; lens, well-corrected for close-up work.  Quite nice

5 1/2in, 6 3/8in, 7 1/2in, 8 1/2in, 10in and 12in - all f/4.5
Cover from 3 1/4 x 4 /1/4 to 8x10 (with movements) depending on the focal
length.  Fine lenses (great for architecture, as they don&#39;t display much
linear distortions of any kind.)

There were also Anastigmats for small format cameras (35mm, Bantams and
Vigilants)

Well after WWII, Kodak started tinkering with their lenses a lot, and the
distinctions between many lens lines blur in the 50s.  (The summary above
describes the mid-to-late 40s status quo.)

 An additional note.  Many prewar Kodak lenses were sold as Kodak
Anastigmat followed by a number. It would seem from catalogue data
that numbers in the &amp;quot;thirty&amp;quot; series, like K.A. No.33 are Tessars,
those begining with 70 seem to be dialytes (four element air spaced
type).

Here are the numbers (actually in the Kodak catalogue, the numbers
precede the lens name:)  All data come from Kodak Reference Handbook, 1946
(practically unchaged from 1940-1946.)

No. 31 Kodak Anastigmat f/4.5  5 1/2in (140mm)
No. 32 Kodak Anastigmat f/4.5  6 3/8in (161mm)
No. 33 Kodak Anastigmat f/4.5  7 1/2in (190mm)
No. 34 Kodak Anastigmat f/4.5  8 1/2in (216mm)
No. 35 Kodak Anastigmat f/4.5  10in (254mm)
No. 36 Kodak Anastigmat f/4.5  12in (304mm)

All appear to be Tessars (4 elements in 3 groups, 4 internal air surfaces)

No. 70 Kodak Anastigmat f/7.7 8in (203mm)

(Symmetrical, air-spaced, 4 elements in 4 groups, 6 internal air surfaces.)
BTW, that&#39;s the one I like on a 4x5 VC the best (it will cover 5x7, but with
4x5 you&#39;ll sooner run out of swings and titlts, than go beyond its circle of
coverage.)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;goertz-red-dot-artar&#34;&gt;Goertz (Red Dot) Artar&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unless the remounting was butched it should be an excellent lens.
Kingslake gives some history of the Artar in his book _A History of the
Photographic lens_ The Apochromatic Artar was designed by Walter
Zschokke of Goerz in 1904, it became the most widely used process lens
for decades. It is a true apochromat and very well corrected for other
aberrations as well. The corrections of &amp;ldquo;dialyte&amp;rdquo; lenses like the Artar
do not change much with distance. While it is optimized for 1:1 (the
later &amp;ldquo;Red Dot&amp;rdquo; series was not) it will perform very well at infinity.
The lens begins to get a little coma in the corners but stopping down a
bit will cure this. Optimim performance is around f/22. A 12&amp;rdquo; Artar will
just barely cover 8x10 at infinity, coverage angle is usually given as
47deg for this type, but my 12&amp;rdquo; Artar which is older than yours does
just fine and is one of the sharpest lenses I&amp;rsquo;ve ever used. There is
just no margin for movements. .&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They are famous lenses. The C.P.Goerz-American Optical Co. was
originally the U.S. division of the German Goerz company which was
important before the first world war. After the war the German parent
was restricted in what it could make (by the German government) and in
about 1926 was absorbed into the Zeiss-Ikon combine. The American
division became an independant company and continued to manufacture the
Goerz line. Goerz was the manufacturer of the famous Dagor lens. The
designer of the Dagor, Emile von Hoegh, brought a second lens design to
Goerz, a four element air-spaced type sometimes called a &amp;ldquo;dialyte&amp;rdquo;. This
became the basis for several Goerz lenses including the Artar. The Artar
was designed by W. Zschokke and F.Urban in the late teens. It is an
apochromatic lens originally intended for three-color graphic arts use.
Goerz continued to make Dagors and Artars in the US gradually refining
the designs. The Red Dot series of Artars came out in the early 1950&amp;rsquo;s.
They are an improved version of the older Artar and are coated. These
lenses, although intended for close work, do very well at infinity. They
are extremely sharp and generally have excellent performance. The
original Artars were adjusted for best performance at 1:1 but the Red
Dot series were adjusted for better performance at a distance and the
image/object ratios vatied from about 10:1 to 1:1 depending on focal
length and when it was made. Artar&amp;rsquo;s cover a rather narrower field than
a Tessar and your 9.5 should cover a 5x7. The field does not increase
when the lens is stopped down. Optimum f: stop is f:22 This is a super
lens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Red Dots are apochromatic, they are also coated. The Artar was the most
widely used process lens for decades. They were also widely used for
color advertising work. Red Dot Artars in shutters are optimised for
medium distance rather than 1:1 and should be just fine at infinity. I
have a 19&amp;rdquo; Red Dot in a barrel and an old 12&amp;rdquo; Apo Artar in a dial set
Compur. They are both extremely sharp lenses. Artars in shutters are
rather more expensive than in barrels. My 19&amp;rdquo; in barrel cost \$225 but
that was a rather low price for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coverage is limited to about 47 degrees at f/22. This works out to an
image circle of 210mm for your 9.5&amp;rdquo; lens. This will just cover 5x7 with
no movements so it will allow moderate though not extreme movements on
4x5. Unlike most modern lenses, the illuminated circle is larger than
the sharp image circle, so you need to take some care that you don&amp;rsquo;t
exceed the coverage of the lens accidentally. &lt;strong&gt;John Sparks.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;on-goerz-serial-numbers-and-dates&#34;&gt;On Goerz Serial numbers and dates&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;Goerz Amer. Optical Co. Serial #&#39;s from 
Eddie Bolsetzian (former Goerz Tech.)

Lens #

70001-140935     1902-1903
150000-190170    1903-1905
200941-224267    1906-1908
223775-226630    1908-1909
310001-315734    1911-1914
315735-320000    1914-1918
751240-756909    1927-1937
755300                1934
756910-765730    1937-1945
765730-771199    1945-1948
771200-780169    1948-1954
791500                ~1955
ser iii 61/2 #222788    1910
ser iii 81/4  #222836   1907
14&amp;quot; Dagor #190994       1905
19&amp;quot; dagor #757427       1938
ser iii 480mm #174429   1904
Artar 19&amp;quot; #396635       1922
artar 30&amp;quot; #751030       1926
first red dot artar #779612  oct 1953
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are the dates passed to me, I make no claims about their accuracy.
&lt;strong&gt;Michael Buchmeier&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;on-dagor-history&#34;&gt;On Dagor History&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have Goerz American Optical Co.catalogue copies from
1913,1938,1955,1963,1968, and 1971 all of which list dagor lenses. The
W.A.Dagor is listed first in the 1938 and golden dagor (both W.A. and
standard) in 1955. in around 1964 the company changed their name to
Goerz Optical Co. Inc. From the illustrations in the catalogs the golden
dagor was of the &amp;ldquo;gold dot&amp;rdquo; configuration by 1963 but is still referred
to in the catalog as the &amp;ldquo;GOLDEN DAGOR&amp;rdquo; right up to and including the
1971 spec. sheet. Gold Rim and Gold Dot are apparently only useful
descriptive terms to describe the appearance of these lenses but may
only represent an evolution in trim much like a chrome bbl vs a black
bbl convertible Symmar. Goerz did not use these terms in their sales
literature! Goerz was bought out first by Kollmorgen in 1971 and listed
a Pittsburgh address, and was subsequently bought by Schneider in
1972(?). The 355mm Kern Dagors were produced in two lots after that, but
Schneider did sell out existing Goerz inventory after the buyout, and in
fact a few American made 14&amp;rdquo; gold dot lenses are around with Schneider&amp;rsquo;s
name on them. These are in Copal Shutters, marked in inches, and are not
multicoated, but are fine lenses nevertheless. &lt;strong&gt;Michael Buchmeier.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;coverage-of-dagor&#34;&gt;Coverage of Dagor&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For many years Bausch and Lomb were licensed by Zeiss to make Zeiss
lenses in the US. Comparing the catalogue specs for Tessars one finds a
full plate size difference between the catalogues for the same focal
length and speed. i.e. a 12&amp;rdquo; f&amp;rdquo;4.5 series 1C is listed as covering an
8x10 by B&amp;amp;L but only 6-&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; X 8-&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; by Zeiss. However Zeiss gives the
coverage for &amp;ldquo;small stops&amp;rdquo; as 14-&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;&amp;rdquo; circle. So Zeiss is giving plate
size for good image quality with the lenses wide open and B&amp;amp;L for
smaller stops where the corners get better. I think this explains the
difference in the ratings by the two companies, Zeiss was just a little
more honest about what the lenses would do. There is a difference in the
circle of illumination and the circle of good defininition with most
lenses, the circle of illumination being often much larger. The circle
of illumination of a Dagor or similar lens is about as large with the
lens wide open as it is stopped down but the sharpness of the periphery
of the image isn&amp;rsquo;t very good, this area gets lots sharper as you stop
down. To contrast, &amp;ldquo;dialyte&amp;rdquo; lenses, like Artars and Dogmars are pretty
sharp to the edges of the image wide open and the coverage (which is
limited) doesn&amp;rsquo;t get larger as the lens is stopped down. Triplets and
Tessars are midway between these. Generally, older wide angle designs (
and the Dagor really is a wide angle lens) perform best at rather small
stops. Its considered good optical design practice to vignette the
illumination circle of a lens bewond the point of good performance, (see
_Modern Lens Design_ by Warren Smith or Kingslake&amp;rsquo;s design books), so
thhis _may_ account for smaller coverage angle in some late versions
of old lenses but you would have to derermine is by actual measurement.
Both my Dagors are very old and both have the advertised coverage, but I
have no good way to measure the quality of the image at the limit of
coverage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;on-dagor-performance&#34;&gt;On Dagor performance&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is some data from bench testing a lens, &amp;ldquo;Goerz Dagor Focus 7in.
f/6.8, No. 392662.&amp;rdquo; This lens was produced sometime between 1918 and
1927 (thanks, Mike Buchmeir). If this old lens is representative of
others from that time, here is some advice: the spacing is critical, and
also, the orientation of one cell relative to the other. (Turning one
cell a full turn changes the off-axis resolution by a factor of two and
back again. It seems that the optical-centering-error reputation is
deserved.) This Dagor shows very little difference in focal length
(perhaps .2 mm) wide open compared to the small apertures. Vignetting
for 5x7 looks like about a stop&amp;rsquo;s worth at f/16. If you have an old lens
you would like tested, let me know (no charge, you pay postage). I&amp;rsquo;d be
interested in seeing how other early lenses perform. Also, can anyone
post performance data of any modern lenses&amp;ndash; to show us what the
improvements in resolution and coverage have been? Now, here&amp;rsquo;s the bench
test data (considering all the caveats, not too shabby! ;-)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;angle
off-axis  0    5   10   15   20   25   30   35   40  degrees

f/6.8    85   75   65   55   45   35   25    5    0  lines/mm

f/22     70   70   70   70   65   55   40   10    0  lines/mm
         ^diffraction lim^

f/64     30   30   30   30   25   25   25   20   10  lines/mm
         ^diffraction lim^
Corners of the film with this 7&amp;quot; lens are at:    4x5: 24 degrees
                                                 5x7: 31 degrees
                                                8x10: 42 degrees

The astigmatism correction, done well in Dagors for the first time in
history, is interesting :

(table values are the difference in mm from the on-axis focal
distance, positive away from the lens)

angle
off-axis  0    5   10   15   20   25   30   35   40  degrees

sagittal
focus     0    0  -.2  -.5  -.5    0  +.8  +3.0

tangential
focus     0    0    0  +.2  +.3  +.2  -.8  -2.5
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Larry Whatley&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;b-l-5x7-tessar&#34;&gt;B&amp;amp;L 5x7 Tessar&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;gt;Here&#39;s a surprise-- this old lens is surprisingly bad... and will
&amp;gt;probably make surprisingly good pictures!  (Can anyone tell me
&amp;gt;specifically about this &amp;quot;5x7 Bausch - Lomb Tessar Series 1c Pat. Feb24
&amp;gt;1903 No 2448486&amp;quot;?)
&amp;gt;
&amp;gt;It has a field about the same as a Dagor (!) because the astigmatism
&amp;gt;corrections are stretched out to cover more than 60 degrees, even wide
&amp;gt;open.  The problem is that the resolution falls to 5 or 10 lines/mm for
&amp;gt;about half the field for the wider apertures.  (One authority on fine
&amp;gt;print resolution says a resolution of 12 lpmm in the _print_ is
&amp;gt;considered to be truly &amp;quot;fine,&amp;quot; by the way.)
&amp;gt;
&amp;gt;But... at apertures of f/22 and 32 this lens will cover its entire
&amp;gt;plate with resolution of 40 lines/mm or greater-- it sharpens up very
&amp;gt;nicely.  Perhaps this old lens was designed on purpose this way to
&amp;gt;cover this wide field angle, unusual for most tessars, with the fast
&amp;gt;aperture intended just for focusing, not taking?
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have one of these, it was on an old Agfa/Ansco view camera but is much
older than the camera. Mine is S/nr. 3050646. It makes very sharp
images. My guess as to date is based on the following clues: 1, It is a
B&amp;amp;L not a B&amp;amp;L-Zeiss, makes it probably after the entry of the US in WW-1
(1914). 2, In 1927 the patent law was changed to require the actual
patent numbers rather than just the date to written on products, makes
the lens before 1927. 3, Patents are good for 17 years, 1903 + 17 =
1920. B&amp;amp;L may have continued to print the date on the lens rings after
this. B&amp;amp;L was engaged in war production after 1914, they had the only
credible optical glass factory in the US so got very busy. Best guess as
to date therefore is 1918 to 1920. (Watch someone blow this closely
reasoned argument to smithereens:-)) Mine is in a Wollensak Optimo
shutter with marked speeds to &lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;300&lt;/sub&gt; sec. This is an interesting shutter
in which the shutter blades are double sided and turn through a complete
180deg when its tripped. When tripped again, they return. This permitted
higher speeds than the usual oscillating blade variety but the
effeciency at higher speeds wasn&amp;rsquo;t too good, so the &lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;300&lt;/sub&gt; may have been
ligit for effective spped with the lens wide open when the thing was
new. It makes about 1/50th now. This shutter dates from about the same
period. This lens positivly amazed me when I first used it. Please note
that even though its marked 5x7 the focal length is a little on the
short side, about 180mm. It would be interesting to test more than one
example to see if what you found is characteristic of the type or just
an individual lens. It seems to me that B&amp;amp;L had some patents for
modified Tessars themselves but I don&amp;rsquo;t remember the dates. 1903 is the
date of the Rudolph patent for the Tessar in the US.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;xenars-and-other-tessars&#34;&gt;Xenars and Other Tessars&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Xenars are great lenses, in the newer smaller size the will preform
wonderfully on a press type camera. Older 210mm and above Xenars come in
f/4.5 and get large and heavy. I have a 210 f/4.5 which is an excellent
lens, but in a #3 shutter it is too heavy for a graflex and at slow
speeds induces &amp;ldquo;shutter shake&amp;rdquo;. All tessar type lenses should be used at
f/11 or smaller. This is not really a problem since most sources suggest
using any lens at two stops down from wide open (symmars f/5.6 = f/11).
A real problem is cost. If the Xenars are new they cost apx. what USED
Symmar/Sironar/Nikon/Fuji etc. 6 element designs cost. The older chrome
Symmars are generally a good buy used (as is most non multi-coated
ventage glass). Just check out the lens and shutter. However, at 300mm
you are back to a #3 shutter. At 300mm the new Xenar may be the best
choice for you or you may want to look at a used Apo Rronar as they come
in a #1 shutter. The Ektars are generally great lenses, if &amp;hellip; a good
shutter can be found. I am rather fond of the 203 Ektar, not a tessar
type, rather an air spaced design (like artar). Some Ektars can be found
in compur shutters&amp;hellip; this is good stuff, later ventage. Ektar coatings
can be soft though. &lt;strong&gt;Reynolds Neely&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;f4-5-480mm-voigtlander-heliar&#34;&gt;f4.5 480mm Voigtlander HELIAR&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This enormous chunk of glass is one of the classic lens types. The
Heliar was designed originally by Hans Harting of Voigtlander about 1900
although the version made later is a modification of the orginal with
the order of the cemented elements reversed. This is a five element lens
with the outer elements cemented. Kingslake classifies it as a variation
of the triplet. Heliars had a reputation for being deluxe lenses with
excellent performance. The coverage angle is somewhat limited compared
to the simpler Tessar, usually given as 46deg. Heliars were made for
probably about 70 years with design changes periodically. Unfortunately,
I don&amp;rsquo;t have any Voigtlander serial number infomation to help date this
one. More about this lens and its designer may be found in: _A History
of the Photographic Lens_ Rudolph Kingslake, 1989, San Diego, The
Academic Press Inc. Still in print.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;more-information&#34;&gt;More information&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.hevanet.com/cperez/cameras/ektar_list.html&#34;&gt;In praise of Kodak
lenses&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.greenspun.com/com/qtluong/photography/lf/classic-experts.html&#34;&gt;View or add
comments&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>http://lflf.surge.sh/equipment/comparison/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lflf.surge.sh/equipment/comparison/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Large Format Photography: 4x5 Cameras - some comparisons&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;4x5-cameras-some-comparisons&#34;&gt;4x5 Cameras : some comparisons&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Compiled by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.terragalleria.com/&#34;&gt;Q.-Tuan Luong&lt;/a&gt; for &lt;a href=&#34;.&#34;&gt;the
Large Format Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Contents:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#double-vs-triple&#34;&gt;Double extension vs Triple extension flatbeds&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#zone-vs-wisner-vs-canham&#34;&gt;Zone VI vs Wisner vs Canham&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#technika-vs-graphic&#34;&gt;Technika vs Graphic&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#technika-vs-toyo&#34;&gt;Technika vs Toyo&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#sinar-vs-arca&#34;&gt;Sinar vs Arca-Swiss&lt;/a&gt; &lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;01&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[]{#double-vs-triple}&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;double-extension-vs-triple-extension-flatbeds&#34;&gt;Double extension vs Triple extension flatbeds&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;By &lt;a href=&#34;mailto:sparks@col.hp.com&#34;&gt;John Sparks&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In deciding which camera to get, the tradeoffs are cost/weight vs
ability to use longer and shorter lens, and more rigidity. I think, for
example, the Tachihara is about 3 lbs vs 6 for the Wisner/Zone VI. With
the Tachihara you can&amp;rsquo;t really use lenses shorter than 90mm (and 90mm
might be tough) because of no bag bellows. On the other end, you are
limited to long lenses of about 210mm or a 360mm telephoto where the
Wisner/Zone VI easily takes a 360mm normal lens or a 500mm telephoto
(the Wisner Technical camera for even more money will take a 450mm
normal lens). You can use a 210mm lens at 1:1 on the Wisner/Zone VI, but
the longest lens you can use at 1:1 is a 150mm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Wisner/Zone VI camera are very rigid for field cameras, the smaller,
lighter camera have a good bit of movement in the standards even with
everything locked down tight. This will affect the amount of wind you
can tolerate. Even with a 210mm with a good extension, the smaller
cameras will be pretty unstable with all that bellows exposed. Also the
double extension of the small cameras means that the lens is extended
way out in front of the tripod mount and the camera is kind of front
heavy, while the triple extension of the Wisner allows the lens and film
plane to be extended equally from the center section with tripod mount
for a more balanced camera.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Think about the range of lenses you own and/or plan to purchase. If you
will be happy with a range from 120mm to 210mm (with possibly a 90mm
with limited movements and a 360mm telephoto) then the smaller cameras
may be acceptable. If you use longer lenses you will probably want a
Wisner. If you use mostly really short lenses (58mm to 75mm), you
probably really want to stick to a monorail, but otherwise you really
need at least a bag bellows so the smaller field cameras are not an
option.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[]{#zone-vs-wisner-vs-canham}&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;zone-vi-vs-wisner-vs-canham&#34;&gt;Zone VI vs Wisner vs Canham&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;By &lt;a href=&#34;mailto:sparks@col.hp.com&#34;&gt;John Sparks&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have a Wisner Technical and used to own a Zone VI (I&amp;rsquo;ve also compared
the Zone VI to a Wisner Traditional that a friend bought). The Wisner
Traditional and Zone VI cameras are almost identical cameras, but the
Wisner is put together better. In the case of the Wisner Traditional vs
the Zone VI, almost the only difference is the build quality (the
leather bellows on the Wisner is somewhat more flexable allowing more
movements with short lenses without the bag). Not too many things that
can be described, but in a direct comparison of the two cameras, the
better quality of the Wisner does come across fairly clearly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are a few subtle differences. The Wisner has slightly more
extension (maybe &lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;&amp;rdquo;). The opening in the front standard is bigger on
the Wisner. You can mount a Nikkor 120mm SW lens on the Wisner, but it
won&amp;rsquo;t fit through the opening in the front of the bellows of the Zone VI
(I think this is the only lens that can be used on this camera where
this is a problem, a f/5.6 360mm standard lens might have the same
problem, but it&amp;rsquo;s not likely to be a lens used on this camera). The
ground glass frame on the Zone VI has &lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;8&lt;/sub&gt;&amp;rdquo; to &lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;&amp;rdquo; of play from side to
side and up and down (this doesn&amp;rsquo;t effect the position of the film
plane, but does make precise framing of the image impossible. The
position of the ground glass in my Zone VI differed from the film
location by almost 1mm! This was enough that my negatives from the
Wisner were noticably sharper! I don&amp;rsquo;t know how common that problem is
with the Zone VI. I didn&amp;rsquo;t discover this until I tried a different
camera and had some transpariencies of the same subject with both
cameras and the ones from the Zone VI were noticably less sharp with the
naked eye than the other transparencies. These transparencies were some
copywork of flat subjects at relatively large aperatures for large
format, I can&amp;rsquo;t say that I ever really saw it in more typical subjects
though there were a couple of negatives that I thought I&amp;rsquo;d just screwed
up focus but may have been the camera. I don&amp;rsquo;t know if this is a common
problem with Zone VI cameras (I don&amp;rsquo;t really think so) and could have
been fixed with either shimming or sanding the ground glass frame (I
can&amp;rsquo;t remember which direction the focus was off). I did remember
getting a Picker newsletter where he talks about focus/film inaccuracies
in cameras like SLR&amp;rsquo;s and said it couldn&amp;rsquo;t be a problem with a view
camera because there is no mirror. Whether Picker just didn&amp;rsquo;t know
better or didn&amp;rsquo;t want people testing their Zone VI cameras, I have no
idea, but neither one is a good recommendation on the accuracy of the
ground glass poisition in his cameras. The ground glass position on the
Wisner is very accurate. The Zone VI has a bail on the ground glass that
makes inserting holders easier without moving the camera (mine was
before they added this, but new Zone VI&amp;rsquo;s have this). The finish on the
camera and brass seems to be more durable on the Wisner. The fit of all
the parts is much more precise on the Wisners. Since the Wisner
Traditional and Zone VI cameras are basicly the same price new, I don&amp;rsquo;t
think there is any reason to buy a new Zone VI camera. There are many
more Zone VI cameras available used and sell for lower prices than
Wisners. As a used camera in the \$600-\$800 range, a Zone VI is a good
deal, but make sure you check the focus position.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Wisner Traditional is bulkier (when closed, it&amp;rsquo;s probably 1&amp;rdquo; thicker
than the others) and heavier (about &lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; lb) than the other two. The
bellows extension is about 3&amp;rdquo; longer than the others. This allows a
450mm lens to be easily used (I think a 450mm could be used on the
Traditional, but only near infinity). I find the rear rise to be
margionally useful and would prefer not to have it (I think the back is
not as rigid with it as it would be without it). All three of the
cameras are rigid enough that this is really an issue. The geared rear
tilt makes focusing quite a bit quicker and easier, but doesn&amp;rsquo;t offer
any benifits besides speed (you can get the back of the Traditional in
exactly the same position relative to the lens as on the Technical, it
just takes slightly longer).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These cameras are excellent for use with 120mm through 360mm on the
Traditional/Zone VI and 120mm through 450mm on the Technical. You can
use shorter lenses, but you have to move the lens closer to the film
than you can get with both standards vertical (you use the front base
tilt to move the lens back and the front axis tilt to straighten the
lens). The consequence of this is front rise/fall requires refocusing. I
believe you can focus even a 58mm or 47mm lens using this technique with
a bag bellows. Since 120mm is the shortest lens I own, I haven&amp;rsquo;t cared
very much (I&amp;rsquo;m mostly in to long lenses and mostly use 210mm to 450mm
lenses on 4x5).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are a great user of extreme wide angle lenses, you might prefer
the Canham camera. It&amp;rsquo;s really a 5x7 camera with a reducing back so it&amp;rsquo;s
larger than the others (though about the same thickness as the Wisner
Technical; it weighs the same as well). The rear standard slides forward
on metal rails so it can focus a 58mm with both standards vertical. It
doesn&amp;rsquo;t have very much front rise, so this somewhat negates this
advantage at least for architectual photography (you can get more rise
by pointing the whole camera up and returning both standards to
vertical). I don&amp;rsquo;t think it&amp;rsquo;s quite as rigid at full extension as a
Wisner Technical, but it does have 3&amp;rdquo; more extension (enough for a 600mm
for very distant subjects). The focus track on the Canham is aluminum
instead of the brass on the others and the focus is not as smooth. I
find the lever locks of the Canham awkward in comparison to the Wisner
and sometimes pinch my fingers with them (I have an 8x10 Canham). The
Canham is quite a bit more expensive than the others, but in line with
the Wisner 5x7 cameras. You can also always get a 5x7 back (or 4x10) if
you want a bigger negative in the future. The 4x5 Wisners can be changed
to a 5x7 or 4x10 back as well, but I think the 5x7 is horizontal only
and the Wisner 4x10 uses only Mido 4x10 holders that lots of people seem
to have trouble with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[]{#technika-vs-graphic}&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;technika-vs-graphic&#34;&gt;Technika vs Graphic&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;By &lt;a href=&#34;mailto:klotz@adoc.xerox.com&#34;&gt;Leigh L Klotz Jr&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Linhof&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;is much more expensive&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;is better built&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;has more movements and extension&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;is heavier&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;old lenses often come with cams&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;you can get any lens &amp;ldquo;cammed&amp;rdquo; by Linhof&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;is still supported by Linhof&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Graphic&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;inexpensive&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;rugged, but not as well-built as the Linhof&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;has adequate movements for many needs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;no lightweight, but weights less than the Linhof&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;only the Super Graphic has cammed lenses&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cams for new lenses not available (yet)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;is supported by a network of suppliers with old parts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;By &lt;a href=&#34;mailto:congreve@aol.com&#34;&gt;Alan Heldman&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I placed my Linhof Technika IV, and my Speed Graphic (side-mount Kalart;
I don&amp;rsquo;t obsess on model names, not metalbodied) consecutively on a
granite surface plate and employed a high quality dial test indicator
readable to about one-fifth of one thousandth of an inch, and performed
three tests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Test #1: flex, in thousanths of an inch (&amp;ldquo;thou&amp;rdquo;) , between the camera
bed pressed down onto the granite plate, and the top front edge of the
camera body, (a) with forward pressure from my finger, at the top rear
of the camera body, in one direction, approximating one pound of force.
(b) with back tension, at the same point, measured with a spring scale,
of eight pounds&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Test #2: forward flex, in thous, of the front standard or lens board,
measured at its upper edge, when racked out to the proper point for a
150mm lens at infinity, with pressure from my finger, at the top center
of the lens board, in one direction, approximating one pound of force.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;RESULTS:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Test #1 (a) Linhof flex one-half of one thou (0.0005 inch) Graphic
&amp;ldquo;&amp;rdquo; eight thou&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Test #1(b) Linhof flex four thou Graphic &amp;ldquo; thirty thou&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Test#2 Linhof flex seven thou Graphic &amp;ldquo; twenty thou&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[]{#technika-vs-toyo}&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;technika-vs-toyo&#34;&gt;Technika vs Toyo&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;By &lt;a href=&#34;mailto:postmaster@topshooters.com&#34;&gt;Meefter Pahnowt&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you go wider than 72mm, the Technika bed drops away more easily and
the 55/58/65 can be shoved into the box for an acceptable infinity. Yes,
the back movements are better, but other than rear tilt which is
available on both, who among us use sophisticated back movements in the
field? Toyo&amp;rsquo;s larger 158mm standard makes for MUCH easier use of WA
recessed boards, and allow you to use a &lt;sup&gt;72&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;75&lt;/sub&gt; along the geared rail for
finer control of focus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why a Toyo 45A-II over a Technika IV? Sturdier bellows, bigger easier to
handle knobs (a must for shooting in low light or weather),
interchangeable bellows, an accordion style WA bellows, deeper (38mm)
and bigger (158mm sq.) recessed lensboards (ever tried threading a cable
into a #1 shutter in a technika recessed board?), binocular reflex hood
(ease of use in viewing perspective effects and depth during coarse
composition plus the obviation of need for a darkcloth and the setup
involved), plus the fact that it&amp;rsquo;s current, so all accessories are
available and repairs are easy to access. Summary: Faster, tighter,
versatile enough and it&amp;rsquo;s current.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the Tech IV side, it&amp;rsquo;s way cheaper, and has longer extension which is
better for using a 360mm telephoto with some amount of image control.
And I use the Linhof Multifocus finder more than I&amp;rsquo;d expetced I would,
but on my Toyo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;By &lt;a href=&#34;mailto:sparks@col.hp.com&#34;&gt;John Sparks&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I find the toyo field cameras extremely limiting because of their short
bellows. The 4x5 won&amp;rsquo;t handle the 450mm that I regularly use and have
difficulty with even a 300mm (my most used lens on 4x5). The 8x10 won&amp;rsquo;t
handle the 600mm that is my second most commonly used lens. They are
very sturdy cameras, but in my opinion, too heavy for their extremely
limited bellows extension. Technicas have a very useful 4&amp;rdquo; more
extension (plenty for a 300mm though still not enough for a 450mm
without mounting the lens on a 2&amp;rdquo; extended lensboard).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;By &lt;a href=&#34;mailto:chauth@ix.netcom.com&#34;&gt;Chauth&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before the Toyo experience I had played around with a Wisner Technical.
It&amp;rsquo;s a nicely made piece of work but too delicate IMO. Rigidity was
something I was looking for and comparing the two I thought the Toyo
might fit my needs. After the first day using the Toyo I thought this
might be the camera I would invest in. On the second day of the rental
my wife and I were at Shore Acres on the Oregon Coast and ran into a guy
using a Linhof Master Technika. He was very gracious and helpful and let
me play around with it for awhile. After a few minutes I realized that
the Toyo wasn&amp;rsquo;t nearly as rigid as I thought. The extra movements,
bellows legnth, rigidity and quality of the Linhof blows the Toyo away.
It&amp;rsquo;s an amzing piece of work. Needless to say the Linhof was my choice.
Yes, I know the prices for the Linhofs can be astronomical. For what I
paid for a used one I could have purchased a new Toyo body and maybe a
lens or two. I&amp;rsquo;m not a rich man, I&amp;rsquo;m a teacher with two kids in school,
but I know quality and a good investment when I see it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[]{#sinar-vs-arca}&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-comparison-of-the-sinar-f1-f2-and-the-arca-swiss-f-cameras&#34;&gt;A comparison of the Sinar F1/F2 and the Arca-Swiss F cameras&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;by &lt;a href=&#34;mailto:evphoto@insync.net&#34;&gt;Ellis Vener&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have owned an Arca Swiss F camera for nearly six years and recently
considered switching it out for a Sinar F camera system that I was
offered a great deal on. Previous to acquiring the Arca my view camera
was a Sinar C.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;similarities&#34;&gt;Similarities&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Both are base-tilt yaw free designs. Basically this means that if
you incline the monorail and tilt the standards back to vertical and
then have to swing either the standards the standards stay vertical.
This makes life much simpler and limits the time you spend setting
up the camera. Not all base tilt cameras are yaw free.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Both are extremely modular systems that you can expand as your needs
grow.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Both have superb handling characteristics with wide angle lenses.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;differences&#34;&gt;Differences&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Arca has the rise/fall movements (this is the movement most
often used with a view camera) abovethe tilt and swing mechanism, in
the plane of the standard. With the Sinar the rise/fall movements is
located below the tilt/swing axis. In practical terms this means
that with the Arca Swiss there is less refocusing to do.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Sinar has a built-in depth of field (hyper focal distance)
calculator and also a tilt swing calculator built-in. The Arca does
not. This is handy especially for beginners.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Arca function carrier (this is the mechanism that drives the
standards back and forth along the monorail and which also contains
the tilt and swing mechanisms) is designed to carry up to an 8x10
back so it is much stronger than the comparable mechanism on the
Sinar.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The swing and horizontal shift locks on the Arca are segregated.
This is not the case with the Sinar F1 (but is the case with the
Sinar F2).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The standard Arca lensboard is designed to put the nodal point of
the lens directly in the lens plane. This isn&amp;rsquo;t the case with the
Sinar. Also with a standard Arca board you can use super wide angle
lenses like the 47mm XL Super Angulon without having to resort to
recessed lens boards.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Sinar uses a tubular monorail that rotates in the tripod mount.
This makes the camera easier to level to the horizonal . The Arca
Swiss uses a different monorail design which requires the user to
level the tripod head to level the horizonal orientation . To add
extention to the Sinar you simply screw on a new extention rail. The
ArcaSwiss uses two basic monorails of different lengths: The rail
used on the FC folds in half and attaches to the Triod via a short
(85mm) length tripod block. This block can be moved the length of
the monorail. The standard F-line design (aka The F-line Classic)
uses a full length optical bench which fits directly into the
open-ended Arca-Swiss quick release clamp. In the top of the optical
bench are two monorail sections. My camera came with a 40cm optical
bench and I have found that I can spread the two sections apart and
get an extra 20cm of length without need for an extention rail. The
standard Arca bellows is 38cm so to get full use of that length I&amp;rsquo;d
need to get either an intermediate standard and function carrier and
a second bellows or an extra long (70cm) bellows.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Because of the design of the Tripod mount and rise/fall posts that
are located below the standard the Sinar is a bulkier camera.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Arca Swiss has a bright screen / fresnel lens built-in to the
groundglass design. With the Sinar, as with all 4x5 cameras, this is
a (in my experience) necessary accessory.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The lens board and bellows for the Sinar are smaller than those of
the Arca.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In the United States at least, Sinar has an extensive distribution
system and there are a lot of used Sinars out there. Arca has a
small core of dealers and used current models (the F &amp;amp; the big
studio based M series) are scarce.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.greenspun.com/com/qtluong/photography/lf/comparison.html&#34;&gt;View or add
comments&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>http://lflf.surge.sh/equipment/filters/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lflf.surge.sh/equipment/filters/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h2 id=&#34;filters-for-large-format-photography&#34;&gt;Filters for Large Format Photography&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;By &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.terragalleria.com/&#34;&gt;Q.-Tuan Luong&lt;/a&gt; for the &lt;a href=&#34;.&#34;&gt;Large
Format Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Summary: a market survey and collection of tips on filters from the
perspective of the large format photographer, including rear mounted
filters, center filters, polarizers, and rectangular filter systems.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;attaching-filters-at-the-rear-of-the-lens&#34;&gt;Attaching filters at the rear of the lens&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With LF, you have the option to attach filters at the rear of the lens.
This works for color correction filters which don&amp;rsquo;t need to be adjusted.
The advantage is that a filter inside the camera is less likely to get
dust, dirt, smudges, fingerprints, and will cause less flare.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are two precautions to take:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You have to be super careful to keep your filter clean. Any dust,
dirt, smudges, fingerprints, as well as defects, will have more of a
detrimental effect on the quality of the image as the light passing
through the imperfections has already passed through the lens.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A filter mounted behind the lens creates a focus shift equal to
1/3rd the thickness of the filter so all focusing must be done with
the filter in place, except for gels, whose thickness is
neglectible.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;center-filter&#34;&gt;Center filter&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;principles&#34;&gt;Principles&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For most lenses, the illumination will go as cos\^4 theta where theta is
the angle between the center of the lens and the image point on the
film. This is called &lt;em&gt;Light fall-off&lt;/em&gt;. It&amp;rsquo;s basically the result of the
law of optics. For wide-angle lenses, this can result in the corners
being two or three stops darker than the center.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two powers come from the light traveling a greater distance and the
inverse square law, one power comes from the exit pupil of the lens
being tilted and looking like an ellipse rather than the full circe,
another power comes from the rays striking the film at an angle [the
same reason for winter: the sun&amp;rsquo;s rays strike the earth at an increased
angle]. The best aperture re light fall-off is any aperture more than
about 2 stops (maybe 3) down from wide open. Further stopping down
should not change the relative illumination, center to corners. This is
well explained in the book Applied Photographic Optics by Sidney F. Ray,
published by the Focal Press. Excellent but rather expensive. It is a
big book, more than 500 pages. &lt;strong&gt;Michael Briggs&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is different from vignetting, caused by mechanical obstruction. At
wide apertures, lenses will vignete because the glass elements aren&amp;rsquo;t
big enough (if they were made larger, the lens would be more expensive
and heavier).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most wideangle lenses from SLR cameras are retrofocus (retro-telephoto)
designs, meaning that the nodal point is somewhere towards the front of
the lens, in some cases in front of the lens. This is necessary so that
the lens does not protrude into the mirror box area. Retrofocus designs
decrease fall-off, which is why those lenses don&amp;rsquo;t require a center
filter. On the other hand, Mamiya suggests a center filter for their
43mm M7 lens, which has the distinction of being symmetrical thanks to
the RF camera. I don&amp;rsquo;t know of a retrofocus lens for LF. Retrofocus
designs are asymmetric and require floating elements for good
performance at close range.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The center filter is a simple solution to the light fall-off problem. It
is darker in the center and gradually brighter at the edges. Center
filters always are mounted in front. They must be screwed directly into
the lens without using a step up ring, so you need one per filter size
of lens. This is because center filters are designed to be used a
certain distance from the lens. You need to remember that it can not be
seen by the film until the lens has been stopped down at least 2 stops.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;do-i-need-one&#34;&gt;Do I need one ?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The wider the lens, the more of the full coverage of the lens you use
(ie using 5x7 with a 110mm vs using 4x5, or using 8x10 with the 150mm vs
using 4x5 with a plasmat &lt;sup&gt;150&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;5&lt;/sub&gt;.6 ), or the more movements you make, the
worse the effect. Most people find that light fall-off is neglectible
unless you start using a 90mm on 4x5. Even though, few shooters would
use a CF at 90mm on 4x5. On the other hand, most find it necessary at
90mm on 5x7 or at 58mm on 4x5.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whether you feel the need for correction is an esthetic decision. Some
people actually like the fall-off. It&amp;rsquo;s less noticeable for dark scenes
than for bright scenes. It&amp;rsquo;s less noticeable if your scene has dark
areas in the corners (like trees). For landscapes, it is most noticable
in skys and tends to pull the eye toward the center. It seems to be more
bothersome in interiors, particularly white walls.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the more even image, you pay quite a price. Not only these filters
tend to be expensive, they eat at least two f-stops and add complexity
to calculating exposures. Since they are mounted directly on the lens,
and have larger front elements (for example a 67 center filter has an
outer threading of 86mm) they can make difficult to use of other filters
without vignetting. You could correct for the fall off in the darkroom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;which-density-and-brand-to-use&#34;&gt;Which density and brand to use ?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The filters are not matched to a particular lens, so at least you can
interchange them between two lenses if they have the same filter size.
The difference between having a CF and not having one is quite relative
(some photographers are happy without, while some think that they are
necessary), thus you&amp;rsquo;d guess the difference between two different brands
is extremely subtle. Center filters are made by B+W/Schneider, Heliopan,
Rodenstock, Hoya and Fuji. Prices can vary considerably depending where
you buy them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;rdquo; We stock some of the denser Heliopan CF and have sold virtually none.
You would lose so much light (3 stops) + you must stop a lens down at
least 2 stops for the filter to work that the denser version is not too
useable for most people. Virtually every CF sold is either .40
(Rodenstock) or .45 (Heliopan and others). I don&amp;rsquo;t think you will find
many people, if any, who have actually used all 3 [B+W/Schneider,
Heliopan, Rodenstocks] on the same lens with the same film at the same
time [and can compare them]. We are in a unique position. We are the
Heliopan and the Rodenstock importer and also the Linhof importer. As
such we import the Heliopan and Rodenstock ceter filters as well as
Schneider ones for the 58 through 90mm XL lenses we sell. An extremely
knowlgeable photographer named Lief Erickson (tragically died too early)
too had this question. So he took the Linhof Technorama 617 and the old
Fuji 617 with a Schneider, Rodenstock and heliopan center filter for a
test. He found no difference on film between them. However that was
before Rodenstock redesigned their center filters. No center filter is
totally neutral. They tend to shift torwards green under cetain
conditions. The latest version of the Rodenstock ones are the most
neutral of all center filters. &amp;ldquo; &lt;strong&gt;Bob Salomon&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;polarizer&#34;&gt;Polarizer&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main point of using a circular polarizer instead of a linear
polarizer is to ensure that autofocus and TTL metering would work
properly with your reflex camera (although this might not always be
necessary). If you intend to use your polarizer also on a reflex camera,
it&amp;rsquo;s probably safer to get the circular variety. Since a LF camera has
no mirror, you can use either a linear or a circular polarizer on your
LF camera. Linear polarizers are cheaper, and some people think they are
better at removing reflections than circular polarizers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A Kaeseman polarizer is sealed, and therefore more durable (the foil on
other polarizers tends to degrade over time). It is also said they are
better at removing reflections.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To avoid vignetting, you can use a slim polarizer (no threads for a
clip-on lens cap or an additional filter), or a wide-angle polarizer
which has a larger front element.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many polarizers tend to have a cold color bias. It&amp;rsquo;s generally better to
have a warm color bias than a cold color bias, hence the interest of the
warm tone polarizers. In a C&amp;amp;D article, Englander compared ten linear
and circular polarizers. His densitometer readings are
(total,red,green,blue):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt; Wratten  (.6,.62,.62,.62)
 B+W Warm  (.56,.57,.57,.58)
 B+W circular  (.51,.55,.52,.48)
 Heliopan circular  (.58,.64,.58,.53)
 Heliopan linear  (.62,.69,.63,.57) 
 Heliopan Warm  (.60,.60,.61,.56)
 Tiffen linear  (.50,.52,.49,.50)
 Tiffen circular  (.51,.50,.52,.47)
 Hoya circular  (.54,.56,.55,.53)
 Hoya linear  (.45,.47,.45,.43).
 Tiffen Warm  (.62,.58,.62,.62)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He concluded that the most neutral filter was the B+W Warm. The Tiffen
Warm is linear. Hoya has subsequently introduced a Warm polarizer
(called the Moose filter, after the so-named wildlife photographer) in
circular version, which is relatively economical.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Englender also found the Wratten .6ND filter to match the density of the
polarizers well. This confirms the rule to use a filter factor of two
stops for a polarizer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;uv-filter&#34;&gt;UV filter&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some folks like to use them permanently for protection of the front
element of the lens, just like in 35mm. Image degradation would be
neglectible, especially considering the enlargement ratios needed in LF.
Others find that in LF, accidental damage is unlikely. They are
definitively useful at high altitudes to remove excess UV.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;step-up-rings&#34;&gt;Step up rings&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can buy circular filters (glass) to fit your largest lens, and then
a set of step-up rings to fit your other lenses. The main problem with
this approach is that step-up rings put the filter further from the
lens, which might actually increase vignetting on wide-angle lenses. For
instance, I find I get more vignetting on my 110 with a step-up ring
from 67 to 82 than with a plain 67 filter. Filter systems (see next)
work on the same principle (one set of filters, one ring for each lens),
but are more versatile. The only advantage of using step-up rings would
be that they are cheaper than the adaptor rings used in most filter
systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;filter-systems&#34;&gt;Filter systems&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Filter systems are by far the most versatile way to use filters for a
set of different lenses. You only need to get a different adaptor ring
for each lens. You have a huge choice of filters, can adjust them
independently in rotation and translation (making this kind of system
almost mandatory if you use graduated filters) and combine them easily.
Some systems also include a lens shade. Their main drawbacks are the
bulk and set-up time required for the system. Both factors are not a
significant aggravation in LF, hence their popularity with LF users.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A filter system has three components:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A circular ring, one for each lens size. The best systems have two
types of adaptor rings, regular rings, and wide-angle rings, which
keep the holder closer to the lens to avoid vignetting.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A holder. The best systems have a choice of holders to accomodate a
various number and/or thickness of filters .&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A choice of rectangular filters. The rectangular shape allows the
filter to be adjusted in height (critical for graduated filters),
while the holder can be rotated. Various materials are available:

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Gels are the cheapest. Optically good, but not durable. The
Kodak Wratten filters are manufactured to very precise specs,
and their spectral response is published.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Glass could be optically the best, but are easy to break.
Tiffen, Heliopan, and Schneider make glass filters. Schneider
has MC glass filters (a 4x5 grad is over \$400).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Polyester filters are made only by Lee (Calumet sells Lee
products under their own name). One thing to be careful with
them if you wish to combine them with the polarizer is that they
must be between the polarizer and the film. If you place them in
front of the polarizer, you&amp;rsquo;ll see some interesting patterns.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Optical resin (CR-39) is the most common, and will be discussed
further.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are three widths of holders that are usable with LF:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;83mm or 3&amp;rdquo;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;(Cokin P)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;100mm or 4&amp;rdquo; (Hitech, Lee/Calumet, Sinar)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;130mm or 5&amp;rdquo; (Cokin X-Pro)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;cokin&#34;&gt;Cokin&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cokin A (3&amp;rdquo; or 75mm)&lt;/strong&gt;. Rings 36-62mm. Just too small for most
serious photographers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cokin P (83mm)&lt;/strong&gt;. The most common system. Rings 48-82mm. It is by
far the cheapest (holder and rings around \$10 each), so durability
of the holder is not a real concern. It will work for many lenses,
especially if you don&amp;rsquo;t stack filters and saw off the outermost
filter slot to reduce the possibility of vignetting. With this
modification, it works with Nikon &lt;sup&gt;20&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;.8, 24-120, Canon 17-35 above
24, 110 XL in 5x7 without extreme movements. One nice thing the
Cokin system has is the ability to accept a glass polarizer that can
be rotated independently of the holder. This is important when
combining a polarizer and an ND grad. However, this polarizer will
vignette more than the holder. The main drawback of this holder is
that it is too small for some lenses. Cokin P filters are cheap and
low quality. In particular, the graduated grey is not neutral and
has a green cast. However, Hi-Tech and Singh-Ray make filters that
fit the Cokin P holder, so this is not an issue. A Hi-Tech grad to
fit the Cokin P is truly neutral, and costs only \$30. Hi-Tech also
makes their holder in P size, but if you&amp;rsquo;re going to pay more than
\$100 for a holder, you might as well get it in 100mm.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cokin X-pro (130mm).&lt;/strong&gt; The largest holder. It will fit a lens with
max. 122 mm external diameter. Nobody else makes filters that large.
This system is relatively new.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;the-100mm-4-inch-standard-hitech-lee-calumet-sinar&#34;&gt;The 100mm (4 inch) standard: Hitech, Lee/Calumet, Sinar&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The filters are extremely similar in optical quality, the only real
difference being the holder system and the thickness of the filter. The
quality is very high. They might be actually made at the same plant.
Hi-Tech has the best selection and the best prices (notably cheaper than
Lee) for filters. The holders are well built, however they are heavier,
bulkier, and considerably more expensive than the Cokin. The advantage
is having larger filters, and a more configurable holder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lee (100mm)&lt;/strong&gt;. The most versatile holder system as far as filter
thickness is concerned. It can use any 100mm filter. You configure
your holder with a variety of slots systems of different widths,
including gel, 2mm,4mm. The holder is \$100, regular rings \$40
(larger sizes are more expensive, up to 105mm), wide-angle rings
\$62 (mount the filter closer to the lens, available only up to
82mm). Polarizer is a square (\$150). To rotate it independently,
you need to tandem two holders, which might vignette wide-angle
lenses.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hi-Tech (100mm)&lt;/strong&gt;. Offers more lens attachments (in particular
attachments to the back of the lens) than Lee. The filter thickness
is 1.5mm. The Hitech may not handle all Lee filters. The holder is
\$120, regular rings \$25 , and wide angle rings \$45, so it comes a
bit cheaper than the Lee. Standard polarizer is a expensive circular
105mm which fits on a front ring, which might cause vignetting.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sinar (100mm)&lt;/strong&gt; Filters are either 1mm or 1.25 mm thick. The
selection is limited and nobody else makes filter that thin. You
could have the edges of other manufacturer&amp;rsquo;s filters milled to fit
the holder, but I don&amp;rsquo;t really see why one wouldn&amp;rsquo;t prefer to use
Lee or Hi-Tech in the first place. Sinar has discontinued this
product line.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;other-manufacturers&#34;&gt;Other manufacturers&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Singh Ray produces high quality and expensive resin filters to fit other
manufacturer&amp;rsquo;s holders. Their hard-step GND has a sharper transition
than other manufacturer&amp;rsquo;s equivalent. They also offer a few specialty
filters, like a reverse GND and a strip, and will consider making custom
filters. Not all their filters are listed on their web site. Their
filters fit both the Cokin P system (grad: \$100, Pol: \$160), and the
100mm system (grad: \$150, Pol:\$340). Their polarizer for the 100mm
system is a 100mm x 100mm square (like the Lee).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;wide-angle-lenses&#34;&gt;Wide angle lenses&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using additional filters on wide angle lenses present some unique
problems, because of the wide angle of coverage, large front element,
and necessity (for some) to have a center filter. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.skgrimes.com/slipon/index.htm&#34;&gt;SK Grimes
adapter&lt;/a&gt; can help and is much
cheaper than custom adaptors made by Lee. Larry Huppert is developing a
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.greenspun.com/bboard/q-and-a-fetch-msg.tcl?msg_id=003cHE&#34;&gt;custom system based on 100mm
filters&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;more-information&#34;&gt;More information&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rodenstock has a 2-page brochure about the use of center filters. In the
US, you can request it from info@hpmarketingcorp.com&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.2filter.com/&#34;&gt;The Filter Connection&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.singh-ray.com/&#34;&gt;Singh-Ray&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.leefilters.com/&#34;&gt;Lee filters&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.greenspun.com/com/qtluong/photography/lf/filters.html&#34;&gt;View or add
comments&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>http://lflf.surge.sh/equipment/gg/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lflf.surge.sh/equipment/gg/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Large format photography: enhanced focussing screens&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;enhanced-focussing-screens&#34;&gt;Enhanced focussing screens&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Compiled by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.terragalleria.com/&#34;&gt;Q.-Tuan Luong&lt;/a&gt; for
&lt;a href=&#34;.&#34;&gt;largeformatphotography.info&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;If you find it difficult to focus with your ground glass, you might
want to consider a replacement. Two things can make a ground glass
difficult to focus on:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Grain&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Darkness off axis, especially off-axis&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition, the hot spot makes it difficult to assess the composition.
A finer glass will tend to have a worse light fall-off. Two solutions
are to add a Fresnel lens to even up the illumination, or to use a Boss
screen. Although they do their job, the problem with Fresnel lenses is
that they work optimally only for one focal length. On the other hand,
ALL the users of the Boss screen seem to like it. The only drawback seem
to be that this screen might be damaged by extreme temperatures (hot and
cold). I was relatively satisfied with the screen on the 5x7 back of my
tachi, which was a plastic fresnel/ground combination protected by a
sheet of glass. I found the stock screen of my Canham difficult to focus
on. I tried using a fresnel lens, but I got weird problems with it. Then
I switched to a Toyo focussing screen, which has a considerably finer
grain. This made focussing easier but the hot spot was terrible.
Eventually I switched to a Boss screen, and I found it worked fine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;fresnel-lenses&#34;&gt;Fresnel lenses&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some general remarks about focusing screens. Most of these are &amp;ldquo;field
lenses&amp;rdquo; usually of the Fresnel type, so they can be flat, which direct
the light going through the ground glass toward the expected location of
the viewer&amp;rsquo;s eyes. For this scheme to work right the focal length of the
field lens must be such as to focus the light from the lens at a
convenient distance for viewing. This will be affected by the location
of the lens so will vary with focal length of the taking lens and to a
lesser extent with distance focused on. It is the angle of the cone of
light leaving the lens which is important. It also depends on the whole
optical path being centered. For this reason field lenses do not work
well when the camera movements are used. The parts of the screen away
from the optical center will be darker than with a conventional GG. The
same for using WA lenses. The angle of the light striking the edges of
GG are acute and a different FL of field lens is needed to make the
image uniform. &lt;strong&gt;Richard Knoppow&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I tried a fresnel lens made by Arca-Swiss. The illumination is a bit
more even than before, but I don&amp;rsquo;t find the image to be much brighter.
The thing which bugs me is that when I use wide angles, there is a very
weird effect, with concentric bright rings which look like double
images. They are extremely disturbing with a 90 lens, and noticeable
with a 120 lens, to the point of preventing me from assessing the
composition of the image in the corners. Rod Klukas from Photomark says
that with any Fresnel this is going to happen for some focal lenghts (he
observes the same with this 45 lens on 4x5), and as a consequence there
is a folk he knows who has different backs with different fresnels that
he switches as he switches lenses. &lt;strong&gt;Tuan&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-beattie-intenscreen&#34;&gt;The Beattie Intenscreen&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Beattie is, basically, a plastic &amp;ldquo;ground-glass&amp;rdquo; with a built-in
fresnel lens on one side of the &amp;ldquo;ground-glass&amp;rdquo;. get a glass cover plate
to protect the plastic screen. I decided that I didn&amp;rsquo;t like the Beattie
and took it off and went back to using a plain ground glass and fresnel
lens. Why? It really is brighter but:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The grain is much coarser than other ground glasses that I&amp;rdquo;ve used
so that while the scene is easier to see because it&amp;rsquo;s brighter, it&amp;rsquo;s
harder to focus because of the coarse grain of the GG being more
visible. For me the net effect was no change in ease of focusing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The GG becomes strongly directional. Moving your eye away from the
axis of the lens causs the image to go very dark. So as soon as you
use any significant amount of rise/fall or shift, the image &amp;ldquo;blacks
out&amp;rdquo;. Not a problem for those who don&amp;rsquo;t use much movement, and less
a problem with long lenses, but I found it to be nearly impossible
to focus when using a 90mm or shorter lens along with any amount of
vertical/horizontal movement.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One person even said that the plastic screens aren&amp;rsquo;t always perfectly
flat so that prefect focus in the center of the screen may give out of
focus negatives. The probably do make pretty good backup ground glass
for carrying around. I would imagine they are much less fragle than real
glass, and backups are rarely needed. &lt;strong&gt;Barry Sherman&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-linhof-super-screen&#34;&gt;The Linhof Super Screen&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Linhof Super Screen also incorporates a fresnel, but it didn&amp;rsquo;t
interfere with focusing in the same way as a Beattie Intenscreen. I
think the Linhof was brighter than the Boss, but I did not care for the
way it had bowed in the Technika it was installed in. To make matters
worse, I looked at it one day, noted the bowing, then went back about a
week later, and it was bowed differently. I didn&amp;rsquo;t particularly care for
the idea that the damn thing was not stable (it&amp;rsquo;s a plastic screen).
&lt;strong&gt;Paul Butzi&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-boss-screen&#34;&gt;The Boss screen&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &amp;ldquo;Boss&amp;rdquo; screen, made in the Netherlands, is a thin layer of a light
scattering wax/paraffin mixture between two glass layers. In contrast to
a &amp;ldquo;ground&amp;rdquo; glass there is no visible grain, it is brighter and quite
contrasty. In addition you dont need an extra fresnel lens for most
focal length. I use one on my 4x5 with lenses from 75mm to 600mm and I
am very pleased with it. With the 75mm there is a hot spot in the
center, but the corners of the format are still clearly visible without
fresnel. They have screens fitting most view cameras and you can also
choose between a model with clear corners (similar to cut-away corners)
and the standard rectangular shape. If I remember it right, the
manufacturer advises that temperatures should not exceed 55 degrees C,
but I never had any problems in summer. I noticed, however, that at
temperatures below approximately -10 degrees C, some Newtons rings
appeared after some hours in the cold at the edge of the ground glass,
indicating a slight separation between the glass and the wax layer. This
effect was reversible, though. I experienced a partial separation
(1-2square cm) between the wax and (one of the) glass layers when the
camera was subjected to temperatures below -15degrees C (5 deg. F) for
several hours. It shows up as an area with Newton&amp;rsquo;s rings, its not a
crack pattern. You can easily test if its really separated, by applying
a little bit of pressure with your fingers on the glass: when the Newton
rings move, you have a separation ( and not some ice from breathing on
your glass :-) ). Most of the time this was reversible and the rings
disapperared when the camera was warmed up again, but one time (really
cold) it was permanent. As you have mentioned, it is possible to
&amp;ldquo;repair&amp;rdquo; this area by _careful_ heating with a hair dryer _just_
until the wax melts and becomes clear, then let it cool again. Dont
forget to tape the edges of the inner glas, or else some wax will creep
out (I forgot). The repaired area looks a little more translucent when
the GG is held against the light, but in the camera it is only
noticeable at certain angles. I assume this difference can be reduced by
changing the cool-down process of the wax, but I did not want to make a
test series with my Bosscreen. Be aware that according to the
manufacturer separation can also happen if the screen is bent by
tightening the mounting (screws or whatever device is used) of the
ground glass too much. Despite the cold temperature problems I would
still recommend the Bosscreen; its a real improvement over my former
setup (Linhof ground glass and Fresnel). &lt;strong&gt;Arne Croell.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Bosscreen is made by a Dutch company called Stabitech (formerly
&amp;ldquo;Stabilix&amp;rdquo;, which went bankrupt towards the end of 2003). The company
sells direct as well. The new website of the company is
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.stabitech.nl&#34;&gt;http://www.stabitech.nl&lt;/a&gt; You can place an order by email with them and
wire your payment to their bank account. They can cut a screen at any
size to fit your camera, but this took more than a month in my case.
It&amp;rsquo;s imported in the US and probably sold retail as well by Bromwell
Marketing in Pittsburgh (412-321-4118). It was extremely difficult to
get a screen through the specialty LF retailers.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have heard that the temperature limit is around 140F, which is easily
reached in summer in a car trunk. Chris Newman writes &amp;ldquo;I am on my third
one, one damaged by extreme cold the other by moderate heat (90
degrees)&amp;ldquo;. Myself, I didn&amp;rsquo;t have any problems until a summer trip to the
Rocky Mountains, (where it doesn&amp;rsquo;t get that hot). Since then, I have the
dreaded bubbles. They do not interfere so much that the screen would not
be usable, however are enough of a nuisance that I will replace it. One
frequent concern about the Boss screen is that the position of the plane
of focus would be wrong, but this has been addressed properly:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Basically, the sheets of glass of the Bosscreen are two different sizes.
The one which goes closest to the lens is small enough to fit INSIDE the
area on which the ground glass usually rests. It is the inner surface of
the piece of glass on the viewing side which actually seats on the
routed out area that the ground glass normally sits. This then puts the
inner surface of this outermost piece of glass in the correct focal
plane, which means, of course, that the wax is actually too close to the
lens at this point. To compensate for that, there is a piece of plastic
(they call it &amp;ldquo;tape&amp;rdquo;) along the edges on the inner side of the glass
which sits in the rout. This tape is sufficient to correctly space the
glass back far enough to put the wax in the correct focal plane. &lt;strong&gt;David
Fokos&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The layer of glass between the lens and image forming plane probably
affects the focus position. Probably why the real Boss screen comes with
some shims. Otherwise the smaller front glass should put the wax layer
in the same position as the ground side of the ground glass (assuming
you are using a camera designed to have no fresnel between the ground
glass and the lens, some cameras like most speed graphics were designed
to always have a fresnel mounted in front of the GG). I&amp;rsquo;ve heard that
the layer of glass moves the focus point back by about &lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; the thickness
of the glass if I&amp;rsquo;m remembering right. I&amp;rsquo;m sure it depends on the index
of refraction of the glass, but this probably doesn&amp;rsquo;t vary much unless
you are using some exotic glass type. &lt;strong&gt;John Sparks&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;more-information&#34;&gt;More information&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.wisner.com/viewing.htm&#34;&gt;Viewing Screens for Large Format
Cameras&lt;/a&gt; by Ron Wisner. Explains how
a ground glass work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;List compiled by &lt;strong&gt;Craig Blurton&lt;/strong&gt; (originally posted in a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.largeformatphotography.info/forum/showthread.php?t=18137&#34;&gt;LF Forum
thread&lt;/a&gt;):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;FOCUSING SCREENS MADE BY THIRD PARTY MANUFACTURERS&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Beattie Intenscreen&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.intenscreen.com&#34;&gt;www.intenscreen.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
BosScreen&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.stabitech.nl/Bosscreen.htm&#34;&gt;www.stabitech.nl/Bosscreen.htm&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
BrightScreen&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.brightscreen.com/view.html&#34;&gt;http://www.brightscreen.com/view.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Maxwell Precision Optics UNOFFICIAL website&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.mattclara.com/maxwell/index.html&#34;&gt;www.mattclara.com/maxwell/index.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Maxwell Precision Optics&lt;br /&gt;
Contact Bill Maxwell &amp;lt;maxwellprecisionoptics@yahoo.com&amp;gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Satin Snow&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.satinsnowglass.com&#34;&gt;www.satinsnowglass.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Velveteen View screen&lt;br /&gt;
Contact Greg Garret &amp;lt;garretart7@yahoo.com&amp;gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
EXAMPLES OF FOCUSING SCREENS MADE/SOLD BY MANUFACTURERS FOR THEIR
CAMERA&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Ebony Fresnel Lenses&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ebonycamera.com/acc.html&#34;&gt;http://www.ebonycamera.com/acc.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Canham Fresnel Lenses&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.canhamcameras.com/accessoryf.html&#34;&gt;http://www.canhamcameras.com/accessoryf.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Linhof Super Screen&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.linhof.de&#34;&gt;www.linhof.de&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Sinar Fresnel Lenses&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.sinar.ch&#34;&gt;http://www.sinar.ch&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Wisner Fresnel Lenses&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;http://wisner.com/Page19.html&#34;&gt;http://wisner.com/Page19.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Wista Fresnel Lenses&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.wista.co.jp&#34;&gt;http://www.wista.co.jp&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
EXAMPLES OF GENERIC FRESNEL LENS THAT CAN BE ADAPTED FOR USE AS A
FOCUSING SCREEN WITH A CAMERA&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
3DLens.Com&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.3dlens.com&#34;&gt;http://www.3dlens.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Edmund Optics&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.edmundoptics.com&#34;&gt;http://www.edmundoptics.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.greenspun.com/com/qtluong/photography/lf/gg.html&#34;&gt;View or add
comments&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>http://lflf.surge.sh/equipment/heads/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lflf.surge.sh/equipment/heads/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h2 id=&#34;tripod-heads-for-large-format-photography&#34;&gt;Tripod heads for Large Format Photography&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;By &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.terragalleria.com/&#34;&gt;Q.-Tuan Luong&lt;/a&gt; for the &lt;a href=&#34;.&#34;&gt;Large
Format Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;A survey of pan-tilt heads, ball heads, and quick release (QR) systems,
with a discussion of the merits of each system, and a few specific
recommendations based on user&amp;rsquo;s experience. Updated Oct. 2008.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://lflf.surge.sh/images/ball-heads.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ball heads, from left to right: Arca-Swiss B1, Acratech Ultimate
Ball-head, Slik Standard, Velbon PH-253&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;three-way-pan-tilt-heads&#34;&gt;Three way Pan Tilt heads&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A three way Pan Tilt head gives independant control of movement over
each of the three axes (pan, forward-backwards, left-right), using an
independant locking mechanism. It gives you precise control. Most users
find that they would be the most appropriate type of heads for
large-format use. While universally used in the studio, in the field,
they suffer from two drawbacks: (a) they are quite heavy and bulky (b)
they tend to be slow if you also use them for a smaller format camera.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;Bogen 3029&lt;/strong&gt; (less than 2lbs/900g) is one of the smallest PT
heads sturdy enough for a light LF. It has no QR. The &lt;strong&gt;Bogen 3030&lt;/strong&gt;
is identical except for a QR system which uses a very small
rectangular plate, which might not be enough for most LF cameras.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;Bogen Compact Gear Head &lt;sup&gt;410&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;3275&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; (2.75lbs/1.24kg) has geared
movements in 3 directions, making it easy to make minor adjustments.
A disengagement clutch mechanism allows for quick positioning.
Unlike most PT heads, it has no big protruding handles. Although
advertised as a small and medium format head it is functionally one
of the best PT heads for a 4x5. However, so people have reported
some creep and wiggle. The QR system is incompatible with the Hex
system, but has been reported to work fine: &amp;ldquo;The quick release is
one of the desirable things about this head. It takes two motions to
release this plate, one is to push in a button and the other is to
move the lever the button is on in the opposite direction. I haven&amp;rsquo;t
been able to figure out how you could accidently release the plate
and I have tried, the quick releases on most Bogens is a real weak
point in my opinion but this is a big improvement. Also, to place
the camera on the head everything goes into place with a definite
release noise from the lever or else it doesn&amp;rsquo;t go together at all.
I have also put it through its paces with a 20+ pound monorail to
check to see if there would be any movement or drift from the gears
and found none. I could imagine smacking the head against a rock and
breaking it in 2 or 3 pieces but otherwise mine has performed very
well for me.&amp;rdquo; &lt;strong&gt;Jeff White&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Bogen Deluxe 3047&lt;/strong&gt; has bubble levels and the hexagonal plate
QR system, and is sturdy enough for most cameras. It&amp;rsquo;s pretty cheap
(\$60). The &lt;strong&gt;Bogen Heavy Duty head 3057&lt;/strong&gt; and the &lt;strong&gt;Bogen Super Pro
Head 3039&lt;/strong&gt; are better made heads which will easily support a 8x10
(\$120). Rated to 20lbs+. All are bulky with those handles sticking
out, and heavy 4.2lbs/2kg. &amp;ldquo;I&amp;rsquo;ve used the 3057 head on a standard
Zone VI tripod legset with 8x10 for years. It is a seriously heavy
and solid combination. If you intend to go very far on foot to make
your image it&amp;rsquo;s likely not the best combination. On the plus side:
it handles very heavy LF cameras with ease, the large mounting plate
for the 3057 (which can also be used with other hexagonal head QR
Bogen units) provides excellent support for heavy 8x10 and larger
field type cameras with a large wood (or metal) beds, the quick
release system makes mounting and dismounting large and heavy
cameras very easy, its locking device is quite secure, and the
adjustable two-way bubble levels make camera levelling simple if
your camera does not have these devices attached. On the negative
side: the side-to-side movement locking mechanism is a large, metal
wheel-type device that is not very deeply ribbed and requires a lot
hand strength to tighten and loosen, the fore-and-aft tilt movement
has a rather short rubber-coated locking handle that tightens and
loosens much more easily, but neither of the two mechanisms afford
much in the way of leverage to smoothly or accurately position the
camera. And, of course, it&amp;rsquo;s heavy as hell, though it looks like you
could take a sledge hammer to it with no adverse effects.&amp;rdquo; &lt;strong&gt;Sergio
Ortega&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;Arca B2&lt;/strong&gt;, a double axis ballhead, in spite of its name and
appearance, is a PT head with independent control of the different
axes. It unique in that the pivot points are directly centered under
the center of the camera. &amp;ldquo; It is a double tilt rational head. It
consists of one &amp;ldquo;ball&amp;rdquo; (for lateral tilts)inside another larger
&amp;ldquo;ball&amp;rdquo; which controls fore and aft tilts. The Arca Swiss B1 Monoball
has a variable tension &amp;ldquo;drag&amp;rsquo; controlled by a thumbscrew which
allows the user to set just how loose you want the head to get when
loosened (the B2 Monoball also has this feature on the outer ball)
and when using a view camera with this head it is possible to set
just enough drag so that it is possible to more easily (than with a
conventional ballhead) level the camera in all directions.&amp;rdquo; &lt;strong&gt;Ellis
Vener&lt;/strong&gt;. It&amp;rsquo;s much more compact than other PT heads, using knobs
instead of handles, It weights about the same as the Bogens (3.5lbs)
but has a considerably higher carrying capacity, being rated at an
astounding 150lbs. It&amp;rsquo;s also astoundingly expensive (\$650).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;Arca Cube&lt;/strong&gt; uses an innovative design with double stacked
goniometers. It is geared, lighter (300g less) and more compact than
the Bogen 410. The operation is very smooth. The main problem is
that it costs \$1300. There is a Korean company &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.tripodballhead.com/&#34;&gt;Photo
Clam&lt;/a&gt;, that offers a similar product
for half of that price. Arca Swiss claims that said product
infringes on their patent, while the Korea company denies it does.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Other heads worth looking at include the &lt;strong&gt;Linhof 3-way leveling
head&lt;/strong&gt; (compact without protruding handles, 2 lbs/900g, \$700, yes
it&amp;rsquo;s a Linhof), and the &lt;strong&gt;Majestic gear head&lt;/strong&gt; (6lbs/2.7kg, supports
35lbs, \$270 but can be bought used for cheap).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;two-way-pan-tilt-head-leveling-heads&#34;&gt;Two-way pan-tilt head (leveling heads)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those heads have independant control of movement over two axes
(forward-backwards, left-right), and are used to level the camera. They
have a large mounting surface, making them secure for large cameras. The
&lt;strong&gt;Ries&lt;/strong&gt; is considered by many to be the best, but &lt;strong&gt;Gitzo&lt;/strong&gt; also makes
a leveling head worth checking out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;panning-ball-heads&#34;&gt;Panning ball heads&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A panning ball head has two independant controls: one for the ball
itself, which you can move freely in any direction, and the other,
generally a smaller knob, for the panning base. A pan bed is a separate
rotational table, which permits free left-right movement even when the
ball is locked. Most medium-sized balls have some sort of
frictioncontrol, which let you adjust the resistance of the ball to
movement. This way, you don&amp;rsquo;t have to hold firmly the camera while
making adjustments. A good ball head should maintain smooth motion, even
with a high friction. Inexpensive ball heads do not seem to be able to
do that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Generally, with the ball head it is faster to frame your shot initally,
but more finicky when you want to refine the framing because trying to
tweak tilt without upsetting side-to-side level can be difficult,
particularly with heavier cameras. What you gain in speed, you loose in
precision. For smaller cameras (35mm and MF), the ball-head is generally
acknowledged to be the tool of choice&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ball heads are much more compact than PT head, having no protruding
handles, and generally lighter, making them a good choice for field
photography, where you&amp;rsquo;d level using bubble levels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Acratech Ultimate Ballhead&lt;/strong&gt; (420g, \$270) This ball-head uses an
innovative design where the ball is locked by an open diagonal
collar. There are two advantages of this design (a) the weight
savings over a classical design with a cup and walls, (b) the ease
of cleaning, especially since there is no grease or oil. The ball&amp;rsquo;s
lock can be very positive, given it an outstanding strength to
weight ratio. I write &amp;ldquo;can&amp;rdquo;, because for that to happen you have to
tightened with excessive torque. With a large format camera, the
head slipped all the time, and I got my fingers pinched quite a few
times too. The other drawback of the design is that while with a
classical design you can tilt in any direction by about 45%, with
the Acratech, you cannot tilt or tilt only very little in one
direction since the ball&amp;rsquo;s stem would be blocked by the collar. You
can use the panning base to change the orientation of the collar,
but it is not as convenient, since a second knob has to be released
and locked. Compared to the Arca, the tension control is not as
useful, since there are no calibration marks for it. The Acratech
comes with an Arca-style platform installed by default.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Linhof Profi II&lt;/strong&gt; (550g, \$250). One of the smallest ball-head of
classical design that you should consider for general use with LF. A
well-proven, smooth ball-head. Mine served me well for 7 years.
However, it is not made of corrosion-proof materials, and got
severely rusted inside after a very wet month in Alaska. Marflex
asked for repair the same price as a new unit bought in Europe. The
standard platform can be unscrewed to adapt a QR system. &lt;strong&gt;Giotto&lt;/strong&gt;
makes a similar, but much cheaper ball head, but it doesn&amp;rsquo;t seem to
have the same track record.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Really Right Stuff BH-40&lt;/strong&gt; (494g, \$295 without clamp, add
\$15-\$95 depending on clamp chosen). Really Right Stuff uses a
different clamping mechanism where compression is appied sideways
instead of from the bottom. Compared to the classical design
(examplified by the B1 and Profi II), the RRS has two main
advantages: a larger and much more usable pan locking mechanism, and
an independent knob for setting the minimum drag on the ball. The
main drawback is that the locking is done by a lever rather than by
a knob. The lever can get on your way in some configurations. RSS
has thought about this problem, by providing the ability to
reposition the lever with a spring-loaded mechanism, yet when the
need to reposition the lever occurs in action, it can be a little
frustrating. The only other problem is that the two knobs are quite
close, and although they are shaped differently, could sometimes be
confused.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Arca B1&lt;/strong&gt; (750g, \$400). The standard by which all other
ball-heads are judged. Under a load, it is significantly more smooth
than the Profi. What makes this ball unique is a patented elliptical
ball which gets stiffer further away from the centered position. The
drawback is that in some circumstances, the ball can lock-up. &amp;ldquo; The
small friction screw defines the stroke of a disk in the
multifunction knob. If you do loosen the multifunction knob onto
this &amp;ldquo;limiter&amp;rdquo; the disk puts a high pressure onto the friction
screw. Therefore you cannot loosen it until you have tightened
slightly the multifunction knob and released the pressure. Another
common mistake is that although the ball is unlocked, the
multifunction knob is turned counter-clockwise onto the stop. ( pay
attention which direction is clock- respectively counter-clockwise.)
If you force the multifunction knob onto this stop, you will need
the same power to tighten the multifunction knob again (as when you
turned counter clockwise) If you experience a &amp;ldquo;lock-up&amp;rdquo;, simply
tighten (clockwise ! ) the multifunction knob approximately &lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; turn
and loosen the small friction screw if possible. That&amp;rsquo;s it. There is
no need to always alter the friction screw when changing the
camera/lens weight. Use the index ring on the multifunction knob.
Arca-Swiss Monoball tripod heads are serviced in the USA through our
Office in Chicago: E-mail: arcaswiss@aol.com, Phone: (773) 248 2513,
Fax: (773) 248 2774 &amp;ldquo; &lt;strong&gt;Arca-Swiss Customer Support&lt;/strong&gt;. Recently
(late 2000), there has been serious availability and quality control
problems. The two competing products are the &lt;strong&gt;Kirk BH-1&lt;/strong&gt; (900g,
\$325), and the &lt;strong&gt;RRS BH-55&lt;/strong&gt; (820g, \$370-\$450). Differences with
the Arca are a separate knob for controling tension, a spherical
head resulting in no progressive tension, but no lock-up too. Both
are said to be very smooth and will support plenty (90lbs/40kg).
Other ball heads with the same carrying capabilities are
significantly heavier.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you need even more support in a ball head, there are the
scaled-up versions: &lt;strong&gt;Linhof Profi III&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Arca B1g&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;non-panning-ball-heads&#34;&gt;Non-panning ball-heads&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Only one knob to control the ball, and no panning base. The ball has to
be unlocked, or the tripod center column used, in order to perform
left-right adjustement. When using a small-format camera, the head&amp;rsquo;s
vertical &amp;ldquo;drop notch&amp;rdquo; cannot be easily relocated. I don&amp;rsquo;t particularly
recomment them, except for the smallest balls, since the weigth and
price savings are only around 25%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Velbon PH-253&lt;/strong&gt; (165g, \$60) Magnesium construction saves a bit of
weight. Probably the the lightest ball-head one can use with LF.
Adequate or lightweight LF cameras such as the Toho or the Tachihara
when backpacking.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Slik standard ball-head&lt;/strong&gt; (350g, \$45) Among the small ball-heads,
this one has the largest ball, making it quite usable for LF. I used
it extensively with my 5x7 on light trips and also as my main
ball-head while waiting for a new B1. It is on-off only, although
some friction can be obtained, which makes adjusting more delicate,
but it locks solidly enough. The standard platform can be removed
(destructively) to add a QR system.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;quick-release-systems&#34;&gt;Quick Release systems&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are two universal QR systems, the Arca-Swiss system and the Bogen
Hex system. Despite of some commonly heard claims, having used both I
think they are equally good. While obviously AS heads come with the AS
system and Bogen heads come with the Bogen system, you can buy the clamp
independantly to retrofit several heads (unlike the old B1, the newer B1
can be easily converted to accept the Bogen). A variety of plates is
available for each system, although because of the &amp;ldquo;open channel&amp;rdquo; nature
of the AS system, there are much more offerings for it. Some Bogen heads
also come with a dedicated plate which is not compatible with the Hex
system, while the AS system has been embraced by several manufacturers.
The Bogen system is quite inexpensive, being a steel casting. The clamp
costs \$30, and each standard plate is \$15. The AS can become pretty
costly, with each plate starting at \$50, especially when you get custom
plates which are not interchangeable. This higher price reflects the
better fit and materials.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the Arca-Swiss system, you line up and then slide the mounting plate
between two opposing jaws and then tighten them using a knob. The Bogen
system is spring-loaded: you position the plate, and press it in place,
which causes a lever to lock the plate. The basic Bogen plate is
hexagonal, however there is also a 4 inch square quick release plate,
which works with the clamp designed for the hexagonal system, and gives
more secure mounting with large cameras. The Bogen system, being
spring-loaded and aligned from the top, is clearly the faster.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main advantage of the AS system is the availability of several
plates in all shapes and sizes to fit exactly your camera and collared
lenses. Kirk enterprises and Really Right Stuff make custom plates.
Being produced in a larger variety of models, RRS plates are generally
acknowldeged to have a better fit. If you use several cameras and
formats, that&amp;rsquo;s a very nice thing. The Bogen plates are quite bulky and
tend to stick out on small cameras and lens mounts. On the other hand,
if you use only LF, the Bogen plates would work just fine. The second
advantage of the AS system is that the clamp is smaller (Kirk makes the
smallest) and lighter than the Bogen clamp. This is significant only if
travelling very light. A third advantage is that you can slide the plate
back and forth in the clamp to better balance your camera.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;RRS claims that plates which have flat tops will twist on the camera
body. In practice, I have not found that to be a problem, provided you
tighten your plate with a screwdriver. For small cameras, plates with a
ridge for the Bogen system are actually available from Bogen and from
Kirk. There is nothing which would prevent someone from making plates
for the Bogen system with the same quality materials and fit as the RRS
plates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is not clear which system is the safer, since the failures modes are
quite different. In the AS system you must turn the knob to grip the
camera plate. Friction is holding your camera, so there is always the
danger of not tightening it enough. In the Bogen system, when you hear a
click, it is locked. However it could be easier to release the locking
lever by accident (although there is a pin which you could flip to
prevent that from happening). The hex plates resist torque equally about
all axes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;more-information&#34;&gt;More information&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.kirkphoto.com/&#34;&gt;Kirk enterprises&lt;/a&gt; and especially &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.reallyrightstuff.com/&#34;&gt;Really
Right Stuff&lt;/a&gt; have good info on the
Arca QR system&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.wildpicture.com/pages/photography/hexplates.htm&#34;&gt;Hans Martens&amp;rsquo; guide to Manfrotto hexagonal Quick Release
Plates&lt;/a&gt;:
has pictures of different plates.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.greenspun.com/com/qtluong/photography/lf/head.html&#34;&gt;View or add
comments&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>http://lflf.surge.sh/equipment/holders/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lflf.surge.sh/equipment/holders/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Large format photography: cut film holders for 4x5&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;cut-film-holders-for-4x5&#34;&gt;Cut film holders for 4x5&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Compiled by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.terragalleria.com/&#34;&gt;Q.-Tuan Luong&lt;/a&gt; for
&lt;a href=&#34;http://lflf.surge.sh/&#34;&gt;largeformatphotography.info&lt;/a&gt;. Updated July 2004.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Contents:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#formats&#34;&gt;Formats&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#double&#34;&gt;Classical double holders&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#grafmatics&#34;&gt;Grafmatics&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#readyloads&#34;&gt;Preloaded systems - Quickloads and Readyloads&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#sharpness&#34;&gt;Effect of different holders on sharpness&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#more&#34;&gt;More information&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[]{#formats}&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;formats&#34;&gt;Formats&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Europe, the formats 4x5 inches and 9x12 cm coexist and you can get
both sizes (but metric is easier to find). The size of the film is
different, therefore the holders are too, however, the exterior
dimensions of the holders are the same so you don&amp;rsquo;t have to modify the
camera. The same applies of 5x7 inches vs 13cm x18cm, although both are
difficult to find.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the United States, metric size sheet film is very difficult to get.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[]{#double}&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;classical-double-holders&#34;&gt;Classical double holders&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;riteway-vs-lisco-fidelity&#34;&gt;Riteway vs Lisco/Fidelity&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Older Riteway Cut Film Holders (the ones with the metal handles on the
darkslides) are more highly regarded than say older Lisco. The Riteway
holders seem to hold up better. When I worked in a studio about 15 years
ago, my boss had over 100 holders all of which he had bought used.
Probably all but about 5 were this style Riteway and none of them leaked
light. Of the Lisco holders he bought, the failure rate (of used
holders) was high enough that he quickly stopped getting them (maybe 50%
of the ones he got leaked).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The current Riteway holders are made by the same company as current
Lisco and Fidelity holders (these three companies merged probably 20
years ago). The Lisco and Fidelity holders are identical except for the
name and slight differeneces in the pattern embossed in the plastic. The
Riteway holders also appear identical except for the automatic locking
built into the darkslides, and the very cheezey number wheels for
marking negatives. I have 2 of the current Riteways and lots of the
current Lisco and Fidelity holders. I can&amp;rsquo;t stand the Riteways. The lock
on the darkslides takes quite some effort to unlock on my wooden camera
and make it very easy to move the camera when removing the slide. The
number wheels turn way too easily and the numbers extend into the image
area. The different handles on the slides make the holders too large to
fit in the quart size Ziplock bags I use to keep dust out of my holders.
None of my holders (all bought new) have ever had light leaks (except
the one slide I managed to crack, the holder itself was fine once I
replaced the slide).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If I were were buying used holders, I&amp;rsquo;d look for the older plastic
Riteways with the metal slides. They seem to hold up much better than
other holders of the same age. If buying new holders (or used current
style holders), I&amp;rsquo;d avoid Riteways for the reasons mentioned above.
&lt;strong&gt;John Sparks&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hi John, My experience with old holders (4x5) is the same. The Riteway
holders all are fine, the film plane is in the right place etc. I have a
box full of Lisco and Fidelity holders most of which have warped, or
maybe were just not accurately made, and are not useable. This is a
matter of the film plane rather than light leakage. I started measuring
holders after getting unexplained mis-focussed pictures. I found the
film-plane to vary all over the place in all but the Riteway holders.
OTOH, later 8x10 Fidelity&amp;rsquo;s seem to be ok. &lt;strong&gt;Richard Knoppow&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;how-to-isolate-a-bad-4x5-film-holder-giving-unsharp-images&#34;&gt;How to isolate a bad 4x5 film holder giving unsharp images ?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can measure them using a depth micrometer (one good enough is about
\$30 US) and a plate of sheet aluminum with some holes drilled in it to
clear the micrometer. Measure with a sheet of scrap film in the holder.
The distance from the reference surface of the holder to the film plane
should be 0.187 inches (I think this is the right value). check the
corners and center. It should be very accurate and should show no signs
of warping. If your holders are reasonably new you may find they are all
OK and the problem came from mis-loading the film. Its all too easy to
miss getting one edge under the rail. If you find a bad one keep it for
spare parts, especially the dark slides and end flap. &lt;strong&gt;Richard
Knoppow&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;problems-with-used-wooden-holders&#34;&gt;Problems with used wooden holders&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main problem with old wood holders is that they can warp. The thing
is to check that the film plane is in the right place. This can be done
with a depth gauge and a reference block which can be a sheet of thick
aluminum with a hole for the guage in it. Put a sheet of film in and
check that the distance from the edges of the holder are exactly &lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;16&lt;/sub&gt;
from the film (4x5). The correct value for 8X10 is 0.251 inch measured
with film in the holder. Make sure the film isn&amp;rsquo;t tilted in the holder.
Sometimes you find a holder that is right on one side but not on the
other. Plastic holders can also warp and wear but its less likely.
Either kind should be checked before use, there isn&amp;rsquo;t really any
difference if they are OK. Once wood holders start to warp there really
isn&amp;rsquo;t much you can do. I&amp;rsquo;ve seen articles showing how to mill them down
or build them up in some way, it seems a lot of work for something that
will be a makeshift. A lot of fuzzy pictures that get blamed on cameras
or lenses are really due to bad holders. BTW my experience with used
8X10 holders hasn&amp;rsquo;t been good, far too many of them are way out of spec.
4x5&amp;rsquo;s are better but I will buy only &amp;ldquo;Riteway&amp;rdquo; holders used now and no
wooden ones regardless of manufacturer. I also have a bunch of 4x5
Fidelity Deluxe holders I got with a bunch of other stuff. They are all
over the place, I think I found two usable holders out about fifteen.
The newer 8x10 fidelities seem to be much higher quality. &lt;strong&gt;Richard
Knoppow&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anytime I have ever bought or used older, used, wodden 4x5 film holders,
I have had problems - warping, dust spots, light leaks, etc. I qucikly
found out the hard way why you can buy used, wooden 4x5 film holders for
a dime a dozen at photo flea markets. Older plastic film holders
however, ones I bought used, have worked just as fine as new plastic
film holders. &lt;strong&gt;Joseph O&amp;rsquo;Neil&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[]{#grafmatics}&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;grafmatics&#34;&gt;Grafmatics&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;a Grafmatic film holder is the same general size and shape of a
conventional 2 sheet film holder. It has a &amp;ldquo;D&amp;rdquo; ring, a locking device,
and a small release tab. The holder is actually a light tight box with
an internal tray that holds 6 &amp;ldquo;septums&amp;rdquo;. Each septum is a thin light
weight metal holder for a single piece of sheet film. These are stacked
one on top of another inside the tray that is then inserted inside the
outter light tight box. When used, the holder shuffels the 6 septums
sequentially from the stack to the film plane and then back to the
stack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In operation, the holder is inserted into the camera the same as a
standard film holder. I recall that it is a little bit thicker, but that
should cause no problem. To bring the first piece of film up for
exposure, you rotate the locking device and insert your finger into the
&amp;ldquo;D&amp;rdquo; ring . With the thumb of the same hand, press the release tap and
pull the &amp;ldquo;D&amp;rdquo; ring so that the inner box is pulled out holder to the
stop. At this time, the bottom septum is freed from the stack and
springs push it to the film plane. Pushing the &amp;ldquo;D&amp;rdquo; ring to press the
tray back into the holder does the final positioning of the septum to be
exposed. After exposure, cycle the &amp;ldquo;D&amp;rdquo; ring again, this time you don&amp;rsquo;t
need to active the release tab, and the exposed septum is pressed to the
top of the stack inside the tray and the film holder is now closed so
that you can remove it from the camera. (I may have the sequence
slightly in error, I don&amp;rsquo;t remember if you use the release tab to
position the unexposed septum or the exposed septum, or if ilt shuffels
film from the top to bottom or bottom to top, but you get the concept.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This takes about 10 times longer to explain than to do. As each septum
is positioned for exposure, a little wheel, positioned at the edge of
the sheet of film rotates &lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;6&lt;/sub&gt; of a turn, exposing a different number
siloutte. When the film is exposed, this siloutte &amp;ldquo;exposes&amp;rdquo; a frame
number ( 1 =&amp;gt;6) onto that piece of film. After the last piece of film
is exposed, the holder locks to prevent accidental double exposure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can use this holder to shuffel 6 pieces of film though the film
plane in well under 30 seconds, if you can cock the shutter of the lens
that fast!. If you want to expose both black and white and color film of
the same image, consider using the same ASA for both types of film and
alternating 3 color and 3 B&amp;amp;W films in the holder. Then just set up,
figure exposure and expose two consecutive pieces of film. This will
give you 3 pairs of B&amp;amp;W/Color negs in one holder. You can do this fast
enought that for most things that you would use a 4X5 camera for, the
image/exposure isn&amp;rsquo;t going to change between exposures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Grafmatic film holder is a VERY compact way to handle sheet film,
and I think a much more convenient way that standard film holders. If
you find one, just be careful to be sure that the septums are not bend
or damanged. &lt;strong&gt;Harvey Chao&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[]{#readyloads}&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;preloaded-systems-fuji-s-quickloads-and-kodak-readyloads&#34;&gt;Preloaded systems - Fuji&amp;rsquo;s Quickloads and Kodak Readyloads&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;images/Quick_ReadyMONTAGE.gif&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;{width=&amp;ldquo;500&amp;rdquo; height=&amp;ldquo;500&amp;rdquo;}&lt;br /&gt;
Picture courtesy of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.robertwhite.co.uk/&#34;&gt;Robert White&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The film is in a factory-loaded paper packet that you put in a special
holder. There are several advantages:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You don&amp;rsquo;t have to load holders.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The film is always clean (whereas it is difficult not to get dust
while loading holders yourself)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It is easier to take notes for each sheet, since you can just write
on the packet.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You can carry more film with you, since the weight and bulk is
considerably less than carrying the same amount of film in holders.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Drawbacks:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Not all emulsions come preloaded, and it is available only in 4x5.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;More expensive.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Some say that film holders ensure better flatness (see discussion
below).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you need to carry massive amounts of film (more than 100 sheets),
it ends up more bulky and heavy than carrying the film in boxes plus
enough holders to use.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fuji makes the Quickloads. At the time of the last update (July 2004),
the following emulsions are available: Provia 100F (transparency) Velvia
100F (transparency, enhanced saturation) , 64T (tungsten-balanced
transparency) Neopan (B&amp;amp;W negative), NPS (color negative). The Fuji
holder is available in two versions that are almost identical, save for
a small ink stamp for marking the packet as exposed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kodak makes the Readyloads, with the following emulsions: EPP
(transparency), E100 VS (transparency, enhanced saturation), TMax 100
(B&amp;amp;W negative), 160 VC (color negative). The Kodak holder was designed
to take Fuji readyloads as well as Kodak readyloads.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition, Polaroid makes a large variety of instant emulsions, and a
dedicated holder to process them. This holder can be used with
Readyloads and Quickloads as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;quickload-readyload-and-polaroid-film-holders-compatiblity&#34;&gt;Quickload, Readyload and Polaroid Film holders compatiblity&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.robertwhite.co.uk/&#34;&gt;Robert White&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[]{#Readysteady}The following table was put together through straight
experimentation, by trying each film in each back.&lt;br /&gt;
All the films physically fit all the backs but it is their operation in
these backs that counts. Therefore if it failed to work faultlessly
first time then in our opinion it doesn&amp;rsquo;t work at all. The test was
carried out using the current Kodak Readyload back and both the Fuji
Quickload Mk1 and Mk2 backs. The only significant difference between the
two, that we are aware of; is that the Mk2 has a small ink stamp built
in that can be used to mark the film as exposed. The Polaroid back is
the current 545 Pro with timer and thermometer. It has to be said that
there may well be people out there with different experiences than this;
but it should go without saying, that there is nothing safer than
sticking to using manufacturers&amp;rsquo;s backs with their own brand film for
absolute certainty that everything will be OK for critical work.&lt;br /&gt;
However there is the obvious temptation to mix and match for various
reasons; so, hence the experiment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;div align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;

**Kodak film in Quickload Mk1 - the back pulled the metal clip off
the end of the envelope when the envelope was removed post
exposure…Yes the release catch was pushed!**

&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;div align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;

**Kodak film in Quickload 2 - the whole of the film sheet is not
exposed when the envelope is pulled out to make the film ready for
exposure inside the camera.**

&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;div align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;

**Kodak film in the Polaroid back - works but bear in mind that this
has no pressure plate so one of the great advantages of this type of
film is being lost.**

&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;div align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;

**Fuji film in the Polaroid back - works but the situation is as
above with Kodak film.**

&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;div align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;

**Polaroid film in the Kodak back - didn&#39;t work because the metal
clip on the end of the envelope didn&#39;t catch when it was inserted.**

&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;div align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;

**Polaroid film in Fuji Quickload 1 - the whole of the film sheet is
not exposed when the envelope is pulled out to make the film ready
for exposure inside the camera.**

&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;div align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;

**Polaroid film in Fuji Quickload 2 - the whole of the film sheet is
not exposed when the envelope is pulled out to make the film ready
for exposure inside the camera.**
&lt;div align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;div align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;

+-----------------+-----------------+-----------------+-----------------+
| Film/Holder     | KODAK\          | FUJI\           | POLAROID\       |
| compatability   | Readyload Film  | Quickload Film  | Single sheet    |
|                 |                 |                 | film            |
+-----------------+-----------------+-----------------+-----------------+
| Kodak Readyload | &lt;div            | &lt;div            | &lt;div            |
| Holder          | align=&#34;center&#34;&gt; | align=&#34;center&#34;&gt; | align=&#34;center&#34;&gt; |
|                 |                 |                 |                 |
|                 | **Y**           | **Y**           | **N**           |
|                 |                 |                 |                 |
|                 | &lt;/div&gt;          | &lt;/div&gt;          | &lt;/div&gt;          |
+-----------------+-----------------+-----------------+-----------------+
| Fuji Quickload  | &lt;div            | &lt;div            | &lt;div            |
| Holder I        | align=&#34;center&#34;&gt; | align=&#34;center&#34;&gt; | align=&#34;center&#34;&gt; |
|                 |                 |                 |                 |
|                 | **N**           | **Y**           | **N**           |
|                 |                 |                 |                 |
|                 | &lt;/div&gt;          | &lt;/div&gt;          | &lt;/div&gt;          |
+-----------------+-----------------+-----------------+-----------------+
| Fuji Quickload  | &lt;div            | &lt;div            | &lt;div            |
| Holder II       | align=&#34;center&#34;&gt; | align=&#34;center&#34;&gt; | align=&#34;center&#34;&gt; |
|                 |                 |                 |                 |
|                 | **N**           | **Y**           | **N**           |
|                 |                 |                 |                 |
|                 | &lt;/div&gt;          | &lt;/div&gt;          | &lt;/div&gt;          |
+-----------------+-----------------+-----------------+-----------------+
| Polaroid 545    | &lt;div            | &lt;div            | &lt;div            |
| Pro             | align=&#34;center&#34;&gt; | align=&#34;center&#34;&gt; | align=&#34;center&#34;&gt; |
|                 |                 |                 |                 |
|                 | **Y**           | **Y**           | **Y**           |
|                 |                 |                 |                 |
|                 | &lt;/div&gt;          | &lt;/div&gt;          | &lt;/div&gt;          |
+-----------------+-----------------+-----------------+-----------------+

### About the OLD readyloads

The OLD readyloads from Kodak hold two sheets of film. In 2001, Kodak
introduced a NEW readyload system, which holds only one sheet of film
like the Fuji Quickload. **The new system, unlike the older one, is
reliable** (see Paul Butzi&#39;s report by following the link at bottom of
the page). The old system was unreliable. A lot of people have reported
having light leaks problems with the old Kodak readyloads. Kodak
redesigned the holder three times. They had a dedicated forum on AOL for
&#34;Readyload Problems&#34;. The fact that there are two sheets of film made it
worse: when you had a failure, you lost both sheets Infortunately, some
desirable emulsions (B&amp;W) were not readily available preloaded from
Fuji, and therefore a lot of people put up with the old Kodak system.
**Please note that the material that follows refers to the OLD
readyloads**.

#### Readyloads, Quickloads, and Polaroid holder

The quick/ready loads are more convenient, cleaner and more expensive
than using film holders. I think it&#39;s that simple. Kodak Readyloads are
double sided (two sheets to the packet) and because of this don&#39;t work
well in the Polaroid holders. I&#39;ve had thick emulsion films like T-Max
fog in the Polaroid 545i holder. The Fuji Quickloads are a single sheet
affair like Polaroid and work just fine in the Polaroid holder. We use
more Fuji than Kodak now mostly for that reason. We can go from proof to
final exposure without changing holders. If you&#39;re going to use Kodak
Readyloads you should buy the Kodak holder. It&#39;s a very inexpensive
plastic affair and it works fine with their films. **Fred/ Maplewood
Photography**
I&#39;ve used the following combos with the following results:

    Holder                  Film Packets            Results

    Kodak Readyload         Kodak Readyload         Massive Light Leaks
    Koadk Readyload         Fuji Quickload          Massive Light Leaks
    Polaroid 545            Kodak Readyload         Occasional Light Leaks
    Polaroid 545            Polaroid ProChrome      Occasional Light Leaks
    Polaroid 545            Fuji Quickload          Occasional Light Leaks
    Fuji Quickload          Fuji Quickload          Not a Single Problem

After a very high failure rate with the Kodak Readyload holder (over 50%
with the original holder, about 30% with the &#34;improved&#34; model III) I
abandoned the Kodak system altogether. In fact, I was so turned off that
they would market such a poor product and then blame the users for such
consistantly high failure rates (improper technique - oh yeah, then why
have you re-designed the holder at least two times?) that I have vowed
to never buy Kodak products again. I finally got smart and bought a Fuji
Quickload holder about a year ago. I have since shot several hundred
sheets of Velvia Quickloads without a single failure. No light leaks, no
jams, never a problem. The Fuji holder costs more, but IMHO it is well
worth it (especially considering how many sheets of film will be lost to
failures with the Kodak system at 2 sheets per packet times \$4.00 per
sheet for film and processing). The Fuji holder works smoothly and
positively. It feels like a precision tool, not a piece of plastic junk.
Some folks will say that if you stand on your head and tap the packet
just right, you can eliminate MOST of the light leak problems with the
Kodak system. I say, why bother? The Fuji system works right every time
(I used to shoot extra shots with the Kodak system in the hope that at
least one wouldn&#39;t be ruined). My time and my work are both important to
me. I can&#39;t afford to constantly have important shots ruined by poorly
designed equipment. I spent good money on a camera and lenses. I work
hard to get to the locations where I shoot. It doesn&#39;t make sense to me
to jeopardize that investment to save the cost of buying the Fuji
holder. No matter how good your lenses, the images will be useless if
you suffer light leaks. If you want to shoot Fuji film, and you need
dependable results, I highly recommend you spend the \$105 and get the
Fuji holder. It will pay for itself within a very short period. You will
never regret it, and you won&#39;t always be wodering which important shots
we ruinued this time. **Kerry Thalmann**
#### The slam technique

I have had several otherwise nice looking negatives ruined by light
leaks a few years ago when I started using Readyloads. Btw - I&#39;ve never
had a similar problem with Fuji Quickloads. Only Kodak Readyloads.

I&#39;ve found a solution to the problem, though: ensure that the covering
envelope is well seated in the metal clip which closes the bottom before
removing it from the holder.

How? After exposing the film I slide the envelope shut normally. Then,
keeping the release lever in the holder pressed down so that I can
withdraw the entire Readyload, I pull the Readyload out maybe 1-2
inches, and kind of &#34;slam&#34; it home again. Repeat. Repeat a third time.
Note that this doesn&#39;t take long. Just a second or two. It&#39;s really just
a quick &#34;slam-slam-slam-withdraw the Readyload&#34;. It&#39;s the equivalent of
removing the Readyload normally and then tapping the metal clip on the
bottom on a hard surface to ensure that the envelope is properly seated
in it, except that it&#39;s being done in the dark inside the Readyload
holder.

The result has been that rarely do I have a light leak at all and on the
rare occasions that I do it almost never extends far enough into the
image area to be a problem. This is still not as perfect as the results
that I get with Fuji Quickloads, but then Fuji doesn&#39;t make Tmax 100 and
I used to have far more negatives ruined by dust on the film at exposure
time than I now do from light leaks with Readyloads. **Barry Sherman**

#### Other tips

I use TMX in readyloads extensively. I confess to having something of a
love/hate relationship with the things. I love the light weight and
compactness of the things. I hate the increased cost (incidental issue
in my mind - film costs are small compared even to gas for me) and the
increased fiddlyness of using them. On the bright side, they do offer a
nice place to put a sticker with notes on it; this sticker stays with
the film until it&#39;s taken out of the packet at development time. I&#39;ve
ended up with far fewer sheets of film that wanted N-1 development but
somehow managed to sneak into the N+1 box as a result.
Kodak have gone thru several different versions of their Readyload
holder. It may be possible to differentiate between the different
versions and ensure that you&#39;re buying a recent one when buying used,
but I don&#39;t know how. I&#39;d recommend buying a new one from a store which
turns them over, to ensure that you get a newer holder. They apparently
avoid some of the problems caused by the old holders. I&#39;ve never
actually seen one for sale used, but then I don&#39;t hit the swaps and
stuff. Caveat emptor.

Lots of folks have had problems with light leaks, particularly at the
corners where the envelope seats in the metal clip. I&#39;ve evolved a
procedure which seems to eliminate this. It&#39;s included below. My
procedure is as follows:

1\. Before I load the holder, I inspect the packet carefully. At one
point I determined that I was causing fogging because the non-clip end
of one packet was catching the clip on another packet, bending the clip
and causing a leak. I now stack readyloads (after exposure) with all the
clips at one end, to prevent this problem after exposure. Packets with
bent clips are now placed in the &#39;fogged film&#39; pile. (I haven&#39;t found
one in months and months)

1a. I dust the readyload holder before inserting it in the camera. I&#39;ve
gotten dust on the film, and finally concluded that it was dust on the
pressure plate, transferred to the film on the other side from the
exposed film. Then when you withdraw the packet, the dust stays with the
film. Dusting the holder eliminated this.

1c. John Sexton, who consulted on the readyload packet design with EKC,
told me that it was a good idea to expose the &#39;side one&#39; side first.
Apparently if the packet is going to fail, it&#39;s more likely to fail in
that orientation. If it fails, of course, both sheets of film are
ruined. Better to ruin unexposed film than exposed film.

2\. I shield the holder when withdrawing the darkslide/envelope as much
as possible. I&#39;ve had no problems with fogging occurring while the
envelope is out, but I suspect I&#39;ve gotten fogging whilst pulling it.
It&#39;s vital to make sure that when you pull the darkslide/envelope, you
pull it out \*straight\*, with no flexing to the front or back of the
camera.

3\. Finally, the most important step: when you return the
darkslide/envelope after the exposure, run the packet back in, and then,
with the release button held in, grasp the envelope firmly where marked
for &#39;expose&#39;, and give the envelope several sharp raps back into the
holder. This prevents about 99.5% of the cases where the packet doesn&#39;t
re-seat in the clip. This trick was given to me by Barry Sherman, and I
think that using the &#39;slam&#39; turns using readyloads from a nightmare into
a reliable thing.

4\. For people who are just beginning with readyloads, it&#39;s important to
note that you \*must\* hold the packet firmly where marked &#39;expose&#39; when
pulling the darkslide to make an exposure, and must hold it \*firmly\*
where marked &#39;remove&#39; when withdrawing the packet afterwards. I&#39;ve
noticed people struggling with packets coming open whilst taking them
out of the holder, and it&#39;s almost always caused by holding it on the
&#39;expose&#39; part of the tab and having the clip catch on the light trap.
Note well: the location of the &#39;expose&#39; and &#39;remove&#39; switch when you
turn the packet over.

5\. Even when the envelope reseats properly, you can get minor leaks at
the corners. I noticed once that a stack of readyloads that I left on my
desk for two days all got fogged in the corner nearest the window (the
sun was shining on them directly) and now I keep readyloads in boxes to
keep light off of them. Use the little &#39;exposed&#39; stickers by putting
them over the clip. This prevents the clip from pulling a bit when
snagged, and letting light in.

Kodak have gone thru several generations of the readyload packets,
ranging from the yellow ones of several years ago, thru at least two
different versions of the black packets. When they first switched from
yellow to black, I had a run of problems (mostly bent clips from offset
stacking the packets). In the past two years or so, I&#39;ve had no problems
at all (at least since they started with the black packets with large
white labels on the clip end).

I use the Kodak readyload holder. I&#39;ve tried the Polaroid 545i holder
and that&#39;s just more hassle than I can stand. Other people report good
success. I suspect that the Kodak holder holds the film flatter. I&#39;ve
put packets in both the Kodak holder and the Polaroid holder and pulled
the dark slide/envelope and examined the film for flatness, and it looks
flatter to me. I didn&#39;t measure it, though. **Paul Butzi**.

I bought a pack of Tmax100 ready loads and did some lens testing with
them out side in the sun light. My experience is a follows: READ THE
DIRECTIONS: The two sided packs stick out the end of the Polariod 545
holder. The problem I had was that I couldn&#39;t pull the dark sleeve out
and trying to do so let light in the back of the camera. The reason I
couldn&#39;t pull the sleeve out is that on the inside there is a plastic
sheet that holds the film on one side of the sleeve. YOU DO NOT WANT TO
PULL ON THIS when you are making the exposure, only when you pull the
pack out of the holder do you hold this side of the sleeve. Once I
figured this out (once you develop your first film it becomes obvious)
and that you have to be careful when you pull the dark sleeve to take
the exposure all works well. I got no fogging from waving the packet
around in the sun light (not recommended). Sooooooo, well, they are not
bullet proof. Film holders are easier to use for the actual exposure.
**Kirk Fry**

------------------------------------------------------------------------

[]{#sharpness}
### Effect of different holders on sharpness

*&#34;Readyload, Quickload, shoot. A comparison of 4x5 film holders&#34;*: [page
1](articles/englander-holders.1.gif), [page
2](articles/englander-holders.2.gif), [page
3](articles/englander-holders.3.gif), [page
4](articles/englander-holders.4.gif) (gif files).\
by [Joe Englander](http://www.englander-workshops.com)
(jenglander@englander-workshops.com), Copyright 1995. *The article was
published in the April 1995 edition of C&amp;D, pages 52-7. The current
publication name is [Photo Techniques](http://www.phototechniques.com).\
Reproduced with the author&#39;s permission. Thanks to Gary Rowlands for
scanning.*\
There is a concern , raised by an article by Joe Englander in Camera and
Darkroom, that preloaded systems would give results less sharp than
conventional holders due to film flatness problems. He does a comparison
of focusing accuracy, and it&#39;s relationship to different film holders.
There are some very interesting shots made through the same lens (180
Apo Symmar) using both Velvia and T-MAX film. The resulting test
pictures show very obvious variations in sharpness. The best holder
(Grafmatic) is noticeably sharper than the Riteway holders that I
normally use. The Fuji QuickLoad, Kodak ReadyLoad, and Polaroid 545
trail in sharpness. The author explains that the ANSI standard for film
holder depth is .197&#34;. Most film is .007&#34; thick. In order to have the
ground glass in exactly the same plane as the film, the back of the film
holder should be at .190&#34;. The center depth of the Graphmatic was .189&#34;.
The Riteway measured .185&#34; on side one and .198&#34; on side 2. The other
holders with T-Max varied from .175&#34; to .205&#34;. The holders also varied
in corner-corner flatness. The test prints (admittedly based on flat
test images) showed some pretty dramatic correlation to his
measurements. **Todd Alleckson**

This is in regard to Kodak ReadyLoad holders. The sleeve, when pulled
out, stays within the &#34;throat&#34; of the holder, thus forcing the plate and
film back from their nominal location by the thickness of the sleeve
material AT THAT END. According to my measurements, Kodak did not
compensate for this discrepancy in the design of the holder. Therefore,
I shimmed my ground glass on that end by approx. .005&#34;, as I recall,
which seems to produce fine results. I usually make subtle adjustments
of the swing or tilt of the camera back anyway, which makes up for the
ground glass being out of whack with the lens axis. At least, I have the
confidence that what I see on the ground glass is the same as what hits
the film (aside from any warping or curling of the film). **Ken Schory**

According to my measurements, it&#39;s a lot worse than .005&#34;. The numbers
are at home, but I recall it being .215&#34; or more from the septum (at the
edge where the film is inserted vs. the desired .197&#34;. Furthermore, the
positioning of the film in the Readyload accross the entire film surface
is not as accurate as the Quickload or standard sheetfilm holder. I&#39;ve
seen some followup posts where people questioned the ability to focus
within .005&#34; or whether that difference would be noticable in the
results. If it&#39;s within .005&#34;, I think the error would be fairly benign.
However, I think the error is actually worse than this. In doing
comparison shots of actual scenes with the Readyload and Quickload
holders, there was no question that the Quickload produced sharper
results. This is really too bad as I would like to use some Kodak films
more frequently. **Dan Baum**

Back in April, when the article in C&amp;D came out, I spent some time using
a micrometer depth gauge to measure different film spacing in various
film holders: Polaroid 545, Kodak Readyload, conventional Fidelity,
Grafmatic. I found that my measurements agreed with the article: The
only two which conformed to the ANSI specs were the Grafmatic and the
conventional Fidelity with the Grafmatic being somewhat superior to the
Fidelity. The Kodak Readyload and Polaroid 545 both deviated from the
spec. I&#39;d remember the numbers off the top of my head. Shots of a test
target (glossy magazine page taped to a wall) confirmed the measurements
with slightly noticible differences between sheets exposed in the
various holders. I used an aperture of f/16 on my sharpest lens, a 135mm
APO-Symmar, as I recall. But then I set up for a couple of &#34;real world&#34;
scenes, using movements to optimize the the plane of focus and stopping
down for maximum DOF, and used the different methods of holding film. I
was utterly unable to distinguish between sheets exposed in the
different holders. I decided that there are enough other factors
degrading focus in the real world including variations in focus position
(I think of those who doubted that anyone can repeatedly set focus to
within .005&#34;), diffraction from stopping down to &#34;real world&#34; apertures
(not too often do I use f/16 as I did in the test target shots),
variations in setting of plane of focus, puffs of breeze, et alia, that
small variations in film placement don&#39;t seem terribly important. So
I&#39;ve continued to use Tmax in Readyloads and Fuji emulsions in
Quickloads in the Kodak Readyload holder. I did do a little shimming
which seerved to bring the center of the holder into the ANSI standard
range, but haven&#39;t felt bothered by softness of focus at the edge. On
the other hand, I fully believe that Dan obtained different results in
his tests. We each try things for ourselves and conclude our own
conclusions. **Barry Sherman**

### For the Picky: Quickloads vs. Regular Holders re Sharpness

By [Dan
Benjamin](mailto:ReverseOrderAndRepositionAt@net.att%20photoart93)
I haven&#39;t tried Readyloads nor the Fidelity Regular film holders, so my
test results technically apply only to the Quickload holder and several
Toyo Holders. However, based on earlier experiences with Fidelity
holders and other information I&#39;ve seen on this site and elsewhere, I do
feel it probably applies in general, that the results with regular film
holders will be superior to the packet holders, as far as desired
sharpness is concerned.

While perhaps most amateur and professional 4x5 photographers find
packet holders not only more convenient than regular holders, but find
that they give sufficiently sharp results (for most uses), my tests show
that where ultimate sharpness is desired, it&#39;s best to use regular
holders. Of course, sharpness is not the most important part of most
photographs, etc. - I am just saying that for those interested in such
matters, at times, the info below could be of value.

To be more specific, for those who don&#39;t print larger than 16x20 (from
4x5), or don&#39;t look at 16x20 prints extremely closely, and for those
those who usually need great depth-of-field that can&#39;t be taken care of
by movements (i.e. need f32 or smaller apertures), and for those who
find the decreased dust, lower weight, and general convenience of
Quickloads and Readyloads outweigh other considerations, what follows
won&#39;t matter (maybe that means 90%+ of the 4x5 shooters out there,, so
no reason to read further if you are one of them.

Here are the details of my results:

It may be known from other postings and articles on this large format
forum that regular film holders give a more consistently accurate or
flat film plane, than the packet type holders (Quickload, Readyload,
etc.). However, I didn&#39;t know how significant this was until I had
reason to obtain the sharpest possible result in a close up, and in
another case, of buildings in the distance. Using 10x and 20x loupes to
review my RVP 50 and Provia 100F transparencies shot with Quickloads, I
noticed areas of unsharpness that were at the same distance as other
areas that were sharp (although for the most part nothing looked totally
sharp). Thinking I didn&#39;t focus carefully enough, or the camera was not
aligned properly, or that there was something wrong with the camera, I
did some careful tests.

The tests: I used high quality lenses (for most of the shots I used
135mm Apo-Sironar S, 90mm f8 Nikkor, 300 f9M Nikkor lenses at f16-f22,
with some at f11 and f32, and a few comparisons with a 110mm XL),
focused carefully on different areas, using a 7x magnifier on the
groundglass of an Ebony 45SU, on two different subjects (one distant
landscape with fences and building signs, etc, and 12 foot distance
series of shots with several resolution targets on a wall). I shot more
than 30 comparisons on Velvia 50 and some on Provia 100F. I compared
exactly the same conditions - same focus tightly locked down and checked
after a series of shots, the same F-stop, same shutter speed, etc, even
the lighting was matched very well.

Viewing transparencies with a 4x loupe, comparing shots on the Quickload
vs Regular Film Holder, no difference can be seen if the f-stop was f22
or smaller (like f32) unless one looks very very carefully. With a 10x
loupe the difference is more easily noticeable. With a 20x loupe the
difference is glaringly apparent at a glance and the difference appears
to be large in many places on the transparency. The regular holder shots
always came out right on the money, whereas the Quickloads shots always
showed some areas of unsharpness.

For example I can easily read wording on signs and detail on objects
(detail that is contained WITHIN signs or other objects, the object or
signs themselves appear about 1/2 to 4mm on the transparency) on shots
made with the regular holder, but with the Quickloads shots the wording
or other detail is totally blurred, and nothing can be read/made-out.
Fence posts are blurred in most places (but not all) on the quickloads
shots, but uniformly sharp with regular holder shots. The difference
between shots with the two holder types decreases when diffraction comes
into play, which is around f32 for most lenses.

So what does it really matter anyway? For me, an amateur, if I&#39;m going
to the trouble of lugging LF gear, taking a lot of time and effort and
expense, most of the time I want the best results possible, regardless
of my subject or potential enlargements.

I now feel that one of the reasons some people feel that high-end
digital may appear to be superior in certain respects to medium format
cameras, and scanning backs superior to LF film up to maybe 8x10, is
that the imaging plane in the digital cameras/backs is totally flat and
very accurate; but not so with film (even 35mm and MF). When film is
scanned, which is probably a compromise in itself, and the film image
plane was already compromised by inaccuracy or unevenness, then the
digital to film comparison is going to be even worse (than if the film
image was made with a totally flat and accurate plane). Of course there
are many other factors involved in a digital capture vs film capture
debate, but sharpness is surely one of them.

For other factors involving whether to choose regular holders or
Quickloads, I&#39;ve found that in using regular holders I don&#39;t have to
worry about the packet waving in the breeze, and that it is quicker for
me to insert a regular holder, and then shoot, than with all the steps
involved with a Quickload - if the light is changing and I&#39;m trying the
get a shot off quickly this has come into play. However, if the
difference in sharpness between the two methods was closer, I &#39;d gladly
do 100% of my shooting with the packets, so as not to deal with dust,
nor limitations on how much film I can easily take with me on a shooting
outing due to weight and bulk.

After going thru this exercise I did find that another photographer, Ken
Rockwell, who has a website at www.kenrockwell.com, Ken Rockwell,
already came to a similar conclusion (about the sharpness difference)
long before I did. []{#more}

### More information

-   [Paul Butzi&#39;s film holder
    review](http://www.butzi.net/reviews/filmholders.htm)
-   [Paul Butzi&#39;s 4x5 packet systems
    review](http://www.butzi.net/reviews/readyquick.htm): includes a
    test of the new Kodak readyload system.

[View or add
comments](http://www.greenspun.com/com/qtluong/photography/lf/holders.html)

&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>http://lflf.surge.sh/equipment/lensboard_hole_sizes/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lflf.surge.sh/equipment/lensboard_hole_sizes/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h2 id=&#34;lensboard-hole-sizes&#34;&gt;Lensboard Hole Sizes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Compiled by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.rbarkerphoto.com&#34;&gt;Ralph Barker&lt;/a&gt; for
&lt;a href=&#34;.&#34;&gt;largeformatphotography.info&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;ForstnerBit.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;Forstner Bit&#34; /&gt;{width=&amp;ldquo;225&amp;rdquo; height=&amp;ldquo;115&amp;rdquo;}Having
lensboards precision-bored with a machinist&amp;rsquo;s lathe may be the next best
thing to buying lensboards pre-bored by the manufacturer. Metal boards
(aluminum or mild sheet steel) can be easily drilled with reasonable
accuracy, however, with a good hole saw in a drill press. Similarly, a
good Forstner bit of the right size works well for wooden lensboards.
Careful sanding or filing of the hole may be necessary for a proper fit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Forstner bits in sizes up to 2&amp;rdquo; are fairly common at better woodworking
supply stores. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.router-bits-shaper-cutters.com/information/cfb.cfm&#34;&gt;Woodshed Tools,
Inc.&lt;/a&gt;
also carries sizes up to 3&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Brand&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;# Size&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hole Size - mm&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hole Size - Inches&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Nearest fractional size&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Comments, lenses&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Compur&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;#00&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;26.3mm&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;#0&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;34.6mm&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1.362&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1 &lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;8&lt;/sub&gt;&amp;rdquo; = 1.375&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;#1&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;41.6mm&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1.638&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1 &lt;sup&gt;5&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;8&lt;/sub&gt;&amp;rdquo; = 1.625&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;#2&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;52.5mm&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;oddball&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;#3&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;65mm&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2.559&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2 &lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Copal&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;#0&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;34.6mm&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1.362&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1 &lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;8&lt;/sub&gt;&amp;rdquo; = 1.375&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;#1&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;41.6mm&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1.638&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1 &lt;sup&gt;5&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;8&lt;/sub&gt;&amp;rdquo; = 1.625&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;#3&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;65mm&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2.559&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2 &lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ilex&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;#3&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;50.42mm&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1.985&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1 &lt;sup&gt;7&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;8&lt;/sub&gt;&amp;rdquo; = 1.875&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kodak 10&amp;rdquo; Comm Ektar f/6.3&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;#3 dial set&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1.985&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;#4&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;66.14mm&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2.604&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2 &lt;sup&gt;5&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;8&lt;/sub&gt;&amp;rdquo; = 2.625&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kodak 12&amp;rdquo; Comm Ektar f/6.3&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;#4 dial set&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2.604&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;#5&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;85.47mm&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;3.365&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;3 &lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;8&lt;/sub&gt;&amp;rdquo; = 3.375&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kodak 14&amp;rdquo; Comm Ektar f/6.3&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Prontor&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;#0&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;34.6mm&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;#1&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;41.6mm&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;#3&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;65mm&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>http://lflf.surge.sh/equipment/lenses-general/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lflf.surge.sh/equipment/lenses-general/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Large format lenses: generalities, classic vs modern issue&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;large-format-lenses-generalities-classic-vs-modern&#34;&gt;Large format lenses: generalities, classic vs modern&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;By &lt;a href=&#34;mailto:sparks@col.hp.com&#34;&gt;John Sparks&lt;/a&gt; for &lt;a href=&#34;.&#34;&gt;the Large Format
Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;basic-lens-questions&#34;&gt;Basic lens questions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;what-is-the-difference-between-symetrical-and-asymetrical&#34;&gt;What is the difference between symetrical and asymetrical?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A symetrical lens has two identical lens groups on either side of the
shutter facing in opposite directions. Several lens abberations are
automatically eliminated by symmetrical design (only at 1:1) so it&amp;rsquo;s a
popular lens design, especially before the days of computers when all
the lens caculations were done by hand. The symmetrical designs require
fewer computations to design. If truely symmetrical, the lens will
perform best at 1:1. Asymetrical designs are all designs that are not
symmetrical. Today, almost all lenses are at least somewhat asymetrical
(the only exceptions I know of are lenses like the G-Claron, Apo-Ronar
and other lenses optimized for use at 1:1). Any lens that is truely
designed for distant subjects must be at least somewhat asymetrical.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is nothing fundamental that makes symetrical or asymetrical
designs better than the other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;what-is-the-difference-between-coated-and-non-coated&#34;&gt;What is the difference between coated and non-coated?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coatings are applied to all air/glass interfaces to reduce the
reflections off these interfaces. This reduces flare and increases
contrast. There are actually three types, non-coated, single coated and
multicoated. Single coating was first developed in 1936 and most lenses
made since WWII have been at least single coated. Multicoating was
developed later (late 60&amp;rsquo;s or early 70&amp;rsquo;s??) and most current lenses are
multicoated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The biggest advantage to coatings is to allow the lens designer to make
more complex lens designs with more air/glass interfaces. More complex
designs can decrease abberations giving a sharper lens or a lens with
more coverage. For the fairly simple designs used by most large format
lenses, the difference between single and multi-coatings is relatively
small but the difference between uncoated and single-coated is
significant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The best lens designs before coatings were only 2 or 3 lens groups (the
number of groups indicates the numbers of air spaces, each group is a
set of lens elements that are cemented together with no air spaces).
Modern large format lenses are mostly 4 groups and some (particularly
wide angles which need better corrections to get their wider coverage)
have 5 or 6 groups or more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Multicoating&amp;rsquo;s real contribution was to allow the 12 to 15 group zoom
lenses possible. Without multicoating, these lenses would be unusably
low contrast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;what-is-the-significance-of-elements-and-groups&#34;&gt;What is the significance of elements and groups?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not very much just from the numbers. More elements and groups allow more
degrees of freedom for the lens designer to make a better corrected
lens, but with care and some limitations (like small maximum aperature
or small coverage), very good lenses can be made with few elements and
groups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I wrote above, more groups means more air-spaces and requires better
coatings. The best of the large format lenses priar to coatings had only
2 groups (like the Dagor and Protar) or maybe 3 groups like the Tessar.
The Dagor and Protars have good coverage, but are only really sharp at
f/16 or small aperatures while the Tessars are good at relatively wide
aperatures but with limited coverage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After coatings were developed, most lenses were 4 groups (with a few 3
group tessars still around and some 5 or 6 group lenses) as this gives a
better corrected design for a faster lens with good coverage like the
current plasmats with 70-80 degree coverage that are very sharp even
wide open.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;classic-vs-modern-lenses&#34;&gt;Classic vs Modern lenses&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think &amp;ldquo;modern&amp;rdquo; means: maximizing coverage, multicoating, computer
design, modern glass choices, good sharpness at all aperatures rather
than requiring the f/22 to f/45 needed for good sharpness with older
lenses. They will be sharper lenses, especially when you can avoid
diffraction effects from stopping way down. Any wide angle by Nikkon or
Fuji, Rodenstock Grandagons and Schneider Super Angulons are the
&amp;ldquo;modern&amp;rdquo; wide angle lenses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s some stuff written about older lenses in the view camera book by
Steve Simmons. There&amp;rsquo;s also been a lot in various back issues of View
Camera and Darkroom Techniques magazines (especially articles by Ron
Wisner who knows a great deal about older lenses). Anyway for a brief
overview, your best bet is to get used lenses of current or almost
current designs. There was a big revolution in the 50&amp;rsquo;s in 60&amp;rsquo;s of
computer designed multicoated lenses that really perform much better
than the older lenses. This is especially true for 4x5. Larger formats
require less enlargment, smaller aperatures with their greater
diffraction so differences between lenses matters less. With really
large format and contact printing only you can use almost any lens you
can find that covers the format. Any Fuji or Nikkor lens can be
considered modern as can most by Schneider or Rodenstock.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For more specific answers, I&amp;rsquo;ll divide the lenses into three groups,
wideangles, normals and long lenses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Wideangles: Here more than anywhere, modern lenses are really the
best. These are Schneider Super Angulon, Rodenstock Grandagon,
Nikkor SW and Fuji NSWS. Schneider introduced their first Super
Angulons in the mid 50&amp;rsquo;s so there are quite a few older ones out
there (the others are newer but still turn up used). The older ones
have some chrome rather than the current all black housings so look
older, sell for less but preform pretty much the same. The older
wide angles that work fairly well are Schneider Angulons, Wide-angle
Dagors and Wide-field Ektars. This is in order of decreasing
coverage, the Angulons at 90mm and the Wide-field Ektars at 135mm
work fairly well on 4x5 (though less coverage than a modern wide
angle).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Normal lenses: The current and almost current normal lenses are
Schneider Apo-Symmar, Symmar-S, Rodenstock any Sironar, Nikkor W,
Fuji NWS, WS and W. Older lenses that work fairly well are Symmar,
Dagor, Protar, Commercial Ektar. I&amp;rsquo;m sure I&amp;rsquo;m leaving out quite a
few usable lenses.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Long Lenses: Many of the normal lenses come in longer versions
(especially for formats smaller than 8x10). There are also some
other lenses that can be used here that don&amp;rsquo;t cover enough for
normal lens use. The modern examples are Nikkor M, Fuji CS,
Schneider G-Clarons and Artars, Rodenstock Apo-Ronars. The best of
the older long lenses are Goerz Apo-Artars (the Red Dot Artars were
coated but not multicoated, older Artars were not).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All the lenses I currently use are modern lenses. I have one older 135mm
lens from a press camera that actually works pretty well for B&amp;amp;W. It has
very limited coverage on 4x5 and much lower contrast that my other
lenses, but with B&amp;amp;W I can increase contast pretty easily to compensate
for it. 16x20 prints from 4x5 negatives don&amp;rsquo;t look less sharp than from
my other lenses, but I&amp;rsquo;d guess I have to print on 1-2 grades higher
contrast paper. I have made a few transparencies with it but the shutter
is erratic enough that getting good exposures was difficult. The colors
are quite a bit less saturated than from modern lenses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For 4x5, I generally prefer modern lenses, though the best of the older
lenses still perform well. With many older lenses you will get much
sharper results with a yellow filter (many were designed when films were
ortho or blue sensitive). Color requires only the best of old lenses or
modern ones (older lenses will give softer more pastel renderings
compared to modern saturated ones). With larger formats, older lenses
may be the best or only choice and the smaller or no enlargment means
less resolution is required. I have several older lenses I use on 8x10
though I can tell the difference even here compared to modern ones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Have you ever made the same photograph with a modern lens and an older
good uncoated lens of similar photographs. I have (in B&amp;amp;W). From seeing
the results, I don&amp;rsquo;t think I could pick a given print and say which lens
made that photograph, but given two prints made of the same subject with
modern and older lenses, it&amp;rsquo;s quite clear which one is which. In color,
I think I could even pick which lens was which without the side by side
comparison (though the older lenses may yield pleasing images in color).
The biggest problem with using older lenses with color (particularly
color transparencies) is the questionable accuracy and repeatabiliy of
old shutters. The ones I&amp;rsquo;ve owned vary enough that getting accurately
exposed transparencies, even with wide bracketing, is very hit or miss.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, I&amp;rsquo;m talking here about old uncoated lenses. With last generation
modern multicoated non-apo lenses compared to the current apo lenses,
I&amp;rsquo;m not sure I could pick which is which in side by side comparisions.
There is very little difference between a Apo-Symmar and Symmar-S for
example. The Apo lens is very slightly sharper, but you probably get
more sharpness variations from film position in the holder than the
difference between these two lenses (or similar lenses from other
manufacturers).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I a lot of cases, older shutters have more problems than older lenses.
Shutters can be replaced, but often cost more than an older lens is
worth. A shutter who&amp;rsquo;s speeds are off (almost all older shutters) is not
a problem as long as the speeds are consistant (you just need to have
the speeds checked and use the actual speeds instead of the marked
speeds). An eratic shutter is useless.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Small scratches or &amp;ldquo;cleaning marks&amp;rdquo; have no real effect on image quality
and mean much lower prices, but cloudy areas or other marks covering a
fairly large area of the lens will reduce contrast and resolution (try
to think of the mark as a percentage of the surface of the lens, a
scratch covering 1% or less of the lens will have almost unnoticable
effect while one covering &lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; of the lens is much worse).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;importance-of-corrections-by-richard-knoppow-mailto-dickburk-ix-netcom-com&#34;&gt;Importance of corrections by &lt;a href=&#34;mailto:dickburk@ix.netcom.com&#34;&gt;Richard Knoppow&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are two issues here, aberrations and coating. Coating first.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coating prevents flare. Flare can be either an overall haze or ghost
images. If we consider the haze only, its effect is to lower the
contrast of the shadow areas of the image. In B&amp;amp;W this can be
compensated for satisfactorily (if there is not too much flare) by using
short toe film (high contrast in the shadows) and simply developing or
printing for a little more contrast. In color, the haze, because it is
mixture of all the light recieved by the lens, tends to reduce the
saturation of all colors. There is less flexibility with color film for
correcting this sort of fault. None, really with reversal materials.
Also, since single coatings are more effective at some color than
others, it may result in a slight color cast, which, because it is due
to a colored haze, isn&amp;rsquo;t easy to correct in any simple way. Multiple
coatings have much more even reduction of reflected light so improve the
color rendition as well as saturation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The kind of flare that is manifested as ghose images or hot-spots is
much more damaging to images whether B&amp;amp;W or color and are more due to
the lens design than coating although coating will either reduce them or
get rid of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ghost images or images of the diaphragm have much more to do with the
design of the lens than with coatings, although coating will reduce the
effect when it is present. I have several old, uncoated lenses which do
not produce ghost images. The main effect of lens flare is to generate
an overall glow, which tends to fill in shadow areas and reduce the
saturation and purity of colors in color photography, and to produce
halos or flary areas around bright objects. While the advise of often
given to use lens shades to reduce flare of uncoated lenses, a lens
shade has no effect on light going into the lens to produce an image.
They are mainly useful in cutting off non-image light which causes flare
by bouncing around inside the camera. Multiple layer coating extends the
range of colors over which the coating is effective. A single layer is
effective at a single color and its effect falls off on either side of
that paticular wave length. Because the range of colors used in normal
photography or visually is only about an octave, a single coating is
practical. Multiple coatings have a broader band of effectiveness. By
using several coatings of the right materials and thicknesses it is
possible to make the lens surfaces nearly completely non-reflective over
pretty much the entire bandwidth used for photography. For those with
backgrounds in electronics coating is related to filter theory and
transmission line theory. Essentially, a coating forms an impedance
matching section between the air and glass. The fewer glass-air
interfaces there are in the lens the less the effect of coating will
have on its performance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lens with residual aberrations may actually be _less_ noticeable
with color than with B&amp;amp;W! This is because of the phychology of seeing.
The brain interprets color images as having more detail in them than
they do (this is why color television is possible). Also, even when an
obvious color fringing is present, the fringes, in the case of lateral
color, will be sharp, and the eye will see the image as sharp, whereas
the same image in B&amp;amp;W will have all the colors integrated in the image
which will look blurred. Even box cameras will take surprizingly good
looking color pictures. Where panchormatic film is used, as is the
almost universal practice today, a lens with superior color correction
will make superior images in B&amp;amp;W as well as color. Many older lenses, (I
mean the 70+ year ones) were designed with the assumption that ortho
film would be used, and the acromatic correction was made toward the
blue end because that&amp;rsquo;s what the film recorded. More modern acormat
design moved the colors more toward the yellow for panchormatic film.
Also, modern glass types (post 1940) permit much smaller overall
chromatic deviations regardless of the wavelengths chosen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The argument about the definition of apochromatic and whether certain
lenses are really apo&amp;rsquo;s is somewhat silly. The real issue is the maximum
deviation of the corrections at any color. Where a lens is to be used
only with very sharp selective filters, the correction at specific
wavelengths that correspond to the filters may be enough for perfect
images but that is not a very common condition. The generic definition
of color correction is that an acromatic lens is corrected for two
colors, an apochromatic one three colors, and a superchromatic one for
four or more. Modern lens design permits the designer to correct for any
number of colors although there is, of course, a point of diminishing
returns in cost vs: performance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Warren Smith demonstrates in his book on design that a properly designed
acromat may have better overall chromatic correction than an apochromat.
He also demonstrates the design of superchromats.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rodenstock and other manufacturers now use an ISO definition of
apochromatic that is based on the lens having very small deviations from
ideal. This may nott be in agreement with the rigorous definition used
for microscope objectives but nonetheless, the performance, even for
color separation purposes is likely to be superior to a &amp;ldquo;true
apochromat&amp;rdquo; which is what matters. I suspect these lense are actually
superchromats. The ISO standard, or rather, family of standards, which
specifies this definition runs into a huge number of documents to which
I haven&amp;rsquo;t got access.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.greenspun.com/com/qtluong/photography/lf/lenses-general.html&#34;&gt;View or add
comments&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>http://lflf.surge.sh/equipment/lenses4x5/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lflf.surge.sh/equipment/lenses4x5/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Lenses for 4x5 cameras -landscape&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;lenses-for-4x5-cameras-landscape&#34;&gt;Lenses for 4x5 cameras - landscape&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;by John Sparks and Kerry Thalmann for &lt;a href=&#34;.&#34;&gt;the Large Format Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Here are listed the favorite lenses picked by two experienced landscape
photographers. Note how similar their choices are !&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;john-sparks-pick&#34;&gt;John Sparks&amp;rsquo; pick&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With current lenses from Nikon, Schneider, Rodenstock and Fuji there is
very little difference between the performance of similar lenses. The
variation between samples of the same lense may well be greater than the
difference between similar lenses from different manufacturers. With
that said, there are a few differences that exist because some
particular lenses are only made by one or two manufacturers. What I
would choose for the above focal lengths for landscape work where weight
and size of the lenses is generally more important than max coverage or
other criteria would be as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;90mm -  Nikkor SW f/8, this is lens has the most coverage of any f/8 90mm.
    The f/8 is important because it keeps the size/weight of the lens
    down.

120mm   Schneider Super Symmar f/5.6.  Again this is the smallest 120mm
    lens that has enough coverage for moderate movements.  It is
    much smaller and lighter than the true wide angles like the
    Super Angulon or the Nikkor SW.  Those are only really
    appropriate for studio work or architecture or larger formats
    where the larger coverage is really important or the size/weight
    doesn&#39;t matter.

    Alternately, I might choose a Rodenstock 135mm Sironar-S.  This
    isn&#39;t all that different in angle of view from a 120, but is
    even smaller than the Super Symmar and probably eliminates the
    need for having both 120mm and 150mm.  The Sironar-S is because
    it has the largest coverage of any current 135mm and all the
    current 135mm&#39;s are a bit short on coverage.

150mm   Any one of Nikkor-W, Fuji-NWS, Schneider Apo-Symmar or
    Rodenstock Sironar-N or -S.  These don&#39;t vary much in size or
    weight and the performance is all pretty much the same.  I might
    choose the Sironar-S again because a little more coverage at
    this focal length might help and it doesn&#39;t cost too much in
    size or dollars.  Rodenstock says that the Sironar-S lenses are
    the sharpest ones they sell and are at least the equal if not
    better than anything else out there (though the differences will
    be pretty small compared to the others in this list expecially
    at the f/22 &amp;amp; f/32 I usually use with 4x5 for landscapes).
    However, any of the lenses listed will be the sharpest lens you
    own (unless you get a 135mm version and a 120mm Super Symmar
    would be a pretty close call).  For the same basic design,
    shorter lenses will always be slightly sharper than longer
    lenses and 135mm/150mm is the shortest &amp;quot;normal&amp;quot; lens design
    usable on 4x5.  Wide angle lenses trade off sharpness for more
    coverage so will be slightly less sharp than longer lenses.

210mm   Same list as for 150mm except I probably wouldn&#39;t choose the
    Sironar-S here because it starts to make a real difference in
    size and weight and any of these 210mm&#39;s will have plenty of
    coverage.  I&#39;d probably choose which ever of these weighs the
    least (I think it&#39;s the Nikkor), but it won&#39;t make much
    difference.

    As an alternative, I might choose a 210mm Schneider G-Claron or
    200mm Nikkor M instead.  These are light, tiny lenses that
    probably have enough coverage for 4x5 landscapes.  The Nikkor is
    smaller and may be slightly sharper and contrastier because it&#39;s
    multicoated and optimized for distant subjects (the G-Claron is
    single coated and designed for use at 1:1).  The G-Claron does
    have more coverage which might be useful.  I&#39;d chose one of these
    if I planned on backpacking with the camera and probably one of
    the others if I rarely carried the camera more than a couple of 
    miles.

300mm   The best choice here is the Nikkor M.  It is very sharp, optimized
    for distant subjects, plenty of coverage for most uses and quite
    small.  I might choose a G-Claron if I planned to switch to 8x10
    at some point because of its greater coverage, but I&#39;m using a 
    Nikkor M 300mm on 8x10 now with little trouble.  Any other 300mm
    is way too huge and heavy for almost all 4x5 needs.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;kerry-thalmann-s-future-classics&#34;&gt;Kerry Thalmann&amp;rsquo;s Future Classics&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Basically, what I was wondering is: which of the large format lenses in
current, or recent, production are destined to become highly sought
after classics decades after they are no longer being made. We all know
about the Dagors. Which are still highly prized (especially those with
serial numbers higher than 770xxx, Gold Dot Dagors and Wide Angle
Dagors). The Red Dot Artars are also very highly regarded and always in
demand in the longer focal lengths. Kodak is well represented with the
Commercial and Wide Field Ektars. And the Voigtlander APO Lanthar
commands ridiculously high prices (this one, frankly baffles me). There
are more, but these are representative of the lenses that are currently
highly prized classics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What makes a classic? Well, in many cases these older lenses offer
something not found in the current product lines from the few remaining
large format lens manufacturers. Some offer large coverage in a small
package (Dagors and Wide Field Ektars). Others offer outstanding
performance at a much lower cost than their modern counterparts
(Commercial Ektars). And some come in focal lengths not available in the
current crop of large format optics (long focal length Artars). The real
key, is that they fill a need, and are highly suited to specific
applications (ultra large and banquet formats where large coverage
and/or long focal lengths are needed, or field photography where small
size and weight are important factors).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With that in mind, what current lenses do you think are destined to be
future classics? To get the ball rolling, I&amp;rsquo;ll toss out a few from my
current stable of lenses. I currently shoot landscapes in 4x5 and 6x17
formats using color transparency film. Obviously, someone who shoots
12x20 black and white will have a different opinion, so it would help if
you would state your format and media of choice along with a brief
summary of the reasoning behind your choices. Perhaps if we can all
agree on a few of these future classics we can hoard a few away to
finance the college educations of our grandchildren or great
grandchildren.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;90mm f8 Nikkor SW
The lightest of all modern (Biogon derivative) multi-coated 90mm wide
angle lenses.  It is an excellent performer, with great coatings (NIC).
It&#39;s relatively compact size and lightweight (lighter than the 90mm
Super Angulon and 90mm f6.8 Grandagon-N) making it a favorite for 4x5
field photography.  It also has substantially greater coverage (235mm)
than the other compact (slow) modern 90mm wide angles.

120mm f5.6 Schneider Super Symmar HM
Another lens I feel is destined to be a classic for 4x5 field
photographers.  It is really the only modern lens in the desirable 120mm
focal length that is best suited for this application (the 120mm APO
Symmar is lacking in coverage at 179mm, the 115mm Grandagon-N, 120mm
Nikkor SW and 120mm Super Angulon are really 5x7 wide angles and
therefore much larger and heavier).  It is not a tiny lens, but it
weighs about 1/2 the 115mm Grandagon-N.  This one could be shoved aside
by the new 110mm Super Symmar XL (which again is more of a 5x7 wide
angle, but small enough to be favored by 4x5 shooters as well).  BTW,
personally, I love this lens for 6x17cm and it is currently mounted on
my home made 6x17 point and shoot.

150mm f5.6 Rodenstock APO Sironar-S
This is a wonderful little lens.  Compact, lightweight and more coverage
(231mm) than the other 150mm 4x5 lenses (I consider the larger 150mm APO
Sironar-W and 150mm Super Symmar HM to be overkill for 4x5 landscapes
and better suited for the 5x7 format in that application).  It uses ED
glass and is incredibly sharp all the way to edges, and even at large
stops (I have found it to be incredibly sharp even wide open, and have
read at least one test report that showed it to achieve maximum LPM at
f5.6 - which is where it should be sharpest in theory, but in practice
is rarely true).  I don&#39;t know what it is about this lens, but images
made with it just scream SHARP! and have an incredible sense of
&amp;quot;depth&amp;quot;.  I&#39;ve used a lot 4x5 &amp;quot;normal&amp;quot; lenses, both modern and classic,
and this one beats them all IMHO.  Out of all the lenses I own, this is
the last one I would ever part with (you&#39;ll have to pry it from my cold,
dead hands).

300mm f9 Nikkor M
Another tiny gem of a lens.  Small, sharp, contrasty.  What else could
you ask for in a long focal length field lens for 4x5.  Variation of the
classic Tessar design, but with modern multi-coatings and a modern Copal
shutter.

360mm f8/500mm f11 Nikkor T-ED
Two great long focal lengths in one and a half lenses.  ED glass, true
telephoto design.  Extremely sharp for a telephoto (as good or better
than most &amp;quot;standard designs for distant subjects).  360mm focal length
useable with short bellows (~12&amp;quot;) field cameras.  500mm length useable
with about 16&amp;quot; of bellows.  720mm option also available if you want a
really long 4x5 lens and have a long bellows monorail or field camera
(Wisner or Canham).  This baby is already in hot demand on the used
market.  Imagine what it will be like when they haven&#39;t been made for 20
or 30 years.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s my short list. Since I don&amp;rsquo;t have my 110mm XL yet, I&amp;rsquo;ll leave
others to comment on that one. Also, I did not nominate anything in my
favorite focal length, 210mm. I use a 210mm Nikkor W and love it, but
I&amp;rsquo;m not really sure if it offers any advantages over the current 210mm
offerings from Schneider or Rodenstock. I also didn&amp;rsquo;t nominate any of
the ultra wide Super Angulon XL series. I&amp;rsquo;m amazed by their tremendous
image circles and coverage angles, but as a field photographer
specializing in landscapes the coverage seems overkill and the huge size
(and very huge price tag and huger still filter sizes) are big
turn-offs. Perhaps someone who does 4x5 architectural work will offer s
dissenting opinion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, let&amp;rsquo;s hear from everyone else. I&amp;rsquo;d like to hear from other 4x5
shooters to learn their favorites and find out what they think of my
choices. I&amp;rsquo;d also like to hear from the 8x10 shooters, and especially
the ultra large and banquet shooters. They are the ones who, out of
necessity and practicality, seem to rely most heavily on using classic
optics. What do they think will happen 50 - 100 years down the road when
it is even harder to find those long focal length Dagors? Let me know
what you think.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;more-information&#34;&gt;More information&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kerry has a new &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.thalmann.com/largeformat/future.htm&#34;&gt;updated list with
photos&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;view-or-add-comments-http-www-greenspun-com-com-qtluong-photography-lf-lenses4x5-html&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.greenspun.com/com/qtluong/photography/lf/lenses4x5.html&#34;&gt;View or add comments&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>http://lflf.surge.sh/equipment/lenses5x7/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lflf.surge.sh/equipment/lenses5x7/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Modern lenses for 5x7 cameras&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;modern-lenses-for-5x7-cameras&#34;&gt;Modern Lenses for 5x7 cameras&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.terragalleria.com/&#34;&gt;Q.-Tuan Luong&lt;/a&gt; for &lt;a href=&#34;.&#34;&gt;the Large
Format Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here I survey the modern lenses that I know to be suitable for the 5x7
format. Depending on the use of the camera, and the intended result,
there are many choices possible which are not mentionned here. In
particular I don&amp;rsquo;t discuss older lenses, or current but little-known
lenses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;wide-angle-lenses&#34;&gt;Wide-angle lenses&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;72:&lt;/strong&gt; The new Schneider Super Angulon XL. It will just cover 5x7
with no movements. Equivalent to a 14mm in 35mm, it is one of the
widest lenses (with the 47XL on 4x5) which can be used on any LF
camera.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;90:&lt;/strong&gt; Older lenses such as the Angulon. won&amp;rsquo;t cover the format.
Among modern lenses each manufacturer offers a fast (4.5 or 5.6) and
a slow (6.7 or 8) lenses. The first ones are easier to focus and
offer generally more coverage, but they are bulkier, take larger
filters, and cost two times more. Among them the new Schneider Super
Angulon XL offers significantly more coverage. Among the f8 lenses,
the Nikkor SW offers significantly more coverage (identical to all
the fast lenses but the Super Angulon XL). The other f8 lenses just
cover the format with almost no movements. Therefore the two lenses
mentionned are recommended. If you don&amp;rsquo;t need extensive coverage,
you&amp;rsquo;ll be better of with the Nikkor. Equivalent: 18mm.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;120:&lt;/strong&gt; Older lenses (ie Angulons) just cover the format. Among the
modern offerings, the Nikkor SW has the most coverage, being
actually sufficient for 8x10, but the others are also very adequate.
Schneider is releasing a new Super-Symmar &lt;sup&gt;110&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;5&lt;/sub&gt;.6 XL aspheric which
is half the size of a Super-Angulon (the oldest design), sharper,
and actually covers 8x10. This terrific lens costs \$2300 at B&amp;amp;H in
NYC, but it can be found in Europe (and through some
grey-marketters) for less than \$1300. Equivalent: 24mm.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;135:&lt;/strong&gt; I know no modern lens of this focal with enough coverage.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;150:&lt;/strong&gt; The modern plasmats (Symmars, Nikkor W, Sironars&amp;hellip;) will
cover the format with little to no movements. I have a 150
Apo-Sironar-S which covers with so little movements that most of the
time I don&amp;rsquo;t bother using it. The discontinued Apo-Sironar-W has
larger coverage, in a relatively compact package. The Super-Symmar
has lost a lot of his appeal since the Super-Symmar XL was
introduced. The traditional design wide-angles (Super-Angulons,
Nikkor SW, Grandagons&amp;hellip;) will be plenty for 8x10 or more but they
are extremely big and expensive, and therefore not recommended for
5x7. Equivalent: 35mm&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;normal-lenses&#34;&gt;Normal lenses&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;210&lt;/strong&gt;: Plenty of good choices among the plasmats with adequate
coverage. Since this is a popular focal length for 4x5 it is easy to
find used lenses. The focal is equivalent to a 42mm (like the normal
lens of a Rollei 35) which is slighly shorter than normal, but I
find it better in LF to be too short than too long since you can
crop without losing quality.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;240&lt;/strong&gt;: Plenty of choices among the plasmats with adequate
coverage. They are bigger (#3 shutter) and significantly more
expensive and rarer than 210, and therefore I would favor more
compact designs such as the G-Claron or the Fuji A which are also
very good. Equivalent to 50mm.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;300&lt;/strong&gt;: The plasmats are too big and expensive and would be
recommended only for ultra-large formats (larger than 8x10). The
best choices are narrow field lenses such as Nikkor M, G-Clarons,
Apo-Ronars, which are all quite small. The Nikkor M (covers just
8x10) has been recommended by many, however the G-Claron has more
coverage and could be a better choice if you intend to shoot 8x10 as
well. The Apo-ronar has the smallest coverage of all (does not cover
8x10) Equivalent to 60mm.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;long-lenses&#34;&gt;Long lenses&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;355-400&lt;/strong&gt;: Schneider Tele-Xenar, Fuji-T. Both are telephotos which
will cover little more than the format and are somewhat big. Not
particularly recommended, unless your 5x7 camera doesn&amp;rsquo;t have enough
bellows for this focal (most do). G-Claron, Apo Ronar: narrow field
lenses, but in #3 shutter which makes them much bigger than the
300mm lenses. They will cover 8x10. Equivalent: 70-80mm.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;450-480&lt;/strong&gt;: Narrow field lenses. The apo ronar is the heaviest. The
highly regarded Nikkor M is reasonable but has also a #3 shutter.
The Fuji C is in a #1 shutter, which makes it as small and light as
a 300, and is also very well regarded. Cover 11x14. Equivalent 90mm.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;600&lt;/strong&gt;: Fuji has the only non-telephoto lens in this focal, as well
as the only telephoto to fit in a #1 shutter. Equivalent 120mm.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;up&lt;/strong&gt;: The first series of Nikon telephotos 360-500-720 barely
covers the format according to Nikon. The second series of Nikon
telephotos 600-800(-1200) is huge and weights a ton. Apart from
these, and a couple of exotic lenses with astronomical prices (Apo
Tele Xenars), the only lenses are older designs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For more details, see the &lt;a href=&#34;lenses-long.html&#34;&gt;general discussion on long lenses for
4x5&lt;/a&gt;, since at this focals they will (almost) all
cover 5x7.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.greenspun.com/com/qtluong/photography/lf/lenses5x7.html&#34;&gt;View or add
comments&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>http://lflf.surge.sh/equipment/lfpacks/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lflf.surge.sh/equipment/lfpacks/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;backpacks for large format cameras&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;backpacks-for-large-format-cameras&#34;&gt;Backpacks for large format cameras&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Compiled by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.terragalleria.com/&#34;&gt;Tuan&lt;/a&gt; for &lt;a href=&#34;.&#34;&gt;the Large
Format Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;why-you-need-one&#34;&gt;Why you need one&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Edward Weston said that there were no truly photogenic subjects which
couldn&amp;rsquo;t be seen from the road. Although I am a montaineer, I have come
to somewhat agree with this conclusion. I have backpacked a few times
with my LF gear without finding something which really inspired me, so
that i ended up shooting just a couple of bad photos because I wanted to
justify having carried the gear so far. In general, if my purpose is
purely photography, I have found that it is more efficient to drive
around and do short hikes than to take long hikes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That said, I still find that the only practical way to carry my large
format system is to use a backpack. The fact that you see it from the
road does not mean that you photograph it from the road. Even on a short
hike of a half-mile, having to carry a case is a pain, esp. if you are
not on a good trail. They really work well only for shooting next to the
car. On the other hand, put the same weight on a good backpack, and you
can carry it comfortably for hours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition, there are actually a large number of natural areas which
can be reached only by hiking. A few examples are the mountain scenery
in parks such as sequoia/kings canyon, north cascades, guadalupe
mountains, the bottom of most canyons in the southwest, including
narrows, the paria, slot canyons, the grand canyon, havasu, etc&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With LF, you often end up with more accesories that you think. Some
photographers (like me) also carry other formats as well. It&amp;rsquo;s good to
have some room for additional outdoor gear, food and water, so I don&amp;rsquo;t
think it is a good idea to find a backpack which just fits your LF gear
with no room to spare.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t try to guess whether a given backpack will work for you. Take all
your gear to a couple stores. Test fit it in as many different packs as
you can, and watch how easily you can get it out of the packs. Try on
the loaded pack and walk around the store. Pay close attention to how
well the pack fits you and how well the weight seems to be distributed.
Too much weight on the shoulders can be very painful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;general-purpose-backpacks&#34;&gt;General purpose backpacks&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The suspension systems of the hiking/climbing packs is considerably
better than the suspension system of cameras backpack of similar
capacity. I used for several years a climbing backpack, a Gregory Big
Wally. It weighted less than 4lbs, was compact enough to carry-on, and
has been used to ferry (non-photographic) loads in excess of 70 pounds
(yes, climbing hardware for big walls is heavy).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can customize exactly the backpack for your needs. Some people use
foam that they cut. I use additional cases inside. My (wrapped) lenses
and wide angle bellows are in an Artic Zone cooler, and my film holders
are in an Artic Zone lunch bag (Artic Zone makes great camera gear :-)).
Accessories are in small outdoor research pouches which go in the lid
pocket with the shade. My system (5x7, holders, 4 or 5 LF lenses,
accessories, N90 + 1-3 lenses, tripod) weights only around 25lbs. There
is enough room for plenty of clothing, or the 4x5 and polaroid back with
an extra box of Quickloads.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is to say that for volume/carrying comfort/weight this system was
excellent. The problem was that it is only top-load so that accessing
equipment is a bit slow, and my stuff ends up all over the place if I am
not careful. However, this doesn&amp;rsquo;t need to be the case. Although most of
the backpacks are top-loaders, there are still a few panel loaders.
Check in particular among the Dana Designs and Gregory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently I upgraded to a Dana Designs Swiftcurrent. This is quite a bit
bigger and heavier (6lbs), but it is panel-loading, has a great usable
volume, the panel system is handy for stowing the tripod and the
carrying comfort is just great.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are some other suggestions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I took all my camera gear to a backpacking store and found a front
loading pack that fit me and was large enough to hold everything (I
actually have two, both Gregory packs, one for the 4x5 and a larger
one for 8x10). There are not many front loading backpacks, but they
do exist. The Gregory packs fit me better than any photo backpacks
I&amp;rsquo;ve ever tried on (most of which are way too short for me and have
really lousy waistbelts. Even really good camping backpacks seem to
cost only about half what the photo backpacks cost. For the 4x5, I
made an insert out of a cut up foam backpacking matress covered in
nylon pack cloth on the outside and some kind of padded interior
that velcro sticks to. Before I made that, I kept my lenses wrapped
in foam in rubbermaid containers and had various sacks and other
rubbermaid stuff for holding everything else. The 8x10 is so big
that the camera and 3 holders fill the main compartment. There is a
smaller compartment below that holds 3 or 4 lenses, spot meter and
misc. accessories. Both backpacks have some straps on the sides that
hold the tripod vertically on one side of the pack (the larger one
also has some pockets at the bottom for holding cross-country skis
that fit the bottom of the tripod legs). For longer hikes, I find
this very comfortable, though for shorter hikes or when I&amp;rsquo;m stopping
a lot, I just carry the tripod in my hands. I found that my dog&amp;rsquo;s
puppy collar fits around the bottom of the legs and keeps them from
coming apart as I carry the tripod by one leg. &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;mailto:sparks@col.hp.com&#34;&gt;John
Sparks&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;look into the gregory packs the ritter is a good day pack that i
know some 8x10 phptographers use The wunderlust is a greeat pack
also. go to a reputable hiking store to see the packs. I had a
shoemaker type person custom the inside for my use. &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;mailto:weleibow@aol.com&#34;&gt;W E
Leibow&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For my 4x5 system I have a LowePro MiniMag (I think) which just
holds the folded camera, darkcloth, and a few accessories. I carry
the other stuff in a seperate padded case. Both go inside my Dana
Big Sky (small panel loader) for day trips, along with any other
gear I want to tote. I also have a number of other camera bags of
various shapes and sizes The 7x17 fits nicely inside a convertible
travel pack &amp;ndash; these are worth looking at. &lt;strong&gt;Clyde Soles&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;photo-backpacks&#34;&gt;Photo Backpacks&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main advantage of a photo backpack is that it makes accessing the
gear easy and organises it well with its compartiments. These packs are
heavy, and for LF they might be over-padded, but this protects your gear
well. The three that I find large enough for a 5x7+35mm system, the
LowePro Super Trekker AW, Tenba PBH, and Sundog Art Wolfe, are all
around 12 lbs. They are reviewed below, as well as the smaller LowePro
PhotoTrekker AW, Temba PBL and Domke Outback. There is a short article
in the July/August 1993 issue of View Camera describing large format
packs. If you fly, it helps if your pack is small enough to carry on a
plane. The largest pack which will fit on an overhead bin is the Super
Trekker.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;lowepro-super-trekker-aw&#34;&gt;Lowepro Super Trekker AW&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A favorite of many photographers, the Lowepro super trekker AW is a very
well made bag. It is sold with several internal dividers which make it
possible to customize the interior compartiment the way you want it. It
can be configured with a lot of compartiments, which might be more
useful with 35mm and MF gear. I&amp;rsquo;ve stripped away most of the dividers,
but still I like the fact not to have to use lens wrappers anymore. On
the panel, there are three zippered pockets for small things, and a
large mesh pocket behind the cover that i find very useful for larger
items like the dark cloth or a jacket. There are two outside pouches and
a tripod basket which can also be repositionned. I like this pack
because it makes accessing the gear easy and organises it well. This
convenience sorts of compensates the weight, especially when you are in
a hurry to set-up. It is the bag that I use most of the time. I switch
to a regular backpack only if I plan a long hike, so that I can then
carry more stuff more comfortably.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is relatively compact (for its size) and could be carried on an
airplane, but so far I checked it because I had another carry-on bag. It
protects quite well too, but since it&amp;rsquo;s not rigid, there is still
possibility of dammage if you check it. One time a filter box was
cracked. Another time, a cable release left on a lens was broken just at
the tip. Still, I don&amp;rsquo;t hesitate to check it. It works like a
convertible travel pack (there are handles and you can cover the
harness) and has a weather cover built it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main drawback is the weight of the pack. It doesn&amp;rsquo;t have that much
usable volume inside. It&amp;rsquo;s a strech if in addition to my 5x7 and 35mm I
want to carry 4x5/polaroid backs, and I when I carry my fleece, I have
to attach it outside of the bag. Yet, it still weights 11lbs11 (5300g),
which I find is awfully heavy (that&amp;rsquo;s the weight of overnight gear which
would work anywhere on this planet). The suspension system is the same
as for the older generation Lowe climbing packs, but due to its reduced
height, the top stabilizing straps are attached too low to be really
useful. The comfort is just decent, barely equal to a low-end
backpacking pack. The tripod carrying system is practical with my 1228,
but I could see it becoming awkward with a larger tripod. You put two
feet of your tripod in the shoe, and secure the top with bungee cord
locked by a fast release buckle. Although it is more neat to have the
tripod ride at the back, it feels heavier than if you have it ride on
the side.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are going to buy one, think twice before getting a used model.
Recently, this pack has been upgraded, and I find the new model to be a
significant improvement in flexibility, in particular because of the
detachable inside panel, additional mesh pocket, and tripod carrying
system (although the built-in back pockets where neater than the current
modular system). Although not the largest, it might be the most
expensive camera bag in the world (\$400 at B&amp;amp;H). If you don&amp;rsquo;t need a
bag that big, try the new Protrekker.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;tenba-pbh-k-by-kerry-thalmann&#34;&gt;Tenba PBH-K by Kerry Thalmann&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I use a Tenba PBH-K. The &amp;ldquo;H&amp;rdquo; stands for huge, which it is. The &amp;ldquo;K&amp;rdquo; means
it mounts on a Kelty backpack frame. This pack is really designed for an
8x10 system, so it might be more than you need for your 5x7. When I
bought it, I was carrying a 4x5 Wisner (roughly the same size as your
Canham), plus the 4x10 conversion back and bellows. I had plenty of room
in the pack for the camera, 4x10 back, lenses for both formats (nine
total), film holders (again for both formats), bag bellows, filters,
meter, etc. On occasions, I also carried a Nikon N90 with 28-85 zoom. It
really does live up to the &amp;ldquo;huge&amp;rdquo; name. I&amp;rsquo;m not sure of the exact
weight, but given the enormous volume, it doesn&amp;rsquo;t feel very heavy (I
think it is ~ 8lbs not counting the Kelty frame). Plus, on the Kelty
frame with a good waist belt and suspension system, it rides well with
plenty of support. I have become much more tired and sore when carrying
loads half the weight in lesser packs. They also make a PBL (&amp;ldquo;L&amp;rdquo; as in
large), that might be better suited for your application. I haven&amp;rsquo;t
attempted to fly with my PBH-K, but even with the frame removed, the
pack would probably be too large to qualify as a carry on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Based on my experiene with the Tenba PBH-K&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pluses: Very well built and well laid out for carrying a large format
system. I have had this pack for almost three years and do a lot of
heavy duty hiking. It has been repeatedly exposed to salt spray at the
Oregon Coast and hot desert sun in the Southwest. It has carried my
euipment on many an off trail bushwhack through very dense brush, has
been rained on constantly in the Columbia Gorge and subjected to
complete immersion (unexpctedly, of course) in the Left Fork of North
Creek (the Subway). It still looks and works like new. The fabric seems
almost indestructible. Even when hiking through heavy brush that has
torn my clothing and bloodied my arms and legs, the fabric hasn&amp;rsquo;t shown
the slightest signs of wear. The pack is not completely water proof, but
it comes close. Even after the total immersion, all my equipment, film
holders and spare clothes were useable (a little bit of moisture leaked
in at the seems and settled in the bottom corners of the pack.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This pack is designed for large format and it shows. Most of the other
packs I looked at were designed for 35mm systems and had oodles of
little compartments and pockets and little elastic loops to hold 35mm
film cannisters. Some of these packs can be reconfigured internally to
accept a large formt system, but the external pockets are often too
small to hold things like film holders. My Tenba has two external
pockets, each plenty large enough to hold 5x7 film holders. All these
extra 35mm oriented features add both weight and cost to the pack (my
huge Tenba cost considerably less than the much smaller Lowe Super
Trekker). In addition to the Lowe (at 12 lbs.), I also looked at a Sun
Dog (again 12 lbs.). Both these packs, while very well built, seemed
very heavy for the relatively small volume. Another brand I have seen
that is designed specifically for large format use is the f64 line. They
were not available when I bought my Tenba, but I recently saw another
photographer using one. It was much smaller than my Tenba, but still big
enough for his 4x5 Wisner, lenses, holders, etc. Also, if you plan to
hike more than a couple miles, be sure to allow extra room for water,
food, a jacket and extra clothing. Although my Tenba is larger than
necessary for the system I am currently using, I like having the extra
space for non-photographic items.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Minuses: The pack is huge. As I mentioned above, this is a problem for
air travel. Also, being a huge pack with an external frame, it tends to
get caught on brush and tree branches. This is exacerbated by my taller
than average height. Branches most people walk right under present
obstacles for me. Ducking my head is not sufficient (the top of the
frame still catches). I must physically stoop down, or occasionally
crawl on my hands and knees in tight spots. Very tiresome and
inconvenient. There are times when I wish for a smaller pack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Somewhat related; I have always found carrying a tripod to be
troublesome. Not just with this pack, but with any pack. The tripods
typically carried by large format photographers tend to be rather large
(I know you have a little Gitzo Mountaineer. so this might not be a
problem for you). My tripods are too long to fit inside the pack, so
that gives me two choices; strap it vertically to one side of the pack,
or horizontally across the top. A heavy tripod, vertically mounted makes
the pack unbalanced, which makes my shoulders sore and tends to cause me
to lean when I walk. A horizontally mounted tripod seems to snag on just
about every tree branch in sight. My solution. In most cases, I just
carry my tipod in one hand (switching hands if one gets tired). This
seemed rather tedious at first, but after years of doing this, it now
seems natural to me. It also allows me to set up and tear down faster
for the moments when I am running up the trail trying to catch the last
light on a snow covered peak before it fades. I can extend the legs on
the tripod while I am approaching my planned location, rather than
waiting to drop the pack and unstrap the tripod. I did look at the Lowe
Super Trekker before I bought my Tenba. It has the built-in tripod pouch
that runs vertically up the center of the pack. It was too small for my
tripod, and even if it wasn&amp;rsquo;t, the tripod would have stuck up so high in
the air I wouldn&amp;rsquo;t have been able to walk upright on any tree lined
trail. Again, this might not be applicable with your smaller tripod.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note by David Fokos:&lt;/strong&gt; I have a Tenba PBH. This is the non-Kelty
version. My only addition to the informative message above, is that you
*NOT* buy a non-Kelty PBH. I carry an 8x10 with 1 lens, 6 filmholders,
a half dozen filters, etc. I still have room to spare, but the pack, and
my shoulders are not very happy with the weight (the straps are not very
well designed as far as serious backpacks go). I had to return the pack
to have the shoulder strap re-stitched (where it joins the pack), which
by the way, they did quickly and well. Also, the pack no longer holds
it&amp;rsquo;s shape (from carrying it by the handle on top, as well as hanging
off my shoulders). This makes it increasingly difficult to unzip and
open the top section where the camera lives. The rain flap no is no
longer able to cover the zipper for this section properly. I know it&amp;rsquo;s a
pretty poor description of the problem, but just take my word for it
that it&amp;rsquo;s undesireable. Otherwise I think the pack is great &amp;ndash; well,
laid out, etc. &amp;ndash; and I think the Kealty frame would have prevented my
problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Editor&amp;rsquo;s note:&lt;/strong&gt; According to tenba, the PBH-K weights 8 lbs 6 oz
(3800 g.) and the frame is 4 lbs 9 oz (2069 g.). That&amp;rsquo;s pretty heavy.
Maybe I am biased against external frames but it also looks quite bulky.
The 8x10 case is a good design for those who use this format, otherwise
I don&amp;rsquo;t think it makes efficient use of the (abundant) space. The same
could be said of the the bottom compartiments, which are quite deep, so
that one has to stake lenses unless they are really huge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;sundog-art-wolfe-backpack-by-denis-hill&#34;&gt;Sundog Art Wolfe backpack by Denis Hill&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve used one for several months with a variety of equipment. Some major
features are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Two removable internal cases that can be attached to shoulder strap
for separate use, one will also take the waist belt from the pack to
be a fanny pack, but this feature does not work well for me.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Side mount for substantial tripod.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Top handle and cover for straps, so it&amp;rsquo;s tidy when carrying on
planes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Plenty of different sized pockets on side, inside and outside of
flap.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The two rectangular removable units fit the bottom, leaving a large open
space in the upper pack: perfect for a field camera.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Drawbacks: expensive (list price is over \$300), limited distribution
(try LL Rue catalog).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was attracted by the modularity (having a collection of different
cases ranging from a 25-year-old Halliburton to recent Tamrac stuff:
never seem to have quite the right thing) and my admiration of the work
of Art Wolfe. I&amp;rsquo;m happy with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;lowepro-phototrekker-aw-by-marc-f-hult-mailto-hult-cinternet-net&#34;&gt;LowePro PhotoTrekker AW by &lt;a href=&#34;mailto:hult@cinternet.net&#34;&gt;Marc F. Hult&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I use the LowePro PhotoTrekker AW and am quite satisfied. I bought in
part because I was quite smitten by the Orion AW for my 35mm gear and it
seemed of comparable quality. The Orion will actually hold a compact 4x5
kit but certainly not 5x7.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The pack more-or-less permantly houses about six LF lenses, filters,
spotmeter, reflectors, small hot-lights and other gear. I can load it
with an 8x10 Deardorf, 4x5 Arca Swiss monorail or field 4x5 and
appropriate holders. If I&amp;rsquo;m carrying a field 4x5, there&amp;rsquo;s room for 35mm
gear too. If I don&amp;rsquo;t carry the reflex housing for the Arca, I can
squeeze in a small field camera too. The Arca monorail fits because the
rails folds up. Most other monorails will not fit because the pack is
not deep enough although it will hold 4x5 holders vertically which is
important to me. A 5x7 holder would have to be laid on its side. It&amp;rsquo;s
cramped for 8x10 (not enough holders).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I very briefly had the next smaller LowePro (non-AW PhotoTrekker?) but
found that the only provision for attaching a tripod was a strap on the
bottom of the pack which was useless. The AW has loops on both sides
which work well. The AW (all-weather) cover has come in handy. I&amp;rsquo;m not
thrilled about how the pack fits me (it is too short for my torso), but
perhaps I&amp;rsquo;m spoiled from having used good back-packing gear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;tenba-p-253-pbl-by-timo-ripatti-mailto-timo-ripatti-online-tietokone-fi&#34;&gt;Tenba P 253 PBL by &lt;a href=&#34;mailto:Timo_Ripatti@online.tietokone.fi&#34;&gt;Timo Ripatti&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The weight is just a little over 3 lbs and it holds my 4x5 Toyo Field
with 3 lenses easily. Plus there&amp;rsquo;s room for a 6x12 roll film holder and
a Kodak Readyload Film holder and 20 exposures worth of film. What
else&amp;hellip; in goes the compendium lens hood and a loupe and a Cambo reflex
focusing viewer and there&amp;rsquo;s still room for a Minolta spot meter and all
the filters I might need. This Tenba has a large back flap which, when
opened, lets me reach everything I&amp;rsquo;ve packed without moving anything
aside. There are loops at the sides for attaching a tripod and/or some
extra pouches. I&amp;rsquo;ve used it regularly for 4 or 5 years without any
noticeable sign of wear or tear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I chose this one because I was going to Lapland and that involved some
cross-country skiing. It was also important to keep all that snow
outside of the pack even if I tumbled over. Which I did a lot&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And then some criticism: this is the second one I have - the first one I
returned to the dealer after I inspected every seam and noticed that the
large zipper was not sewn to the position where it was supposed to be,
leaving a risk of ripping off if I overpacked the backpack. The price
may not sound like a bargain - according to the Tenba Webpage it is
\$286.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;domke-outback-by-mark-dubovoy-mailto-md-itventures-com&#34;&gt;Domke Outback by &lt;a href=&#34;mailto:md@itventures.com&#34;&gt;Mark Dubovoy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although too small for 8x10 and marginal for 5x7 (depends on your
camera), this might be the hands down best pack for 4x5. It is extremely
compact and light versus the interior room, has three major front
loading zippers which I find great when working in windy or inclement
weather (you only open what you need, you do not have to expose
everything else, and the flaps are small), and it has a unique
padding/compartmentalizing system that works great. The straps and
suspension system (an external aluminum frame that you bend to fit your
body)are no nonsense and second only in comfort to some of the top
hiking packs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This pack looks so small, it is deceiving. Do not let it fool you. I
carry a Linhof 4x5 with six lenses, 2 lightmeters, filmholders, tripod,
lens shade, filters, extra straps, a couple of towels, a rain cover,
lunch food, sunscreen, etc. and I find that I always still have a little
room to spare. It is also reasonably priced.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have learned from experience that the Domke bags in general do not
look too exciting in the store, but when you use them in the field, you
will probably conclude that they may just be the best stuff around.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;view-or-add-comments-http-www-greenspun-com-com-qtluong-photography-lf-lfpacks-html&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.greenspun.com/com/qtluong/photography/lf/lfpacks.html&#34;&gt;View or add comments&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>