<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Starts on Large Format Photography</title>
    <link>http://lflf.surge.sh/start/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Starts on Large Format Photography</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 01 Oct 1999 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://lflf.surge.sh/start/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>A Closer Look at a Large Format Photo</title>
      <link>http://lflf.surge.sh/start/example/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 1999 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lflf.surge.sh/start/example/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;autumn-close.3.html&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;autumn-close.3.small.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;{width=&amp;ldquo;120&amp;rdquo;
height=&amp;ldquo;120&amp;rdquo;}&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;autumn-close.2.html&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;autumn-close.2.small.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;{width=&amp;ldquo;120&amp;rdquo;
height=&amp;ldquo;120&amp;rdquo;}&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;autumn-close.5.html&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;autumn-close.5.small.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;{width=&amp;ldquo;120&amp;rdquo;
height=&amp;ldquo;120&amp;rdquo;}&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;autumn-close.8.html&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;autumn-close.8.small.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;{width=&amp;ldquo;120&amp;rdquo;
height=&amp;ldquo;120&amp;rdquo;}&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;autumn-close.6.html&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;autumn-close.6.small.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;{width=&amp;ldquo;120&amp;rdquo;
height=&amp;ldquo;120&amp;rdquo;}&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;autumn-close.7.html&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;autumn-close.7.small.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;{width=&amp;ldquo;120&amp;rdquo;
height=&amp;ldquo;120&amp;rdquo;}&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;autumn-close.9.html&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;autumn-close.9.small.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;{width=&amp;ldquo;120&amp;rdquo;
height=&amp;ldquo;120&amp;rdquo;}&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;autumn-close.4.html&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;autumn-close.4.small.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;{width=&amp;ldquo;120&amp;rdquo;
height=&amp;ldquo;120&amp;rdquo;}&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;autumn-close.11.html&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;autumn-close.11.small.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;{width=&amp;ldquo;120&amp;rdquo;
height=&amp;ldquo;120&amp;rdquo;}&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;autumn-close.14.html&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;autumn-close.14.small.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;{width=&amp;ldquo;120&amp;rdquo;
height=&amp;ldquo;120&amp;rdquo;}&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;autumn-close.13.html&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;autumn-close.13.small.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;{width=&amp;ldquo;120&amp;rdquo;
height=&amp;ldquo;120&amp;rdquo;}&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;autumn-close.12.html&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;autumn-close.12.small.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;{width=&amp;ldquo;120&amp;rdquo;
height=&amp;ldquo;120&amp;rdquo;}&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;autumn-close.17.html&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;autumn-close.17.small.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;{width=&amp;ldquo;120&amp;rdquo;
height=&amp;ldquo;120&amp;rdquo;}&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;autumn-close.18.html&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;autumn-close.18.small.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;{width=&amp;ldquo;120&amp;rdquo;
height=&amp;ldquo;120&amp;rdquo;}&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;autumn-close.15.html&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;autumn-close.15.small.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;{width=&amp;ldquo;120&amp;rdquo;
height=&amp;ldquo;120&amp;rdquo;}&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;autumn-close.16.html&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;autumn-close.16.small.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;{width=&amp;ldquo;120&amp;rdquo;
height=&amp;ldquo;120&amp;rdquo;}&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those close-ups were extracted from the image below. Each of them contains enough detail to make a sharp photograph on its own. Click on them to view.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;autumn-reflections.html&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;autumn-reflections.small.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;{width=&amp;ldquo;300&amp;rdquo;
height=&amp;ldquo;214&amp;rdquo;}&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[]{#lf}&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For landscapes, I prefer &lt;a href=&#34;../canham/canham.html&#34;&gt;this large format (LF)
camera&lt;/a&gt;, because it produces an image which
matches my perception of a visually rich world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, because the size of the film is 5x7 inches (12.7cm x 17.8cm), the
camera records an amazing amount of detail, 25 times what is contained
in a regular 135 (24mm x 36mm) frame. Everything which I saw is on the
film, and even more. When I examine my transparencies under a lupe, I
notice from time to time details which escaped me when I was looking at
the scene.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that what I display here does not even capture the full detail in
the original transparency, but only a quarter of it: the scanning was
done only at a resolution necessary to produce a 24x30 inches (60 x 75
cm) print, which is 6000 x 9000 pixels. However, the transparency has a
resolution of at least 50 lpm, is 5x7 inches (12.7cm x 17.8cm) and
therefore could have been used to produce a quality digital image file
at least four times larger (12000 x 17000 pixels). Such a file would
have been close to 1 Gigabye. At the resolution used, there is
absolutely no fuzziness and no grain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, the LF camera is not rigid because the lens is connected to the
film plane with a bellows. This let me control the perspective and the
distribution of sharpness in a way which cannot be achieved with a
regular camera:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I remember the trees as beeing parallel to each other. The LF camera
renders them that way. However the camera is looking down since the
lake fills up more than two-thirds of the frame. With a regular
camera, this would cause the trees in the background to lean towards
the edge of the frame, which would not be quite right.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I remember each part of the scene with the same clarity. The LF
camera looks at the close objects sharply and looks at the horizon
sharply at the same time: notice that the grass in the foreground,
only a few feet in front of the camera, is seen as clearly as the
distant trees. In contrast, a regular camera has to focus either
close or far.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For this particular photograph, those adjustments were quite simple and
intuitive. It was getting dark fast. I didn&amp;rsquo;t want to make the
photograph in full daylight, because I knew that the colors would be
lost to the contrast, and instead I chose to wait for the quiet and soft
light of dusk. After leveling the camera, I lowered the lens using front
fall to obtain the composition I wanted. I then tilted the lens, which
tilts the plane of sharp focus, until it became horizontal. I was lucky
that day because the air was quite still, so even in the 15 second
exposure (necessitated by the f 22 aperture and the slow speed of Fuji
Velvia), there was only minimal blurring of the grasses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;.&#34;&gt;More large format landscapes&lt;/a&gt; - &lt;a href=&#34;../&#34;&gt;More about technical aspects of
large format photography&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>http://lflf.surge.sh/start/5x7/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lflf.surge.sh/start/5x7/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-5x7-format-in-practice&#34;&gt;The 5x7 format in practice&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;By &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.terragalleria.com&#34;&gt;QT Luong&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; for
&lt;a href=&#34;%20/&#34;&gt;largeformatphotography.info&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once popular, the 5x7 format has fallen far behind in popularity behind
the 4x5 and 8x10 formats. This article looks at the advantages and
disadvantages of the 5x7 format, and gives a few practical pointers to
the resources available to the 5x7 photographer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-size-and-format-advantage-of-5x7&#34;&gt;The size and format advantage of 5x7&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Compared to 4x5, 5x7 is almost twice as large. The image on the ground
glass is nice and big to look at, but not so big that it becomes
difficult to see as a whole, like in 8x10.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The additional size makes it easier to make high quality large prints.
Since you need to enlarge two times less, imperfections in equipment or
technique are less likely to show up. Some photographers find that the
improvement in B&amp;amp;W quality is quite visible at 16x20 (a 4x enlargment
from 4x5). In color, if digital printing is used, based on an on-film
resolution of 40 lpm and a requirement of 5 lpm for critical sharpness
at normal viewing distance, one would begin to notice a difference
between 4x5 and 5x7 starting from 30x40, which is large, but not
uncommonly large. I have made prints at the largest Lightjet size
(50x70) with excellent results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, it is when you are not enlarging that the larger negative
counts the most. Contacts from 5x7 are large enough to view comfortably,
whereas contacts from 4x5 appear small. If you are a B&amp;amp;W photographer
using 5x7, all you need to create satisfying visual gems is a lightbulb
and a contact printing frame. A 5x7 transparency on a light box displays
a sharpness and a brillance which are far more impressive than a 4x5
transparency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other difference is in aspect ratio. 5x7 is more elongated than 4x5.
For that reason, I find it more satisfying for photographing large
landscapes. Others have reported that the format fits architecture and
the human figure well too. However, photographers more interested in
abstracts will probably like the more squarish aspect ratio of 4x5
better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like many photographers, I learned using 35mm, and since the aspect
ratio of 35mm and of 5x7 are practically the same, I felt immediatly
comfortable composing with a 5x7. When using both formats
simultaneously, there is no aspect ratio confusion. I find 5x7 to be the
perfect companion to a 35mm system. In addition, with the advant of
high-end digital cameras, the gap between 35mm (digital) and 4x5 (film)
is narrowing. Using 5x7, I still have two systems with widely different
capabilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-5x7-camera-versatility&#34;&gt;The 5x7 camera versatility&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you move to 8x10, you&amp;rsquo;ll almost certainly find yourself wanting a
ligher system to use on long hikes, backpacking trips, or travels. Then
you will have to maintain two systems, with the different lenses and
film holders, and think about which one to take on any given trip. On
the other hand, it is quite possible to do all your large format
photography with 5x7.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;5x7 gear is not much more heavier or bigger than 4x5 gear that it
becomes difficult to work with. The tripod and camera can still be moved
with one hand, and it is still possible to backpack. I have traveled in
Europe on public transportation with my 5x7. I have backpacked
extensively with it, including on a week-long trip into one of the world
ultimate wilderness areas, Gates of the Artic National Park in Alaska,
and a trip down to the river (and up !) from the North Rim of the Grand
Canyon. I have fit it inside a kayak for two weeks in Glacier Bay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With a reducing back, a 5x7 could be used as a nice 4x5 camera. It has a
longer extension, bigger bellows to reduce internal flare, and more
generous movements. Furthermore, a 5x7 can be used as a 6x17 (cm)
panoramic camera with an appropriate back. Such backs were rare (only
Art Pan made one, that you had to custom modify). However, recently
Keith Canham has presented a new model, with a battery operated advance
system. Weighting 2.2 lbs, and costing around \$1000, it will fit behind
the ground glass of many 5x7 that have 1 &lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; inches of clearance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the surface area is almost double, depending on the design, 5x7
gear is in general not twice as heavy as 4x5 gear. In some cases, the
difference in size and weight with 4x5 models is quite small, while 8x10
cameras are significantly heavier and bulkier. For instance, my own
Canham 5x7 weights less than popular 4x5 cameras such as the Zone VI,
Wisner Technical Field, Linhof Technika, and Arca-Swiss F-line.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One way to get started in the 5x7 camera is to use a 5x7 extension back
for 4x5. This was the route I initially took. However, these backs are
quite cumbersome, and have limitations, such as internal vigneting (you
are using bellows and a back opening made for 4x5) and the difficulty to
use very wide lenses, because of the additional depth of the back. Once
look at transparencies on the light table, it will be difficult to use
4x5 again, and you may be tempted to sell your 4x5 ! This is what
happened to me in 1995, after buying a 5x7 for my 4x5 in 1993. I&amp;rsquo;ve used
almost exclusively 5x7 since then, except for a couple of projects on
Polaroid film where I used the 4x5 reducing back on my 5x7.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;cameras-and-lenses&#34;&gt;Cameras and lenses&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The lightest 5x7 weights only 3 lbs and can be ordered from Peter
Gowland. Some fully featured 5x7 cameras (eg the Canhams, Lotus, Wisner
Pocket Expedition) are lighter than popular 4x5 cameras (eg Linhof,
Wisner Technical, Arca-Swiss). However, if you optimize 4x5 gear for
portability, you will usually get to &lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; of the weight of a 5x7 system
of comparable capacity. Over the past few years, manufacturers seem to
have realized that weight matters, and a flurry of lightweight camera
designs has emerged. While five years ago, you couldn&amp;rsquo;t find a fully
featured 4x5 field camera for less than 6lbs, now there are plenty in
the 4lbs-5lbs range, and the lightest ones are under 3lbs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 4x5 Canham DLC metal is 4 lbs. 11 oz. while the 5x7 Canham MQC is 5
lbs. 11 oz. On the other hand, the 5x7 versions of the Tachihara and the
Toho, two of the lightest 4x5 cameras, are both about twice the weight
of the 4x5 version.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While five years ago there was only a couple of field 5x7 made,
offerings have increased recently, with new flatbed cameras available
from Canham (classic woodfield T657 and metal MQC), Ebony
(SV57,SV57E,SV57UE,57SUE), Fine Art Photo Supply (Artworks, similar to
Tachi), Gandolfi(Traditional, Variant, All movements), Lotus (their most
popular camera: Rapid Field 5x7), Osaka, Shen-Hao (HZX57), Tachihara,
Walker (ABS 5x7 wide), Wisner ( Traditional, Technical Field, Pocket
Expedition). New monorail cameras available from Arca-Swiss (F-line,
Metric, Monolith), Linhof (Kardan), Sinar, Peter Gowland (all movements,
light), Toho (FC-57).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of the most affordable cameras on the used market such as the
Kodak, Burke and James, and Korona were made at a time when 5x7 was
still a popular format. They come with 4x5 and 5x7 backs, like the the
4x5 Canham wood, which is actually a 5x7 with a reducing back. Worth
noting on the used market are the Nagaoka and Anba Ikeda, which weight
only 3.75 lbs, less than almost all 2x3 cameras ! Nagoaka still makes
ultralight 5x7, but they are not imported to the US.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lenses to cover 5x7 are plenty, and range from the Schneider 72XL
(equivalent to a 15mm lens in 35mm) to the Nikkor 1200 T, with plenty of
choice in between. Most of the 4x5 lenses, especially in the longer
focals, will cover 5x7. Taking into account the usable surface area of a
sheet of 5x7 film, you&amp;rsquo;d multiply your 35mm focal length by 4.7 to get
your 5x7 focal length. Most photographers will find that, with a few
exceptions, the lenses that they use in 4x5, starting from 90mm up, will
cover the 5x7 format.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The focals for 5x7 are 1.4 as large as those for 4x5 for the same angle
of view, which translates into larger lenses. However, a lot of 4x5
photographers use lenses which have more coverage they need. Examples of
such lenses are the &lt;sup&gt;120&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;8&lt;/sub&gt; wide angle lenses (which are being displaced
by the Schneider 110XL), and the &lt;sup&gt;210&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;5&lt;/sub&gt;.6 plasmats, which all cover the
5x7 format with plenty of spare image circle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;film-and-holders&#34;&gt;Film and holders&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The cost is automatically higher due to larger size. This is the one
area where the choice in 5x7 is much less than in 4x5.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No preloaded film (ie Fuji Quickloads or Kodak Readyloads) are
available, so you have to use double cut film holders. These are
bulkier, heavier, require you to spend a significant amount of time
loading and unloading (usually at a time you&amp;rsquo;d rather go to bed to get
rested for that 5am sunrise), are more prone to catching dust, and more
difficult to track. You cannot use Polaroid film in this format either
(it&amp;rsquo;s available for 4x5 and 8x10). All the digital scanning backs are
designed for 4x5.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main problem for many is that the number of emulsions available is
extremely limited in color in their country. In particular, those
emulsions can be difficult to get in the US market.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kodak recently dropped several of their 5x7 emulsions. As of 2005, in
the US, you can get only Kodak Ektachrome Professional EPR 64 and EPY
64T as transparency films. Those are pretty old films which have a
following for product photography but that few landscape photographers
would find satisfying. In addition Kodak 160NC (negative) is also
available in 5x7.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fuji makes Velvia, Astia, and Provia F in 5x7, but it is not officially
imported in the US. International sources include:
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.unicircuits.com/shop/&#34;&gt;http://www.unicircuits.com/shop/&lt;/a&gt; (in Japan) &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bobrigby.com/&#34;&gt;http://www.bobrigby.com/&lt;/a&gt;
(UK) &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.robertwhite.co.uk/&#34;&gt;http://www.robertwhite.co.uk/&lt;/a&gt; (UK) however, note that in any case
the price will be above \$5/sheet. In the US the most convenient source
is Badger Graphics, however, they have to buy it retail in Japan, and as
a result, you&amp;rsquo;ll also pay \$5-\$6/sheet (Jeff says they don&amp;rsquo;t make money
on the transaction). Note that due to lack of demand, Badger doesn&amp;rsquo;t
import Astia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In B&amp;amp;W, the choice is better, with Kodak Tri-X, TMX, Ilford FP4+ and
HP5+, and Bergger BPF200, to choose from in the US. Other available
European films in 5x7, all currently imported by J and C, nclude Forte
400, Efke PL25, Efke PL100, and Rollei R3. B&amp;amp;H offers Fomapan 100 and
200 in 5x7 by special order. Arista films from Freestyle in Los Angeles
have been found to have identical characteritics to Ilford films. T-Max
100 film in 5x7 size is available as Nov 2001 a special order in single
50 sheet box qualities from a Kodak registered sales dealer (the Kodak
order number is #822-6334). The same 5x7 sheet film in T-Max 400
requires a 30 box minimum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Europe, both 5x7 and 13cmx18cm coexist and you can get both sizes
(but metric is easier to find). The size of the film is different (5x7
is 12.7cm x 17.8cm and the difference is beyond the internal dimensional
tolerance), therefore the holders are too, however, the exterior
dimensions of the holders are the same so you don&amp;rsquo;t have to modify the
camera. In the US, Calumet sells 13x18 film holders (that are actually
makes by the same factory that produces 5x7 holders), and J and C photo
sell European 13x18 film. There is also the option of buying over the
internet over suppliers such as Nord Photo in Germany. The choice of
13x18 film is quite large and includes Kodak Portra 100 T,E100G, E100VS,
Agfa RSX 100, Fuji NPS (negative), Provia F, Astia F, Velvia F, Velvia.
Prices are comparable to the retail price for 5x7 film in the US before
it was discontinued in the late 1990s, eg. 40-50 Euro. Using 13x18 film
may possibly be the best option for color photographers. Ted Harris has
offered to &lt;a href=&#34;http://largeformatphotography.info/lfforum/topic/502165.html&#34;&gt;facilitate a group
order&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I chose to cut myself the film from 8x10. This is done neatly with a
Rotatrim Mastercut II, a rotary blade cutter, and while it sounds a
delicate task at first, it is in fact very easy to do. I wouldn&amp;rsquo;t use
anything else, as precision is critical. One tip: I&amp;rsquo;ve found that it is
difficult to align the film with minute precision, I cut slightly
smaller than 5x7 to be sure there won&amp;rsquo;t be problems to fit holders.
Because of that, you&amp;rsquo;ll need to cut a sheet of 8x10 three times to make
two 5x7. If you use only one kind of film, it is not necessary to punch
a new notch. I just keep the film emulsion facing the top of the film
box. I have misloaded film only one time, out of more than a thousand of
sheets cut. It takes me between 30 min to one hour to cut 25 8x10
sheets. It&amp;rsquo;s not that tedious if you listen to music at the same time.
The problem is that while you don&amp;rsquo;t have to worry about finger marks
which are washed away by the developper, you increase significantly the
chance of getting dust on your film, which in turn can cause surface
scratches as you are traveling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With this method, you can use any emulsion which is available in 8x10.
The cost of a sheet of color transparency film is \$3-\$4 if 8x10 is
bought in boxes of 50. Personally, I located a large batch of
out-of-date, cold-stored 8x10 Astia that I bought at a very low price,
so I won&amp;rsquo;t have to look for film for maybe one more decade. At this
point, my main problem is that I have only 5x7 film boxes that date from
the good old eays days when EPP and Velvia were available in the US, and
although I have a large number of them, each year they get more worn
out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;processing-viewing-scanning-and-printing&#34;&gt;Processing, Viewing, Scanning, and Printing&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All commercial labs will process 4x5, but there are a number of them
which don&amp;rsquo;t have racks for 5x7. The price of processing 5x7 is often
twice as much as 4x5, and comparable to processing 8x10. Most will find
it necessary to use mail order processing, especially with the closure
of many E6 commercial labs caused by the widespread adoption of digital.
I have used Flatiron Color Lab, Holland photo, and Fleshtone LA.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The price of commercial scanning and printing is independent from the
transparency size. An excellent drum scan on the Heidelberg scanners,
resulting in a 300 MB file can be had for \$80 from several sources,
including West Coast Imaging and Pictopia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to scan yourself, for 5x7, the good news is that you don&amp;rsquo;t
need the same scanning resolution as for 4x5 to get equivalent results.
1800 dpi, within reach of most current flatbed scanners, will yield that
300MB file with 5x7. Although the choice in scanners for 5x7 film is
adequate, 4x5 photographers have more choices. Introduced in 2004, The
Epson 4870 was the first popular unit that had a transparency unit large
enough for 5x7. Replaced by the 4990, which can scan up to 8x10, it can
be had for less than \$400. Prior to that, the Epson units were limited
to 4x5 for many years. The recent Microtek i900 scanner in the same
price range will also handle 5x7. I choose the Epson over the Microtek
because its digital ICE (automatic dust removal) works on
transparencies, while Microtek&amp;rsquo;s ICE works only for reflective
materials, however I was not able to get this feature to work on large
scans. The advantage of the Microtek would be a drawer for glassless
scanning. Up to a budget of \$1000, there are a few 8x10 scanners (such
as the Microtek 1800) which are said to be better than the Epsons. While
there are other options available in 4x5 in between, for 5x7, the next
step are the high-end Imacon scanners. However, note that with the
Imacons the resolution drops with film size. So if you have a piece of
5x7 film, the largest file you can produce is about 230MB. This might
suffice in practice, but it is not very satisfying for a scanner of that
price. The FT848 scanner will scan the 5x7 transparencies at a maximum
resolution of 1600 dpi. Their latest and greatest, the FT 949 will only
scan up to 4x5.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you buy a flatbed scanner, you will most likely find that while it
comes with holders for 4x5, and maybe 8x10, there are no holders for
5x7. My solution is to cut a piece of matboard with a 5x7 opening, and
tape the transparency by its four edges with some stretch. The tension
helps with film flatness, to the point that some 4x5 users have reported
obtaining sharper scans with such custom holders than with the stock
holder. Just laying out the transparency on the glass is not optimal for
two reasons: the possibility of Newton rings, and the fact that the
focus distance of the scanner is above the glass. In fact, this focus
distance is not carefully controlled on consumer scanners, and some
users have found that while it is close to the distance to the stock
holders, it is not exactly equal. To experiment with various holder
thickness, matboard is too thick, and a possibility is to use thin
sheets of black plastic from a clear book folder, sold in stationary
stores.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To view 5x7 color transparencies, I recommend the Hakuba KLV-5700
viewer. It is ultra slim with even illumination, and can be used either
with an AC adaptor or on batteries. The viewing area is exactly 5x7, so
there the distracting bright border is minimal. The only drawback of
this viewer is that it is not as bright as some thicker ones. Hakuba
products are not widely sold in the US, so see
http:/&amp;gt;www.hakubausa.com&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you work in B&amp;amp;W, you&amp;rsquo;ll most likely do your own processing, so you
won&amp;rsquo;t incur high costs. You can easily find a 5x7 B&amp;amp;W enlarger on the
used market. The Zone VI enlarger will work with this format, and seems
to be the most popular new 5x7 enlarger.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;in-conclusion&#34;&gt;In conclusion&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;5x7 is an interesting compromise between 4x5 and 8x10.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are a B&amp;amp;W photographer, I believe that by steping up to 5x7,
you&amp;rsquo;ll lose only the portability of some lightweight 4x5 systems, and
you&amp;rsquo;ll have much to gain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The color 5x7 photographer faces additional problems related to scarcity
of film and processing, which do not affect the 4x5 photographers. The
gains from the larger transparency are less tangible, unless you plan to
make huge prints.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, if you are still tempted by a larger format than 4x5, 5x7 can
replace entirely 4x5 and 8x10 so that you can work in a single format,
and not worry about which camera to take regardless of whether you are
shooting next to your car, or backpacking for a week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;view-add-comments-http-largeformatphotography-info-lfforum-topic-503911-html&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://largeformatphotography.info/lfforum/topic/503911.html&#34;&gt;View/Add comments&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>http://lflf.surge.sh/start/how-to-operate/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lflf.surge.sh/start/how-to-operate/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Large format photography: A step-by-step guide to operating the view
camera&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-step-by-step-guide-to-operating-the-view-camera&#34;&gt;A step-by-step guide to operating the view camera&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.terragalleria.com/&#34;&gt;Q.-Tuan Luong&lt;/a&gt; for the &lt;a href=&#34;.&#34;&gt;Large
Format Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Operating the view camera is done in a series of steps, whose order is
crucial. Reversing some of the steps will &lt;a href=&#34;mistakes.html&#34;&gt;ruin the
image&lt;/a&gt;. Reversing some other steps will unnecessarily
&lt;em&gt;waste time&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although this might seem complicated at first, if you always stick to
the same sequence, it will become second nature. You will then be able
to concentrate on the subject. Here is the sequence that I favor in the
field.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Choose the camera position, approximate orientation, focal length.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Set up and level the tripod and camera.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Attach the lens and open it to full aperture.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Focus roughly using the focussing knob.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Adjust precisely the composition while looking at the ground glass.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Focus precisely with tilts/swings.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Determine the optimal aperture.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Re-adjust slightly the composition (optional but recommended).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Adjust filters and compendium shade (optional but recommended).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Check for vignetting (optional but recommended).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Close the lens, cock the shutter, rap and insert the film holder.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Determine the shutter speed.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Set the aperture and shutter speed.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Remove the dark slide.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Look at the subject.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fire the shutter with a cable release.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Put the darkslide back in.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Remove the filmholder.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make a second identical exposure (optional but recommended).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pack and move to the next spot.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a similar sequence described in greater detail, see Howard Bond&amp;rsquo;s
&lt;a href=&#34;articles/bond-checklist.html&#34;&gt;Check list for view camera users&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;in-detail&#34;&gt;In detail&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Choose the camera position, approximate orientation, focal
length.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Walk around, kneel up and down, and observe your subject. Even
for a large landscape a small difference in camera position can
be very important. Camera position will determine your
perspective.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The choice of focal length will determine how much is included
in the picture. If you hesitate between two focals, use the
shorter one. Unlike with smaller cameras, there is no need to
fill the frame, as you are shooting for printing and can crop
while making the print with little quality loss.&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Close one eye to eliminate stereo depth. It is useful to have a
viewfinding device which helps you visualize a part of the scene
as a two-dimensional picture. You can use:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A 35mm camera equipped with a lens of a focal equivalent to
those on the LF camera (a zoom lens like Nikon 24-120 works
well).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A LF viewfinder. The best one is the Technika multifocal
viewfinder. The older ones covers 90-360, while the newer
model covers 75-360 and have a slicker design, so watch out
carefully for the specs. They can be found used for
\$200/\$400.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A viewing frame. This is piece of cardboard with an opening
of the size of your film. The distance you hold it from your
eye will correspond to a lens of the focal length. You can
attach a string with knots to mark the focals that you own.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For B&amp;amp;W, you can also look through a colored filter which
removes most of the colors. Zone VI makes such a viewing
filter/frame.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Set up and level the tripod and camera.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Do not set the tripod before completing the previous step. Moving
it around with the camera is awkward and makes it difficult to find
the optimal position&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Try if possible to have the triangle formed by the legs pointing
towards the scene (so the leg does not get in your way), and the
platform level (so that panning the camera will keep it level).
On uneven terrain, make sure your set-up is stable.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make sure that all the controls of your camera are in neutral
position and locked. It&amp;rsquo;s pretty annoying to discover that your
picture is slightly soft on one side because the lens was swung
without you noticing it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Aim the camera towards your subject&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Level the camera left-to-right using the built-in bubble levels.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If there are vertical structures in your subject (which is
always the case with architecture), level the camera
back-to-front.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Attach the lens and open it to full aperture.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It is a good time to change to a wide-angle belows when using a
very wide lens and extensive movements.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;At full aperture the ground glass is brighter and sharpness
judgements are easier to make. For most lenses, the focus shift
between full aperture and taking aperture is neglectible.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Most lenses have a switch for opening/closing the lens, in
addition to the aperture and shutter controls. If yours doesn&amp;rsquo;t,
use the B shutter speed with a locking cable release to keep the
lens open.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Focus roughly using the focussing knob.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
This is just so that you can see your subject with the proper
magnification. You will refine the focus later.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Adjust precisely the composition while looking at the ground
glass.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use the upside down image on the ground glass to help you pay
attention to the abstract placements of the elements of the
image.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If avoiding convergence of vertical parallel lines is important,
which is in general the case with tall subjects (buildings,
trees, mountains), use primarily rise/fall for vertical framing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If this is not important, which is in general the case with
planar subjects (meadows, desert flats, tide pools), use the
tripod head tilt.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Panning with the tripod head is OK if the platform is level,
otherwise will require releveling. Better to use lateral shifts.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Focus precisely with tilts/swings.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Do not start focussing before the composition is adjusted. Tilting,
panning, and rise/fall/shifts (on most cameras) will alter the
focus, so you would have to refocus&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Precise focussing should be done with a lupe rather than with
the naked eye.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Since this is arguably the most technical part of using a view
camera, there are a variety of &lt;a href=&#34;how-to-focus.html&#34;&gt;focussing
techniques&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Determine the optimal aperture.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;This depends on the focus point&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Principles:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Even if everything looks sharp, it is in general not advisable
to use large apertures because of lens aberrations, smaller
image circle, and micro-alignement and film flatness problems.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Stopping down more than necessary will result in loss of
sharpness due to diffraction. All lenses are limited in
resolution to about 1500/N line pairs per mm (the actual
resolution on film will be slightly lower since it is a product
of lens and film resolutions). At f16, this is 93 lpm, f22:68,
f32:46, f45:33, f64:23. Another possible problem is image shake
due to longer exposures.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Out of focus areas due to unsufficient depth of field are
generally more disturbing than overall softness caused by
diffraction. In practice, I have found that it is easy to
underestimate the amount by which you need to stop down. If
everything on the ground glass doesn&amp;rsquo;t look sharp, be prepare to
use pretty small apertures !&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Three alternative methods:
-   Visual method: stop down until the most out-of-focus parts look
    sharp under the lupe.
-   Mechanical method based on image space: measure the difference
    in extension of the camera (the travel of the focussing rail)
    when the closest and the furthest points of the scene are
    focussed. Taking into account only defocus, your f-stop used
    will be proportional to this distance. The proportionality
    factor depends on the acceptable circle of confusion. This is
    facilitated with a &lt;a href=&#34;dofknob/&#34;&gt;DOF knob&lt;/a&gt;. I prefer to take into
    account also diffraction. Then there is an &lt;a href=&#34;fstop.html&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;optimal&amp;rdquo;
    method&lt;/a&gt; to set the f-stop to obtain the sharpest
    possible picture.
-   Mechanical method based on object space: estimate distances on
    the subject and use a &lt;a href=&#34;tools.html&#34;&gt;DOF table&lt;/a&gt;. I feel this
    method is the less precise of the three unless you use laser
    range finders.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Re-adjust slightly the composition (optional but recommended).&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The tilts and and swings might have altered it.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Adjust filters and compendium shade (optional but recommended).&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Filters darken the ground glass and therefore should not be placed
on the lens before focussing.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The compendium shade is particularly important if the area
outside of the image is brighter than the image, for example if
the sun hits the lens, or shooting on an overcast day with the
sky cropped out. The extra light could cause flare and/or reduce
contrast. In general, it can only increase contrast.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Adjust it by looking through the corners of the ground glass so
that it almost vignettes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Check for vignetting (optional but recommended).&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;This should be the last step before closing the lens, as vignetting
might be due to lack of lens coverage or to obstruction by filters,
shade, or bellows, and should be checked at taking aperture&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Through the corner cut-out of the groundglass look at your wide
open lens: the aperture will look somewhat like a cat&amp;rsquo;s eye
pupil. Now slowly stop down until your the lens opening shape
changes into a round opening in which you see all the aperture
blades. This is the largest stop at which you will have no
vignetting.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Check top and bottom is you used rise/fall or tilt. check left
and right if you used lateral shift or swing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If necessary, straighten the bellows and take care of sag.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Close the lens, cock the shutter, rap and insert the film
holder.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you are going to make a long exposure, rap the bottom edge of
the holder in your hands. This seats the film in the holder so
it doesn&amp;rsquo;t slowly slip down as you expose the sheet of film.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Be gentle not to jar the camera&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make sure the holder is properly sitted.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Determine the shutter speed.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Do not determine the exposure earlier, as the light might change&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use any type of meter you like (including 35mm cameras)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Add exposure time for filters.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Add exposure time for &lt;a href=&#34;bellows-factor.html&#34;&gt;bellows extension&lt;/a&gt;
if you are shooting a close-up.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Set the aperture and shutter speed.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Leaf shutters come with full shutter speeds only. If you need
adjustments of fractional EV values, you&amp;rsquo;ll use the aperture which
can be continuously varied, and is generally calibrated in &lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;
f-stops.&lt;br /&gt;
In case you&amp;rsquo;re worried about changing the speed on a cocked shutter,
the reputed lens machinist and repairman S.K. Grimes says it is OK
and quotes the Copal instruction book, packed with new shutters:
&amp;ldquo;Charging the shutter, opening or closing the shutter blades,
changing the shutter speed, changing the aperture stop&amp;hellip;.all these
things can be manipulated in any order you like without the least
ill effect on the shutter mechanism.&amp;ldquo;,&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Remove the dark slide.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Do not remove it until you are ready to make the exposure. You&amp;rsquo;d
risk light leaks. If you cocked the shutter with the dark slide out,
and missed, you would expose your film.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Be sure to pull the one closest to the lens, and do a parallel
smooth motion.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Double check to be sure that it has the white side facing the
lens.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Look at the subject.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A person or automobile might get into your composition.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If shooting vegetation, you will want to wait for a lull.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fire the shutter with a cable release.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
You&amp;rsquo;ve almost made it !&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Put the darkslide back in.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Turn the black side towards the lens so that you know that the film
has been exposed. On most holders, you would also rotate a hook to
lock the dark slide to prevent accidental opening and indicate that
the holder contains film (a unlocked holder with black side up would
be empty by convention). However I have found those hooks don&amp;rsquo;t stay
in the intended position, so i don&amp;rsquo;t rely on them.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Remove the filmholder.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Now, you&amp;rsquo;ve made it !&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Make a second identical exposure (optional but recommended).&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Once you have gone through all this trouble, it doesn&amp;rsquo;t make much
sense to expose only one sheet of film.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A second identical exposure is a cheap dupe, a guarantee against
dust problems, operator (photographer and lab) error.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You can hold it while having the first sheet processed, examine
the result, and then alter the processing to have a perfect
exposure for the second sheet. This is much more efficient than
bracketing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use the other side of the same holder if possible.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In any case, take notes so that you know latter which holders
contain an identical image.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pack and move to the next spot.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
If you think you are going to use your camera soon, especially with
the same lens, don&amp;rsquo;t fold it yet. Some photographers like to carry
their camera mounted on the extended tripod over their shoulder,
using the dark cloth for cushioning. I prefer to carry in one hand
by the handle, with the tripod folded in the other hand or on a
strap.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;more-information&#34;&gt;More information&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Howard Bond&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;articles/bond-checklist.html&#34;&gt;Check list for view camera
users&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.greenspun.com/com/qtluong/photography/lf/how-to-operate.html&#34;&gt;View or add
comments&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>http://lflf.surge.sh/start/matos-begin/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lflf.surge.sh/start/matos-begin/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Large Format Photography primer: equipment&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;large-format-photography-primer-equipment&#34;&gt;Large Format Photography primer: equipment&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.terragalleria.com/&#34;&gt;Q.-Tuan Luong&lt;/a&gt; for &lt;a href=&#34;.&#34;&gt;the Large
Format Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This article discusses what you need to start large format photography:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a camera&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;lens(es)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;film holders and film&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;tripod&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;accessories: darkcloth, focussing lupe, cable release, meter&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For an example of kit, see &lt;a href=&#34;camera-bag/&#34;&gt;inside my camera bag&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-camera&#34;&gt;The camera&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Think first about your intended application. 35mm cameras are universal,
MF cameras and LF cameras are really more specialized. What kind of work
are you going to do, and in which conditions ?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;which-format-to-use&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Which format to use ?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;roll-film&lt;/strong&gt; Shooting roll-film with a view camera is an
interesting combination. There are cameras and backs which let you
shoot 6x7, 6x9, 6x12, 6x17. Compared to 4x5, you don&amp;rsquo;t have to deal
with sheet film, the cost is very low (lower than for 35mm actually,
if the surface is considered), and there is a very wide choice of
film. If you chose a 2x3 view camera, it can be actually cheaper
than a lot of MF systems, and might not be heavier, especially if
you buy lenses with small coverage. However, compared to
convenentional MF systems, you gain &amp;ldquo;only&amp;rdquo; camera movements (their
effect is not always very easy to judge on the small image area) and
you loose a lot of ease of use (this might be a plus for folks
willing to &amp;ldquo;slow down&amp;rdquo;). Another option that I find more interesting
is to use a &lt;a href=&#34;#roll-film&#34;&gt;roll-film back&lt;/a&gt; with a 4x5 camera. There
are 4x5 lightweight cameras wich are not much more heavy than 2x3
cameras. Then you can have the option of doing 4x5 if the
opportunity looks very good. Speaking from my own experience and
that of other folks, when you come home the 2x3 images will look a
bit small if you have shot 4x5, and you will probably think that
given the burden of carrying and operating a view camera, you&amp;rsquo;d
rather have the big image. If you use a panoramic format like 6x12,
this comparison might not apply.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4x5&lt;/strong&gt; This is in practice the smaller format where you can use
sheet film (2x3 sheet film exists but is marginal). It is by far the
most popular format, with lots of cameras, lenses (from 45mm to as
long as the bellows will accomodate), film, different type of
holders (including roll-film, polaroid, preloaded). For most people
that&amp;rsquo;s the format of choice.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;5x7&lt;/strong&gt; The equipment is not really heavier than for 4x5: the lenses
are most of the time the same, there are 6lbs cameras. It is mostly
the holders which are bigger: they produce an image which is almost
two times as large, but is more rectangular, in a format homothetic
to 35mm and 6x9. It is large enough to produce decent contacts. but
still small enough that it is relatively easy to enlarge. The only
significant drawback comes from the scarcity of the film (as of
summer 96, the only slide film available in the USA are Kodak EPP
and EPR. Euro or Japaneese photographers have Fuji emulsions). One
thing that I am really missing is the possibility to use Polaroid
film, and quickloads. Processing and printing is more difficult to
obtain with labs, and if you want a new color enlarger, you might
have to buy a 8x10 enlarger. However, all these problems do not
affect b&amp;amp;w photographers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;8x10 and larger&lt;/strong&gt; These formats gives you beautiful contact
prints. Contact printing is required for some alternative process
(like Platinium). The marginal quality over 4x5 or 5x7 obtained in
enlargements is probably noticeable only for the extreme
enlargements. The drawback is the size and weight of the equipment,
as well as its cost. Older 8x10 cameras can be have for (relatively)
cheap, and a Philips camera is not much heavier than some 4x5
cameras. However larger formats (sometimes called Ultra LF) require
a considerable amount of work.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;what-features-to-look-for-in-a-camera&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;What features to look for in a camera ?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are a few things to consider. There are more discussions about the
various trade-offs (wood vs metal, monorail vs flatbed, etc&amp;hellip;)
elsewhere on the &lt;a href=&#34;./&#34;&gt;LF page&lt;/a&gt;. Remember that YOU have to find out what
your priorities are first, and that not every camera, no matter how
highly praised, is for everyone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Portable enough.&lt;/strong&gt; Whereas all the folding cameras are portable
and have a reasonnable weight (3lbs - 7 lbs), some monorails are too
heavy and bulky to be used in the field. There is a tradeoff here
between portability and and versatility (possibility to use many
focals and movements), and also rigidity. Usually, for the same
features, a wooden camera will be lighter, but often less compact
than an equivalent metal field camera.&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Allow you to use your focals of choice&lt;/strong&gt; All the cameras do what
they are designed for with a normal lens. However, with shorter and
longer lenses difficulties might arise:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Short focals&lt;/strong&gt;. Some flatbed cameras have very limited
wide-angle abilities, due to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;large minimum extension,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;fixed bellows (the bellows compression will make movements
impossible unless you have a wide-angle bellows which is
shorter and more flexible)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;beds showing in the field of view&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A recessed lensboard can make up for some problems by allowing a
larger lens to film distance than the focal length of your lens.
However, they are expensive (\$150) and the controls of the lens
become hard to reach. A monorail is usually more flexible, since
all of them have a small minimum extension, wide-angle bellows.
Depending on the nature of the tripod mount attachment, the rail
showing in the field of view might or might not be a problem,
but there are sometimes optional short rails.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Long focals&lt;/strong&gt;. A camera with bellows which are too short will
not allow you to use long lenses, or to do close-ups. The cure
for this problem are very limited. You can use on some cameras a
combinations of front tilts, or get an extension board (opposite
of a recessed board), but this will give you only a few
additional centimeters. Here, again monorails are more flexible,
since you can usually purchase a longer rail and extension
bellows.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Enough movements for your type of photography.&lt;/strong&gt; The monorails
have all the movements, whereas some type of flat bed cameras have
almost none. Studio photography usually requires a great deal of
image control, architecture requires shifts to maintain correct
perspective. Landscape require the less movements, although to
obtain adequate depth of field due to the fact that longer focals
are needed for a given field of view, some tilts are often
necessary.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rigidity and precision of alignment&lt;/strong&gt; This is all about sharpness.
To shoot in windy conditions you need a camera which is rigid enough
so that the standards won&amp;rsquo;t move (resulting in unsharp pictures).
The locks have to be strong enough so that the standards don&amp;rsquo;t move
when you insert the holder. Misalignements between standards or
within the back standard to the film plane might cause misfocus in
some areas of the image (although this is critical for reproduction
work, I doubt that for real shooting it matters). Generally
speaking, the metal cameras are more rigid and precisely aligned
than the wooden cameras. The lighweight cameras are more likely to
have problems here.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ease of operation.&lt;/strong&gt; Geared controls, positive and well placed
locks, spirit levels, various scales, zero detents, smooth
operation, rear focussing (very important for macro work), etc..,
all help. If complicated adjustments are used, a
&lt;a href=&#34;yaw.html&#34;&gt;yaw-free&lt;/a&gt; design might help. This feature is not relevant
otherwise.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;which-is-best-wood-or-metal&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Which is best, wood, or metal ?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main advantage of wood (besides being cheaper to work) is that it is
lighter. A consequence is that for the same weight you can make a bigger
camera, which in turn will provide you more movements and more
extension. A typical example are the Wisner and Canhams which are quite
bulky (for 4x5 cameras) but offer more movements and bellows than any
other field cameras. A metal camera using the same design would weight
more than 11 lbs. Wood is also much better at dampening high-frequency
vibration than any metal or metal alloy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Metal has technically many advantages. It is more rigid, which result in
less flexing and low frequency vibrations. This is good for long
extensions. It is more solid, resulting in a more durable camera. If
your tripod is knocked over by the wind, a metal camera is quite likely
to remain functional with a few scratches, whereas a wooden camera could
be totally destroyed. My reversible wooden back broke at the edge, which
would have been unlikely to happy with metal. The stability with respect
to environmental conditions like humidity and temperature is also better
(one day my Canham would focus quite smoothly, one day it would be quite
sticky). Last, it is easier to implement small features on metal.
Therefore metal cameras tend generally to be more compact, and to offer
greater accessory systems like reflex hoods, etc&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;which-cameras-to-consider-to-get-started-on-a-budget&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Which cameras to consider to get started on a budget?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is best to buy used equipment. Shutterbug (dealers advertisements,
classified, swap announces) and the net are good sources. Some
recommended used stores with knowledgeable and honest people are Midwest
Photo Exchange and Lens and Repro. There is not much which can go wrong
on a large format camera which has not been seriously abused, since
there are no delicate small high precision parts or electronics. Older
cameras are well usable, but usually lack the convenience of more modern
designs. Some of them are so beat-up that they lost their original
rigidity. Another thing to watch for is pinholes in the bellows. A new
bellows can always be installed, but the price might be a significant
fraction of that of the cheaper cameras. Here are some suggestions
(refer to the reviews for more details):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cheapest.&lt;/strong&gt; A Speed or Crown Graphic press camera (at the expense
of movements, not a good choice if you are interested in perspective
control or depth of field control. A basic monorail like Calumet
CC-400, Omega, Graphic View II (at the expense of portability, at
about 8 lbs., they are a little heavy and bulky for hiking), Bender
(if you like woodworking). A Burke and James (good movements, more
portable than a monorail, might be a bit ratty). \$250.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cheap.&lt;/strong&gt; A new Calumet Cadet (a monorail camera). \$400. Toyo
45cx. \$450. A used lightweight wood-field (such as the Tachihara).
\$400-\$500. A Technika III (metal, flatbed, adequate movements).
\$600.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Still reasonable.&lt;/strong&gt; A new lightweight wood-field (around \$700), a
used Wista, a used Zone VI. The new Arca-Swiss discovery (maybe too
recent to find used) and the Sinar A1 (monorail cameras).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-lenses&#34;&gt;The lenses&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;what-to-look-for-in-a-lens&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;What to look for in a lens ?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Focal.&lt;/strong&gt; You are probably familiar with 35mm. Pick up your
favorite focals and find the equivalent LF focals either using &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.mat.uc.pt/~rps/photos/angles.html&#34;&gt;Rui
Salgueiro&amp;rsquo;s field-of-view
calculator&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&#34;http://www-swiss.ai.mit.edu/philg/photo/lens-table.html&#34;&gt;Ed
Scott&amp;rsquo; comparison
tables&lt;/a&gt;.
Note however that while 5x7 is homothetic to 35mm, 4x5 and 8x10 are
both more squarish. More folks are happy with just one lens in the
LF world than in 35mm. Personnally, I would tend to err on the wide
side, since cropping is not too much of an issue.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Coverage.&lt;/strong&gt; A lens projects an image circle which must be large
enough to cover the film area without vignetting. The absolute
minimun which is required is the diagonal of the format. If some
movements are used, the diameter of the image circle has to be
larger to cover the film area. The larger this circle is, the more
movements you can do. In particular, it is easy to calculate how
must shift you can get knowing the image circle and the format. The
image circle is usually expressed in a millimeter diameter, at
infinity, and at a specific aperture of f/16 or f/22. Stopping down
might increase its diameter. Focussing to closer distances always
does.
For general use, make sure to get enough to be able to do some
movements, maybe around 180mm for 4x5 and around 230mm for 5x7.
Applications like table top and architecture photography often
require extensive movements and therefore larger image circles.
Lenses with more coverage than you need will be heavy, big, and
expensive.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Maximum aperture.&lt;/strong&gt; You won&amp;rsquo;t use a LF lens wide open, however a
large maximum aperture ( f/4.5 or f/5.6) makes viewing and focussing
easier, especially if you are indoors or like to photograph in low
light. However, for a given focal length, the faster lens will be
larger, heavier and more expensive.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Portability.&lt;/strong&gt; Be careful here. Lenses of same focal lengths vary
*considerably* in size and weight ! Make sure to see the lens
before buying. Generally speaking focal length, coverage, and speed
contribute to a big lens, all other factors being equal. That&amp;rsquo;s
where modern lenses don&amp;rsquo;t necessarily shine. A significant portion
of the weight and bulk can be due to the shutter. Longer focal
lengths and/or faster lenses often come with a big #3.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Optical quality.&lt;/strong&gt; Basically all the modern lenses (current models
from Fuji,Nikon, Rodenstock, Schneider) are good enough, and very
difficult to distinguish from each other at the apertures used in
practice. For color work, it is generally recommended to stick to
those, or to relatively recent multicoated lenses, although a single
coated lens properly shaded might work fine. This is less critical
for B&amp;amp;W. For details, see &lt;a href=&#34;lenses-general.html&#34;&gt;a general
discussion&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fit.&lt;/strong&gt; Some big lenses cannot be used with some field cameras or
with some lensboards. Also, make sure you have enough belows. When
using long focal lengths you may consider choosing a telephoto
design lens (usually designated with a &amp;ldquo;T&amp;rdquo;) rather than a regular
design lens of the same focal length. These lenses require
approximatively &lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; of the bellows a regular lens would. However,
they are usually more expensive, have less coverage, and behave a
bit weird with respect to tilts. They are not necessarily more
compact or lighter.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Working shutter.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a list of recommendations and tests, see
&lt;a href=&#34;http://greenspun.com/ct/qtluong/photography/lf/lf.html?send_to=http://www.hevanet.com/cperez/testing.html&#34;&gt;http://www.hevanet.com/cperez/testing.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;film-and-holders&#34;&gt;Film and holders&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;conventional-vs-preloaded-film-quickload-readyload-polaroid&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Conventional vs preloaded film (Quickload, Readyload, Polaroid)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can either use film that you load yourself in cut-film holders or
preloaded film.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the first case, you need a dark and relatively clean place to load
your film holders (might be a problem when travelling), and to unload
them. Dust might be a problem, you have to clean your holders carefully.
You cannot have too many holders. With a large number of holders, not
only you&amp;rsquo;ll be sure not to run out of film ready to shoot, but you&amp;rsquo;ll
have to reload less often, and you can keep exposed film in holders,
which makes tracking easier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Readyloads are from Kodak, Quickloads from Fuji. The readyloads from
Kodak hold two sheets of film, the Quickloads hold one. The film is in a
paper packet that you put in a special holder (they are made by Kodak,
Fuji, Polaroid). Polaroid film can be processed instantly or latter,
inside the holder. The other films are processed normally in the lab.
Here are the advantages of preloaded film:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No need to load and unload. Especially nice in the field.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Almost dust-free. Because they&amp;rsquo;re factory loaded in a clean room,
the only dust you get on the film is the dust that lands on it after
you pull the envelope/darkslide.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lighter/Less bulky. Preloaded film allows you to carry more
ready-to-use film (although in the long run, if you are using lots
of film, it will end up being heavier) since you don&amp;rsquo;t have the
weight of individual film holders.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Easier to track after exposure. You can just write information on
each packet.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main disadvantages are&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;more expensive (a sheet of conventional Velvia 4x5 costs \$1.7 vs
\$2.6 for preloaded)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;only a limited number of emulsions are offered by Fuji (in
particular no B&amp;amp;W film), Kodak, and Polaroid (the non-instant film
is Fuji film).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Kodak system is known to suffer from light leaks&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Less sharp (maybe). In a Camera and Darkroom article, J.Englender
writes that the preloaded system do not yield as sharp results as
conventional holders due to film flatness problems (the best results
are obtained with Graphmatics, then conventional holders, Fuji and
Kodak holders, and Polaroid holders). Many people ignore that.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;if you have a lot of film to carry on a long trip, the enveloppes
end up adding up.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The best results for the preloaded films seems to be obtained using the
dedicated holder (Fuji and Kodak), although the Fuji Quickload work OK
with the Polaroid holder. The new 545i holder is significantly lighter
than the old 545 which was all metal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;conventional-cut-film-holders&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Conventional cut-film holders&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you decide not to use the preloaded systems but instead buy your film
in sheets and load it, you have the choice between regular film holders
which hold one sheet on each side, and Grafmatics. Generally speaking,
if you buy used holders, check them carefully for dust and light leaks
problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wooden holders tend to slide better in wooden cameras, and are slightly
lighter than plastic holders, but they cannot be found new. As far as
new holders are concerned, most people use Fidelity or Lisco holders,
which are the cheapest. Some brands make more expensive holders, but
nobody has been able to prove that they yield sharper pictures in usual
working conditions. The extremity of the dark slide is marked with two
colors (black and white) and raised dots so that you can remember
whether they contain blank film or exposed film. In addition, there is a
tab which is supposed to keep the dark slide locked and prevent you from
removing it accidentally, as well as help you identified loaded vs empty
holders, but I have found that it tends to be quite unreliable. Riteway
makes a holder with a button instead of the tab, which is an
improvement, but it is not compatible with some cameras.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;holders.html#grafmatics&#34;&gt;Grafmatics&lt;/a&gt; are more light and compact, and
allow you to shoot in a sequence, but the loading is more difficult,
esp. if you want to unload after using a holder only partially. They can
be bought only used. []{#roll-film}&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;roll-film-backs&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Roll-film backs&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Roll film backs are available for all roll-film sizes to 6x12 the most
common being 6x7 and 6x9. There are two types of roll-film holders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Graflock-type holders&lt;/strong&gt;: Some 4x5 cameras have a back (Graflock,
this standard was introduced on the Graflex cameras) where you
remove the ground-glass assembly and replace it with a roll-film
back. There are plenty of brands to chose from: Graflex, Singer,
Linhof (super-rollex), Mamiya RB, Horseman, some of which can be
found for quite cheap.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Slide-in type holders&lt;/strong&gt;: These holders are flat because the film
spools are at one end. They can be inserted under the ground glass
like a sheet film holder. Almost all the cameras accept them, but be
sure to check for compatibility. The Calumet holders are quite cheap
and are now produced in 6x7, 6x9, 6x12 (the latter is quite
expensive actually). Sinar has a vario holder which allow you to
switch format (from 6x4.5 to 6x12) at any time, for \$2500 new.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Personnally I prefer the second type, because I find them faster to use
and it is said that the film flatness is better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;polaroid-film&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Polaroid film&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Polaroid film is a great learning tool because you get instant feedback.
Some people recommend that when you start 4x5 you expose Polaroids to
begin. Another special application is proofing, to check composition,
exposure (esp. with flash), and focus (by luping the negative). But
Polaroid material has its own photographic merits, and can yield
beautiful prints and negatives. It has been used as a medium by some
masters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To use Polaroid film, all you need is a 4x5 camera, and a Polaroid
holder. The sheet film holders are model 545 (older, metal construction)
or 545i (current, plastic construction, lighter). They are reasonnably
sized so they can also be used with Quickload (and maybe Readyloads,
although the failure rate is catastrophic). There are two other Polaroid
holders, for pack film, the 550 which accepts 4x5&amp;rdquo; pack film and the 405
which uses 3 1/4x 4 &lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;&amp;rdquo; pack film. Packs film are cheaper, but the film
area is smaller than 4x5, so that makes them useful mostly for checking
exposure. Personally I would just go for the 4x5 image given by the 545
(which is already a bit smaller than 4x5)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Polaroid also makes material for 8x10 cameras, but it is quite pricey
and you also need a special processor, unlike in 4x5 where the holder
serves as the processor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For more information, call Polaroid to get a free guide to their film. I
have personally found type 52 (gives a beautiful print), type 54 (gives
a print not as beautiful, but which does not require coating), and type
55 (gives a print AND a negative), and type 56 (gives a beautiful sepia
print) useful. Unfortunately with type 55, the negative is about 1.5
stops slower than the print, so you cannot get both well-exposed. The
negative needs also a good cleaning to remain usable. &lt;a href=&#34;polaroid55.html&#34;&gt;More details on
55&lt;/a&gt;. All these materials are B&amp;amp;W. I don&amp;rsquo;t have too much
experience with the color materials, but I heard they are quite
sensitive to heat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-tripod&#34;&gt;The tripod&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;what-to-look-for-in-a-tripod&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;What to look for in a tripod ?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;portability&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;stability/rigidity&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;working height&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ease of use&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first and second points are contradicting, and therefore you have to
compromise. A reasonnable choice would be something like a Gitzo series
300 or equivalent. A Gitzo series 400 would hold any view camera. A
series 200 would be considered by many to be marginal, but I find it
quite usable (see below). Quite a few people use wooden tripods. While
it is said that they damp vibrations better than metal tripod, I find
that their only real advantage is ruggedness (due actually to a simpler
construction, rather than material), and warmer feel. On the other hand,
with respect to the four previous points, for a given weight, the metal
tripod is always better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;do-i-have-to-get-a-monster-tripod-for-this-large-format-camera&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Do I have to get a monster tripod for this large format camera ?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You don&amp;rsquo;t necessarily need a tripod bigger than the one you use for your
small camera. I used to have a very heavy tripod (Zone VI, 16 lbs, ouch
!) that i used next to the car, and a Gitzo 226 for hiking and
traveling. Since then, i have sold my Zone VI, and use exclusively the
Gitzo 1228 with a Linhof Profi II ball head. The combination weights
4lbs, and is quite usable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reasons why I think that a light tripod such that the 1228 is plenty
adequate for my LF use are the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The real issue is the rigidity of the legs, NOT the weight of the
tripod. With this respect, the Gitzos are pretty good. For the weight, I
carry plenty enough. I have put a ring at the bottom of the center
column, and attach by camera bag to it. The combo has a heavy weight
that cannot be beat !&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Some medium format or even 35mm settups are in fact heavier than my
LF, but I see NO reason why a heavier camera would require a heavier
tripod (as long as it does not collapse, of course). Since regardless of
the format, blur due to camera shake is mostly a function of focal
length, I would tend to say that very stable tripods are needed mostly
for very long lenses. Thus if the 1228 is sufficient to hold a 300mm
lens for a 35mm camera (and it is), then it is also sufficient to hold a
300m for a 4x5 in still conditions. Most of my LF photography is done
with 120 and 210 mm lenses.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;tripod-head-with-qr-system&#34;&gt;Tripod head with QR system&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A pan-tilt head is more convenient, because it is more easy to level the
camera, and you can tilt the camera front to back without unwanted
sideway tilt. If your camera does not have levels, it would be useful to
have them on your head. A quick release system is very nice to have.
Unfortunately the smallest PT head made by Manfrotto which meets all
these requirements is the 3047, and although it is nice to use, it
weights almost as much as my Gitzo 1228. I also have a smaller PT head,
the 3029, but it does not have a built-in QR system, and i find it
becomes quite bulky if I attach one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mostly because of the weight and bulk savings, many photographers use
ball heads. An other benefit is that they work better for 35mm and MF if
you use a second format. The Linhof Profi II is good enough for most
lightweight LF cameras, however, the heavier and more expensive
Arca-Swiss B1 is more rigid, smoother, and has an elliptic ball to
prevent flip-over.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A Quick Release (QR) system is not absolutely necessary, but very nice
to have, especially if you switch between different formats. You can buy
a Manfrotto/Bogen adaptator to use the Bogen hex plates with several
ball heads by replacing the stock platform. The spring-loaded Bogen QR
system is inexpensive, quick and easy to operate, lock positively and
well thanks to the hexagonal shape. If tightened enough, the plates
won&amp;rsquo;t slip. However, if you are using at the same time smaller cameras,
you might prefer the Arca Swiss system, where you slip the camera plate
into a dovetail. With that system, camera plates can be custom made for
each camera, which ensures a better fit, while the Bogen plates tend to
stick out from small camera bodies. Don&amp;rsquo;t get the generic plates from
Arca-Swiss. That would negate most of the advantages of the system !
Really Right Stuff is generally thought to make better fitting plates
than Kirk Enterprises.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;accessories&#34;&gt;Accessories&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;darkcloth&#34;&gt;Darkcloth&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can use a jacket, but a dark cloth is preferable and does not cost
much anyway compared to the price of the rest of the equipment. A cloth
with a white exterior is nice on hot days or if photographing on a busy
site. Personnally I don&amp;rsquo;t like those which have weight (ie Zone VI)
because if it gets really windy they can fly around and break the ground
glass, plus they tend to add weight. A Velcro on the side which is used
arround the camera is nice to maintain it in place. For good viewing of
the image with slow lenses, I have found that a second velcro is called.
One part of the velcro is on the left side of the cloth, the other one
on the right side, so that you can close totally the cloth (light coming
from under the cloth is otherwise quite distracting). Darkroom
Innovations have taken this idea seriously and makes a darkcloth with an
elasticized collar that fits around the camera and a velcro-closed slit
that you can close totally for excellent darkness. The choice of
material makes it light and windproof. It&amp;rsquo;s better than any other
darkcloth that I have seen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;focussing-aid&#34;&gt;Focussing aid&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Except maybe in 8x10, don&amp;rsquo;t trust the naked eye to focus critically. A
lupe with a medium magnification, not too big, not too expensive, is the
best here. This eliminates the lupes which are usually used for viewing
slides on light tables. Unlike in that situation, to focus the view
camera you don&amp;rsquo;t need a high quality lupe. On the other hand, there are
a few practical requirements: its skirt does not prevent from viewing
the corners, it is focussable so that you can make sure it is focussed
on the ground glass, and it has attachement for a string so that you can
dangle it around your neck. I like the Calumet lupe (7x) for its small
size and good magnification. It works well with my very fine-grained
Boss Screen but when I had the coarser Canham stock screen, I found it
easier to focus with the Toyo (4x). Some people like cheap +4 dioptre
glasses. Ron Wisner uses (and sells) a linen tester (an inexpensive
folding magnifier that you put in your pocket, and which can be angled
for good corner viewing). &amp;ldquo;Hastings Triplets&amp;rdquo; used by geologists are
similar, but more powerful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;cable-release&#34;&gt;Cable release&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to avoid loosing them or spending time to screw/unscrew them, I
have a cable release permanently attached to each of my lenses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;meter&#34;&gt;Meter&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Pentax digital spot meter seems to be popular with large format
photographers. It is relatively small and light, reliable, and has easy
controls and viewfinder readings. Recently the multi-purpose Sekonic
Zoom-master has been succesfull, because it combines incident and flash
with spot. However it is more complex and does not have viewfinder
displays.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Personnally I use my 35mm camera. I like to have the small camera to be
able to shoot quickly should something change suddently and produce many
images for stock. I also use it as a viewfinder so I don&amp;rsquo;t have to move
the tripod around. When I am in a hurry, I use the matrix metering,
otherwise I use the a built-in spot meter with the &lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; stop analog scale
in the viewfinder. I just set the same shutter speed and f-stop I intend
to use on the LF camera, and then see where different part of the scene
fall. Cameras with such a scale include the Nikon N8008s, F4, F5, F100
(N90 has only a f1 stop scale), and most canons, including the Rebel
2000 and the EOS 3. If I use the polarizer on the LF camera, I just put
a polariser on my 35mm lens. The 24-120 or 24-85 lenses matches all the
4 focals that I commonly use on the LF camera.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;better-focussing-screen&#34;&gt;Better focussing screen&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can replace the focussing screen which comes with your camera, or
supplement it with a fresnel lens to obtain a brighter and/or sharper
image. After several screens, I have found the Boss screen to be by far
the best.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;view-or-add-comments-http-www-greenspun-com-com-qtluong-photography-lf-matos-begin-html&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.greenspun.com/com/qtluong/photography/lf/matos-begin.html&#34;&gt;View or add comments&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>http://lflf.surge.sh/start/mistakes/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lflf.surge.sh/start/mistakes/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Large Format FAQ: mistakes&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-not-to-do-in-large-format&#34;&gt;What NOT to do in large format ?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.terragalleria.com/&#34;&gt;Q.-Tuan Luong&lt;/a&gt; for &lt;a href=&#34;.&#34;&gt;the Large
Format Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are more ways to ruin a photograph than you would think. All these
potentially fatal mistakes are specific to large format, in the sense
that most of them are impossible, or quite rare with 35mm and MF
cameras. Here are some of them, and how to avoid making the mistake.
Additional suggestions welcome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mistakes make while taking the photograph

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#1&#34;&gt;lens not stopped down&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#1&#34;&gt;shutter speed not adjusted&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#1&#34;&gt;dark slide removed before closing the lens&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#1&#34;&gt;holder with exposed film used&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#1&#34;&gt;holder with no film used&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#1&#34;&gt;camera fired with no film holder inside&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#1&#34;&gt;dark slide not removed before the exposure&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#1&#34;&gt;dark slide put back the wrong side&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#1&#34;&gt;dark slide not put back&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#1&#34;&gt;rear dark slide pulled out&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#2&#34;&gt;vignetting due to internal blocking&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#2&#34;&gt;vignetting due to excessive movements&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#2&#34;&gt;vignetting due to compendium shade/filters&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#3&#34;&gt;lack of depth of field&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#3&#34;&gt;poor focussing&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#4&#34;&gt;camera controls unlocked&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#5&#34;&gt;camera shaken by the wind&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#6&#34;&gt;subject shaken by the wind&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#7&#34;&gt;reciprocity failure miscompensated&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#7&#34;&gt;filter factor not taken into account&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#7&#34;&gt;bellows factor not taken into account&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#15&#34;&gt;wrong f-stop scale (with convertibles or Nikkor telephoto
lenses)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#8&#34;&gt;change in light/subject not taken into account&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#8&#34;&gt;cable release / shade showing in picture&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#16&#34;&gt;mysterious double image with long exposure&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pre and post exposure mistakes

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#9&#34;&gt;film loaded backwards&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#10&#34;&gt;film misloaded&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#11&#34;&gt;dusk got on the film&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#12&#34;&gt;forgot at home tripod/holders/essential camera part&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#13&#34;&gt;darkslide accidentaly opened&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#14&#34;&gt;wrong developpment (ie color instead of B&amp;amp;W, or +1 instead of
-1) applied to the film&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#15&#34;&gt;flipping the light on before closing film boxes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Defective equipment

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#17&#34;&gt;light leaks in camera or bellows&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#17&#34;&gt;light leaks in holders&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ground glass mis-alignment&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;film plane mis-aligned in holders&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;erratic shutter&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[]{#1}&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;to-avoid-fatal-confusions&#34;&gt;To avoid fatal confusions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Be sure to operate in a systematic way, to always do the actions in the
same sequence, and to double check everything. After I am done focussing
and composing, the first thing I do is close then lens. Then I meter,
and set the f-stop and shutter speed. Then I insert an holder, making
sure it is white. By prefiring the shutter before pulling out the dark
slide, I make sure that the lens is closed and that an (approximatively)
adequate shutter speed was dialed. By checking that I put the black side
of the dark slide back, before removing the holder, I make sure that the
exposure was done. []{#2}&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;to-avoid-vignetting&#34;&gt;To avoid vignetting&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Always check through the cut corners of the ground glass in doubt. It is
useful to know the situations where problem can occur. For instance with
my camera, I have to be careful if I don&amp;rsquo;t use bag bellows and do tilts
or falls in verticals. []{#3}&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;to-avoid-lack-of-sharpness-from-focussing&#34;&gt;To avoid lack of sharpness from focussing&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Use a lupe to focus, and check very carefully each part of the
ground-glass. In particular, be aware when using tilt that the depth of
field around the focus plane is significantly reduced as compared to the
case when no movements are used, so don&amp;rsquo;t forget to check the top of the
trees or hills. If there are areas in the image which still appear
unsharp after applying movements, stop down until they appear sharp, and
then add one f-stop. This might be difficult to judge with a dim image.
Better to loose some optical performance by overstopping than to have an
area which is lacking critical sharpness. Wide-angle lenses usually have
to be stopped down to f22 for optimum performance anyway, whereas other
lenses have to be stopped down a couple of f-stops. It is not a good
idea to use a lens near full aperture because of the possible alignments
problems. []{#4}&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;to-avoid-unlock-controls&#34;&gt;To avoid unlock controls&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lock all the controls as you unfold the camera. Unlock only those that
you use. Double check that camera controls and tripod controls are
locked before inserting the film holder (which would otherwise cause the
back standard to move and force you to refocus). []{#5}&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;to-avoid-camera-shake&#34;&gt;To avoid camera shake&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Use an unbrella to shield the camera from the wind. For long lenses,
techniques comparable to long-tele tricks like double tripods or
extension arms to support the standard help. &lt;a href=&#34;stability.html&#34;&gt;More
details&lt;/a&gt;. []{#6}&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;to-avoid-subject-shake&#34;&gt;To avoid subject shake&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Be patient enough to wait for lulls. Using the fastest speed (compatible
with the desired depth of field) helps too. []{#7}&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;to-avoid-underexposure&#34;&gt;To avoid underexposure&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are going to do a long exposure (several seconds), a close-up, or
use filters, think about the compensation to apply. Reciprocity
compensation tables are available for most popular films. There are
&lt;a href=&#34;bellows-factor.html&#34;&gt;several methods&lt;/a&gt; to accont for bellows factor.
[]{#8}&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;to-avoid-last-second-problems&#34;&gt;To avoid last second problems&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Be sure to look at your subject until the moment you make the exposure !
[]{#10}&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;to-avoid-improper-loading&#34;&gt;To avoid improper loading&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You must feel the film with your fingers to make sure it is well sitted
in the rails. The things I do is feel the extremities of the rails,
which ensures that the film is beneath. I also lift the film from below
and makes sure it is catched by the rails. See &lt;a href=&#34;loading.html&#34;&gt;detailled description of
loading&lt;/a&gt; []{#9}&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;to-avoid-loading-backwards&#34;&gt;To avoid loading backwards&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Make sure you feel each notch at the right place. If you are holding the
long side of the holder perpendicular to you that&amp;rsquo;s the right corder on
the upper side of the film. If you are holding the holder another way,
be careful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you have shot your film backwards, it will appear underexposed by 2
or 4 stops, and if you are shooting color it will have a predominant red
color cast because it has been filtered by the base. Color film is
ruined. B&amp;amp;W can be salvaged: &amp;ldquo; Develop in a very active developer such
as Xtol or Microphen &amp;ndash; use a concentrated dilution, not a weak one,
particularly with Xtol &amp;ndash; and add 30-40% to the standard development
time for your film. It&amp;rsquo;ll be okay. &lt;strong&gt;Thor Lancelot Simon&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;rdquo; []{#11}&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;to-avoid-dust&#34;&gt;To avoid dust&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some say that the only solution is to use preloaded film (in 4x5), and
recommend to shoot a backup when there are large tonal areas which would
be ruined by dusk. A picture can be also saved by
&lt;a href=&#34;dust-spotting.html&#34;&gt;spotting&lt;/a&gt;. I try to avoid using the changing dome
whenever possible, by using bathrooms or closets at night, sealing the
openings with the dark cloth. My procedure is the following. I clean
each holder with a paintbrush and sometimes canned air. I insert all the
darkslides with the white sides facing out, leaving only about one inch
open, and I stack them on top of each other. This minimizes the chance
of the dusk getting on the holders or inside. I open the film box, but
keep the film between the two cardboard sheets, and put it on my knees.
I extract each sheet of film only to load it, which minimizes the time
it can collect dust. When the loading is done, I put the holders
directly into plastic ziplocks. []{#12}&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;to-avoid-forgetting-equipment&#34;&gt;To avoid forgetting equipment&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Put everything in the same place, and use a check list. []{#13}&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;to-avoid-opening-holders&#34;&gt;To avoid opening holders&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Make sure to reposition the tabs which prevent accidental opening. They
tend to come loose very easily. Be careful whenever you grab your
holders. []{#14}&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;to-avoid-cross-processing&#34;&gt;To avoid cross-processing&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Write on a separate sheet of papers the nature of each sheet exposed
(and, if you are really serious, exposure information, etc&amp;hellip;) []{#15}&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;to-avoid-other-dumb-mistakes&#34;&gt;To avoid other dumb mistakes&amp;hellip;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Triple check and good luck :-) []{#16}&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-mysterious-double-image&#34;&gt;The mysterious double image&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After long exposures, if you are not lucky, you might observe a double
image on all or part of the film. There seem to be four distinct causes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;pinhole in bellows or lensboard (only with very small f-stop)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;periodic vibrations&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;shifting of the film, which may not have been firmly seated in the
bottom of the holder. to avoid, give a rap to the holder before
exposure to make sure the film is already shifted if it&amp;rsquo;s going to.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;popping or bowing, due to humidity or temp changes as the film was
freely exposed to air inside the camera instead of the somewhat
air-tight film holder with a closed darkslide. to avoid, remove the
darkslide and wait something like 5 or 10 minutes before exposure.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(based on &lt;a href=&#34;double-image.html&#34;&gt;comments by Paul Butzi and Jonh Sparks&lt;/a&gt;.)
[]{#17}&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;light-leaks&#34;&gt;Light leaks&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Test all the suspects elements (&lt;a href=&#34;leaks.html&#34;&gt;more details&lt;/a&gt;). It can be
holders, camera, or the combination of both. Some sort of flare, due to
the large image circle light bouncing off belows, can also look like a
leak. Readyload holders require &lt;a href=&#34;holders.html#readyloads&#34;&gt;particular
precautions&lt;/a&gt;. Covering the camera with the dark
cloth while the film is in it might help.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;view-or-add-comments-http-www-greenspun-com-com-qtluong-photography-lf-mistakes-html&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.greenspun.com/com/qtluong/photography/lf/mistakes.html&#34;&gt;View or add comments&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Large Format Primer</title>
      <link>http://lflf.surge.sh/start/why/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lflf.surge.sh/start/why/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Summary: This article explains what large format photography is about,
and weights the advantages and disadvantages of using a large format
camera. It also provides references for further information.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-is-a-large-format-camera&#34;&gt;What is a Large format camera?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s grand-dad&amp;rsquo;s bellows box-like camera, where you had to disappear
under a dark cloth. The principle remains the same, however nowadays
they have evolved into precise and sophisticated instruments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With a few notable exceptions, these cameras share the following
characteristics:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Large image size&lt;/strong&gt;: 4x5 inches (10x12cm), the most popular format
by far, up to 20x24 inches (the Polaroid camera, which can be rented
on-site for a reasonable fee). The film comes in separate sheets
rather than rolls, but see below.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Flexible bellows connecting the front and back&lt;/strong&gt;: they allow the
use of a range of focal lengths (with different lenses. there are no
zooms in such formats) and focussing distances, as well as providing
for lateral adjustments and angular adjustments between film plane
and lens plane.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ground glass viewing&lt;/strong&gt;: makes it possible to assess the image with
great accuracy once you get used to the dimness and inversion.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Interchangeable lenses&lt;/strong&gt;: you are not limited to a particular
mount.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By contrast, Medium format cameras use roll-film which is 6cm wide so
that the format available on those cameras are (all in cm) 4.5x6, 6x6,
6x7,6x9,6x12,6x17. Therefore they produce image whose size is less than
that produced by large format cameras (hence the name). The vast
majority of medium format cameras operate a bit like 35mm cameras
(&amp;ldquo;small format&amp;rdquo;) and in particular don&amp;rsquo;t have features 2,3,4. However, a
few medium format cameras share these features, and are also considered
on this web site, since they actually operate like large format cameras.
On the other hand, with almost all the large format cameras it is
possible to use roll-film holders of various sizes and to therefore
produce medium-format images.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-are-the-main-benefits-of-the-large-format-camera&#34;&gt;What are the main benefits of the large format camera?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Larger image size.&lt;/strong&gt; Results are sharper, have a better tonality,
and are grain-free. A 4x5 has 13 times the area of a 35mm frame. A
5x7 has 25 times that area. Contact printing gives an image whose
delicacy cannot be matched by any enlargment, and allow a number of
&amp;ldquo;alternative&amp;rdquo; processes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Camera movements.&lt;/strong&gt; You have more control on the final geometry of
the photographed objects and of the perspective as well as on the
areas of sharpness.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Individual sheets of film.&lt;/strong&gt; You can use as many types of film as
you like easily, easily, including Polaroid, and process each sheet
of film individually for optimum results. The latter point makes it
possible to use Ansel Adams Zone System for black and white film.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contemplative approach.&lt;/strong&gt; You take your time for each image This
is the flip-side of the drawbacks: you spend so much time on a
single exposure, and invest so much effort in it that you&amp;rsquo;re
compelled to think it through carefully and do it right.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-are-the-main-drawbacks-of-the-large-format-camera&#34;&gt;What are the main drawbacks of the large format camera?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Everything is manual&lt;/strong&gt;. Most other cameras do some things
automatically for us that we take for granted &amp;ndash; like preventing
fogged film, double-exposures, non-exposures and so on. You need to
remember to do things that were never an issue even with the most
manual 35mm camera. As a result, &lt;a href=&#34;mistakes.html&#34;&gt;there are more ways to make
mistakes than you could ever imagine.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Equipment and film:&lt;/strong&gt; the equipment is bulky, heavy (a good tripod
is necessary) and relatively expensive. The cost per photograph is
considerably higher than the same image in smaller format. Think of
it as being proportional to the film area.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Larger magnification: longer focals are needed for the same angle
of view:&lt;/strong&gt; The equivalent of a 24mm in 35mm is a &lt;sup&gt;75&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;90&lt;/sub&gt; lens in 4x5,
a 120mm lens in 5x7. Depth of field is a serious problem. The
cameras movements become *necessary* to put everything in focus,
and even though some subjects cannot be focussed entirely. Start
thinking f32 where you thought f5.6 ! As a result you often get very
long exposures, so wind shake (esp. with vegetation) and reciprocity
failure begin to take their toll. Work which requires naturally a
high degree of magnification, ie macro and tele-photo, is
particularly impractical, the former because of the depth of field
limitations, the second because lenses would have to be insanely
long.&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Everything takes a long time&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;loading/unloading your holders at home&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;moving around your heavy backpack or case and tripod&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;setting your camera&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;composing, esp. in low light with slow / wide-angle lenses (f8
max aperture is common)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;focussing: tricks are necessary to overcome the depth of field
problem&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;exposing: long exposures are quite common.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is impractical to photograph quick action or candids, and even in
landscape you&amp;rsquo;ll end up missing optimal conditions. Your
productivity in terms of number of images (but not necessarily in
terms of number of great images) will be very reduced. Think a dozen
shots or less when you thought a few rolls. Even though your
friends/spouse will complain about the waiting.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Besides, you&amp;rsquo;ll discover by yourself many quirks of Large format
photography, like the fact that the dark cloth sometimes tend to fly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;A_little_too_windy_for_8x10.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;A_little_too_windy_for_8x10.small.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;{width=&amp;ldquo;200&amp;rdquo;
height=&amp;ldquo;138&amp;rdquo;}&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a photograph of my friend Charles attempting to use a
darkcloth for focus and composition on a 8x10 . 40 mph winds were just
a little to strong for the darkcloth. He ended up using the viewfinder
and foot scale with this 300 mm setup. &lt;strong&gt;Mark Cieslikowski&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;pollack.html&#34;&gt;A vivid account by Michael Pollack&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[]{#size}&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-is-the-real-gain-compared-to-other-formats&#34;&gt;What is the real gain compared to other formats?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The consensus seems to be that as far as enlargements are concerned, the
difference between 4x5 and 35mm is huge, but that the &lt;a href=&#34;quality.html&#34;&gt;difference
between 4x5 and 6x7&lt;/a&gt; will show up only in big
enlargements, 16x20 or larger. At 16x20 modern LF lenses have a slight
edge due to reduced granularity and high contrast, above that, modern
4x5 wins due to granularity. However, you will see a bigger difference
with format for B&amp;amp;W prints than with color prints. On the other hand, a
&lt;a href=&#34;contact-print.html&#34;&gt;contact print&lt;/a&gt; has a special quality that some feel
cannot be obtained by an enlargement. Contact printing is also the only
way to work with some alternative process such as paladium/platinium,
carbon, etc&amp;hellip; []{#price}&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;will-i-have-to-sell-the-house&#34;&gt;Will I have to sell the house?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Large format photography is actually not that expensive, especially
&lt;a href=&#34;price-med.html&#34;&gt;compared to medium format photography&lt;/a&gt; (the prices for
the 35mm market are influenced by the fact that it is quite
consumer-oriented), and a good large format system can be built for no
more than a good modern medium format system. There is also possibility
to do large format on a budget. A fairly good 4x5 can be bought used for
less than \$500, and if you are willing to accept some limitations, you
can get something which works for a couple hundred of dollars. The
latest lenses are indeed very expensive, on the other hand there are a
number of older lenses which are really inexpensive, a couple of hundred
dollars or less. Most of the lenses will be totally appropriate for B&amp;amp;W
work. They don&amp;rsquo;t have to be as sharp as lenses for smaller formats.
Modern lenses, which will produce results virtually indistinguishable
from the the latest designs, can be bought used for a rather reasonnable
price. Since LF systems are usually not submitted to an heavy use like
smaller formats, gear which is decades old will usually work fine. A
great news is that as you have built a good set of lenses, when you
upgrade to a better camera, you just keep them, and maybe change the
lensboards. At one point I was hesitating between the Pentax 67 (one of
the cheapest MF systems) and 4x5. One of the reasons which got me
decided for the 4x5 was that the price of the 4x5 system was a little
lower. Film looks expensive too, but you won&amp;rsquo;t shoot as many images as
you used to. If you do color, you&amp;rsquo;ll probably have to have your film
processed by a lab. The total cost of a 4x5 Velvia (film+processing) is
less than \$4, the cost of a 5x7 less than \$8. On the other hand, B&amp;amp;W
film home processed is quite cheap.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-to-find-more-information&#34;&gt;How to find more information?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;books/&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Recommended books&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;: for instruction as well as inspiration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journals:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is only one journal devoted exclusively to large format: []{}&lt;a href=&#34;http://greenspun.com/ct/qtluong/photography/lf/why.html?send_to=http://www.viewcamera.com&#34;&gt;View
Camera
TM&lt;/a&gt;,
published by Steve Simmons (&lt;a href=&#34;mailto:Largformat@aol.com&#34;&gt;Largformat@aol.com&lt;/a&gt;). The quality has been
overall high compared to the mainstream magazines. Over the past few
years, the magazine has concentrated on interviews and portfolios, in
which the emphasis is on vision and photographs, rather than technique.
Earlier in its history, the journal had more technical articles, but
because it tries not to rehash topics which had been already published,
the information really useful for LF beginners is limited in current
issues. You could order back issues, but if you&amp;rsquo;re after technical basic
material, you&amp;rsquo;d certainly be better served by
&lt;a href=&#34;books/general.html&#34;&gt;books&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although not exclusively devoted to LF, &lt;a href=&#34;http://greenspun.com/ct/qtluong/photography/lf/why.html?send_to=http://www.phototechmag.com/&#34;&gt;Photo
Techniques&lt;/a&gt;
(USA) regulary runs more detailed reviews of LF equipment written by
actual users, as well as excellent how-to articles on LF techniques.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Web Discussion forums:&lt;/strong&gt; The &lt;a href=&#34;http://lflf.surge.sh/lfforum&#34;&gt;LF Q&amp;amp;A forum&lt;/a&gt; associated on
this site has proven to be the best place on the internet for discussion
of LF related issues. It is very focussed, yet has the most active
participation of any LF bulletin boards on the web. Other LF discussion
forums on the web include:
&lt;a href=&#34;http://greenspun.com/ct/qtluong/photography/lf/why.html?send_to=http://www.f32.net&#34;&gt;f32.net&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&#34;http://greenspun.com/ct/qtluong/photography/lf/why.html?send_to=http://www.photo.net&#34;&gt;photo.net&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&#34;http://greenspun.com/ct/qtluong/photography/lf/why.html?send_to=http://www.graflex.org/helpboard/&#34;&gt;graflex.org&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&#34;http://greenspun.com/ct/qtluong/photography/lf/why.html?send_to=http://www.viewcamera.com/forum/&#34;&gt;view
camera&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&#34;http://greenspun.com/ct/qtluong/photography/lf/why.html?send_to=http://www.apug.org&#34;&gt;apug.org&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Usenet:&lt;/strong&gt; The newsgroup:
&lt;a href=&#34;http://greenspun.com/ct/qtluong/photography/lf/why.html?send_to=news:rec.photo.equipment.large-format&#34;&gt;rec.photo.equipment.large-format&lt;/a&gt;
dedicated exclusively to LF photography is one of the best places on the
internet to discuss. This newsgroup is one of the most civil on Usenet,
but still, it is unmoderated, so flame wars occur from time to time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mailing lists&lt;/strong&gt; There used to be a mailing list, the &amp;ldquo;Large Format
Digest&amp;rdquo;, discontinued since the creation of the previously mentioned
newsgroup. Besides reading it from the web, you can subscribe to the &lt;a href=&#34;http://lflf.surge.sh/lfforum&#34;&gt;LF
Q&amp;amp;A forum&lt;/a&gt; to read it by email.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;PS. I started large format photography in 1993. There were a lot of
things which were mysterious back then. After shooting thousands sheets
of film, some of them are still mysterious, but I have beneficiated from
advice of really knowlegeable persons on the net. I wrote this series in
order to try and give back by answering the questions that I was myself
asking a couple of years ago. It is written with location and field
photography in mind. I have only very little knowledge about studio
work.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Shooting LF is not difficult, from MF to LF</title>
      <link>http://lflf.surge.sh/start/from-mf-to-lf/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lflf.surge.sh/start/from-mf-to-lf/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;With analog camera and lens prices down to levels no one could have dreamt of as little as twenty years ago, the introduction of digital cameras has opened the door to all kinds of exotic equipment for those who choose to shoot film. However, there seems to be a significant barrier to entry. It does not seem to dissuade easily people from getting into 35mm, but certainly holds them back when they consider buying into MF equipment. From there, even very seasoned photographers seem to view LF as a nigh impossible step. Are the barriers really that high and is the difference that large?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-choice-to-work-with-film&#34;&gt;The choice to work with film&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regardless of the size you choose to work with, there is a very conscious choice involved in shooting film. Quite to the contrary of the general availability and affordability of great photographic equipment, film, places that process it or stock chemicals to do it at home have become scarcer and more expensive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many photographers these days have very possibly never even owned or photographed with any analog camera, let alone system. With photographing, I mean consciously taking a picture, carefully evaluating variables such as film type and speed, lighting, aperture and shutter settings, etc. As such, this is not counting the classic 35mm point and shoot cameras offering only full auto mode. To them, LF may not be the way to go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For those who grew up with film or who shot it for artistic purposes, digital has often been a blessing or a necessary evil. Even though my first camera was a Pentax Spotmatic, followed by various Nikon 35mm film cameras, I too, at some stage abandoned film. As a wildlife photographer, the flexibility, cheap high volume workflow, and the possibility to share pretty much as soon as I shot, meant that digital was great, and film was as good as dead. Or so I thought.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As time passed and I, like many of you, kept upgrading to newer generations of digital cameras, I sometime glanced at analog gear. Remembering the luscious, saturated Velvia colors projected on the wall, I started buying and shooting analog again. First in 35mm (Nikon F6, Contax G2 kits, Leica M6), but soon I was shooting all sorts of MF equipment too (Mamiya 7 and 645 Pro TL, Hasselblad 501C, Fuji GW690II, GW690III, GA645Zi, Bronica ETRSi, GS-1, Pentax 645N and others). MF rapidly overtook 35mm for me as the creative and print possibilities it offers are much greater.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the years, I increasingly started to shoot black and white film in addition to Velvia. The satisfaction of projecting the large slides on the wall or watching them on a light table is so hard to describe. Then at some stage, you take identical or similar shots with your digital camera and on Velvia. Once processed and on the screen, there is a difference between night and day. What more reason do you need to shoot film? Motivations and purposes will differ, but we all have our reason to shoot film and I strongly feel film has a solid place in today&amp;rsquo;s world of photography.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;medium-format-or-large-format&#34;&gt;Medium format or large format&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The basic assumption for the purpose of this article is that your photography lends itself to both formats and that you currently probably shoot MF in addition to another system. Whether it is landscape, fashion, portrait or other, medium and large format have many specializations in which both could work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a nutshell, medium format gear is often comparatively portable. Add to this that quite a few cameras can be shot hand-held that eliminates the need for a tripod and offers flexibility. This makes for quite a compelling proposition. However, large format offers the big advantage of the larger negative or slide and in many cases the movements of the camera that open a whole new world of creative possibilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For those of us who are willing or routinely carry a tripod and a heavy pack of gear, large format seems to be a great choice. Still, many people do not take the leap. The hurdle appears to be high, which is a shame.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-large-format-hurdle&#34;&gt;The large format hurdle&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So your work could potentially benefit from the creative freedom of a large format system, or you are addicted to the big negatives and slides like many of us. You look at classifieds and eBay listings and see the greatest of gear, but just can not make up your mind to buy into it. My question is, why not? Assuming you have shot film before and are familiar with camera basics, the hurdle is much lower than you think. In random order:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Large format is expensive.&lt;/strong&gt; If you have read until here, you have probably also looked at classifieds. If you have, you will have noticed that a great LF set-up costs less than an enthusiast level digital camera (monorail cameras including a simple lens, a few film holders and some bits and bobs sell for as little as 300 euros on Ebay and locally! A full wooden LF field kit can be had for 750 euros if you are patient). The difference is that the LF equipment is not a direct write-off, but should sell for similar money in the future if looked after carefully.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Where to start?&lt;/strong&gt; There is so much gear on sale that finding a first camera can be confusing. This is true to an extend, however, if you carefully think about what you want to shoot and where, life becomes a lot simpler. If you want to shoot in a studio and want maximum movement, monorails are great and sell for ridiculously little money (cameras without accessories from anywhere as low as 200 euros). If you want portability, any of the wooden field cameras will be great (I just saw an &amp;ldquo;as new&amp;rdquo; Shen Hao field for 500 euros). And if you insist on hand held shooting, old press cameras are an option (anywhere from 150 euros and up depending on their condition), as are several modern developments. From there you can always migrate to bigger or better. Chances are that if you stick to the same format, all lenses (and probably lens boards too) and film holders will be directly compatible. Your light meter, focusing loupe, dark cloth and so on will also continue to serve you well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Large format is heavy.&lt;/strong&gt; While not lightweight, an LF system can very much be as heavy or light as you want. This depends on size, types and numbers of lenses and holders, tripod, etc. I have never accurately weighed my travel kit (wooden field camera, three lenses, 10 holders, boxes of sheet film, changing tent, light meter, focusing loupe, etc), but it comes in at around twenty five pounds, including the thinktank bag it all fits into.My full Hasselblad MF kit including three lenses, several backs, two bodies and accessories weighs about the same. In contrast, my digital wildlife kit is significantly heavier, at around thirty-five pounds (although I can shave a few pounds off by leaving the super tele at home). My &amp;ldquo;ultralight&amp;rdquo; LF kit consists of a wista field, 6 film holders, three lenses (75mm, 150mm, 210mm), a loupe, light meter and some bits and bobs. It fits in a think tank sling back and comes in between ten and twelve pounds! Granted, theres a tripod that is carried separately, but there are plenty of lightweight alternatives with simple ballheads or level heads available.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Large format is too complicated.&lt;/strong&gt; Technical cameras, unlike the technical aspects of a space shuttle, are not very complicated at all. Yes, they do require some time and effort to learn, but there are always people there to help, like on this forum. In addition, there are great books such as &amp;ldquo;Using the view camera&amp;rdquo; that provide excellent information on how to use your camera and its movements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Film and supplies are hard to come by.&lt;/strong&gt; It is true that it is unlikely that your local photo shop stock sheet film and other supplies. However, there are many great sources online where you can order sheet film in many formats as well as pretty much anything else you could need or want.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;No access to a darkroom.&lt;/strong&gt; While needed for printing your photos, you do not need one to load and develop sheet film. Most of the people here probably do not have access to a full dark room. Instead, they work with changing tents or bags and daylight developing tanks. There work great and are widely available. Harrison tents are nice and pack very compact, but I have found loading my expert drums easier in a Calumet pop-up tent that sells for around 90 euros.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Developing film is prohibitively expensive or unavailable in my area.&lt;/strong&gt; This is the case for many photographers. There are probably professional laboratories in your country of residence that will receive and return film by mail for processing. This, however, can indeed be expensive (I am not sure about other countries, but the cheapest I have found in the Netherlands is 4.5 euros ex-vat and shipping for a 4x5 sheet). However, developing your own film is quite easy. Particularly if you choose to shoot black and white (My total costs for a drum with 6 sheets of B&amp;amp;W films is around 1,25 euros and includes developer, stop batch, fixer and a few drops of photo flow). Color (slide) film is somewhat more complicated but do-able. If developing seems too daunting, why not take a darkroom course. You will learn how to do it and have the confidence to experiment at home. And if you ask nicely, you may very well meet someone who is willing to show you how its done for free.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;in-conclusion&#34;&gt;In conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Large format has much to offer and provides great creative possibilities when compared to small and medium format alternatives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If your photography lends itself to working with large format film, or if you desire to print large, there is little reason not to try.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is no mystique to LF and hurdles to a switch to LF are much lower in real life than they may seem when reading about them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Basic photographic principles apply, just like they do for any other format. If you are familiar with them, you will feel comfortable with an LF camera.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is no such thing as mutual exclusivity. I for one continue to shoot digital, MF and LF. Each of the systems has its merits. View them as complementary, rather than incompatible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And finally, yes, people will look at you when you shoot a LF camera. Most people will just look surprised, however, if you get any, reactions are almost always positive.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>