<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>A large format photography home page on Large Format Photography</title>
    <link>http://lflf.surge.sh/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in A large format photography home page on Large Format Photography</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 01 Apr 2015 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://lflf.surge.sh/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Shooting LF is not difficult, from MF to LF</title>
      <link>http://lflf.surge.sh/from-mf-to-lf/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Apr 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lflf.surge.sh/from-mf-to-lf/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;With analog camera and lens prices down to levels no one could have dreamt of as little as twenty years ago, the introduction of digital cameras has opened the door to all kinds of exotic equipment for those who choose to shoot film. However, there seems to be a significant barrier to entry. It does not seem to dissuade easily people from getting into 35mm, but certainly holds them back when they consider buying into MF equipment. From there, even very seasoned photographers seem to view LF as a nigh impossible step. Are the barriers really that high and is the difference that large?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;the-choice-to-work-with-film&#34;&gt;The choice to work with film&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regardless of the size you choose to work with, there is a very conscious choice involved in shooting film. Quite to the contrary of the general availability and affordability of great photographic equipment, film, places that process it or stock chemicals to do it at home have become scarcer and more expensive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many photographers these days have very possibly never even owned or photographed with any analog camera, let alone system. With photographing, I mean consciously taking a picture, carefully evaluating variables such as film type and speed, lighting, aperture and shutter settings, etc. As such, this is not counting the classic 35mm point and shoot cameras offering only full auto mode. To them, LF may not be the way to go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For those who grew up with film or who shot it for artistic purposes, digital has often been a blessing or a necessary evil. Even though my first camera was a Pentax Spotmatic, followed by various Nikon 35mm film cameras, I too, at some stage abandoned film. As a wildlife photographer, the flexibility, cheap high volume workflow, and the possibility to share pretty much as soon as I shot, meant that digital was great, and film was as good as dead. Or so I thought.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As time passed and I, like many of you, kept upgrading to newer generations of digital cameras, I sometime glanced at analog gear. Remembering the luscious, saturated Velvia colors projected on the wall, I started buying and shooting analog again. First in 35mm (Nikon F6, Contax G2 kits, Leica M6), but soon I was shooting all sorts of MF equipment too (Mamiya 7 and 645 Pro TL, Hasselblad 501C, Fuji GW690II, GW690III, GA645Zi, Bronica ETRSi, GS-1, Pentax 645N and others). MF rapidly overtook 35mm for me as the creative and print possibilities it offers are much greater.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the years, I increasingly started to shoot black and white film in addition to Velvia. The satisfaction of projecting the large slides on the wall or watching them on a light table is so hard to describe. Then at some stage, you take identical or similar shots with your digital camera and on Velvia. Once processed and on the screen, there is a difference between night and day. What more reason do you need to shoot film? Motivations and purposes will differ, but we all have our reason to shoot film and I strongly feel film has a solid place in today&amp;rsquo;s world of photography.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;medium-format-or-large-format&#34;&gt;Medium format or large format&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The basic assumption for the purpose of this article is that your photography lends itself to both formats and that you currently probably shoot MF in addition to another system. Whether it is landscape, fashion, portrait or other, medium and large format have many specializations in which both could work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a nutshell, medium format gear is often comparatively portable. Add to this that quite a few cameras can be shot hand-held that eliminates the need for a tripod and offers flexibility. This makes for quite a compelling proposition. However, large format offers the big advantage of the larger negative or slide and in many cases the movements of the camera that open a whole new world of creative possibilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For those of us who are willing or routinely carry a tripod and a heavy pack of gear, large format seems to be a great choice. Still, many people do not take the leap. The hurdle appears to be high, which is a shame.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;the-large-format-hurdle&#34;&gt;The large format hurdle&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So your work could potentially benefit from the creative freedom of a large format system, or you are addicted to the big negatives and slides like many of us. You look at classifieds and eBay listings and see the greatest of gear, but just can not make up your mind to buy into it. My question is, why not? Assuming you have shot film before and are familiar with camera basics, the hurdle is much lower than you think. In random order:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Large format is expensive.&lt;/strong&gt; If you have read until here, you have probably also looked at classifieds. If you have, you will have noticed that a great LF set-up costs less than an enthusiast level digital camera (monorail cameras including a simple lens, a few film holders and some bits and bobs sell for as little as 300 euros on Ebay and locally! A full wooden LF field kit can be had for 750 euros if you are patient). The difference is that the LF equipment is not a direct write-off, but should sell for similar money in the future if looked after carefully.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Where to start?&lt;/strong&gt; There is so much gear on sale that finding a first camera can be confusing. This is true to an extend, however, if you carefully think about what you want to shoot and where, life becomes a lot simpler. If you want to shoot in a studio and want maximum movement, monorails are great and sell for ridiculously little money (cameras without accessories from anywhere as low as 200 euros). If you want portability, any of the wooden field cameras will be great (I just saw an &amp;ldquo;as new&amp;rdquo; Shen Hao field for 500 euros). And if you insist on hand held shooting, old press cameras are an option (anywhere from 150 euros and up depending on their condition), as are several modern developments. From there you can always migrate to bigger or better. Chances are that if you stick to the same format, all lenses (and probably lens boards too) and film holders will be directly compatible. Your light meter, focusing loupe, dark cloth and so on will also continue to serve you well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Large format is heavy.&lt;/strong&gt; While not lightweight, an LF system can very much be as heavy or light as you want. This depends on size, types and numbers of lenses and holders, tripod, etc. I have never accurately weighed my travel kit (wooden field camera, three lenses, 10 holders, boxes of sheet film, changing tent, light meter, focusing loupe, etc), but it comes in at around twenty five pounds, including the thinktank bag it all fits into.My full Hasselblad MF kit including three lenses, several backs, two bodies and accessories weighs about the same. In contrast, my digital wildlife kit is significantly heavier, at around thirty-five pounds (although I can shave a few pounds off by leaving the super tele at home). My &amp;ldquo;ultralight&amp;rdquo; LF kit consists of a wista field, 6 film holders, three lenses (75mm, 150mm, 210mm), a loupe, light meter and some bits and bobs. It fits in a think tank sling back and comes in between ten and twelve pounds! Granted, thereÕs a tripod that is carried separately, but there are plenty of lightweight alternatives with simple ballheads or level heads available.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Large format is too complicated.&lt;/strong&gt; Technical cameras, unlike the technical aspects of a space shuttle, are not very complicated at all. Yes, they do require some time and effort to learn, but there are always people there to help, like on this forum. In addition, there are great books such as &amp;ldquo;Using the view camera&amp;rdquo; that provide excellent information on how to use your camera and its movements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Film and supplies are hard to come by.&lt;/strong&gt; It is true that it is unlikely that your local photo shop stock sheet film and other supplies. However, there are many great sources online where you can order sheet film in many formats as well as pretty much anything else you could need or want.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;No access to a darkroom.&lt;/strong&gt; While needed for printing your photos, you do not need one to load and develop sheet film. Most of the people here probably do not have access to a full dark room. Instead, they work with changing tents or bags and daylight developing tanks. There work great and are widely available. Harrison tents are nice and pack very compact, but I have found loading my expert drums easier in a Calumet pop-up tent that sells for around 90 euros.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Developing film is prohibitively expensive or unavailable in my area.&lt;/strong&gt; This is the case for many photographers. There are probably professional laboratories in your country of residence that will receive and return film by mail for processing. This, however, can indeed be expensive (I am not sure about other countries, but the cheapest I have found in the Netherlands is 4.5 euros ex-vat and shipping for a 4x5 sheet). However, developing your own film is quite easy. Particularly if you choose to shoot black and white (My total costs for a drum with 6 sheets of B&amp;amp;W films is around 1,25 euros and includes developer, stop batch, fixer and a few drops of photo flow). Color (slide) film is somewhat more complicated but do-able. If developing seems too daunting, why not take a darkroom course. You will learn how to do it and have the confidence to experiment at home. And if you ask nicely, you may very well meet someone who is willing to show you how itÕs done for free.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;in-conclusion&#34;&gt;In conclusion&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Large format has much to offer and provides great creative possibilities when compared to small and medium format alternatives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If your photography lends itself to working with large format film, or if you desire to print large, there is little reason not to try.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is no mystique to LF and hurdles to a switch to LF are much lower in real life than they may seem when reading about them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Basic photographic principles apply, just like they do for any other format. If you are familiar with them, you will feel comfortable with an LF camera.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is no such thing as mutual exclusivity. I for one continue to shoot digital, MF and LF. Each of the systems has its merits. View them as complementary, rather than incompatible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And finally, yes, people will look at you when you shoot a LF camera. Most people will just look surprised, however, if you get any, reactions are almost always positive.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Closer Look at a Large Format Photo</title>
      <link>http://lflf.surge.sh/start/example/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 1999 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lflf.surge.sh/start/example/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;autumn-close.3.html&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;autumn-close.3.small.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;{width=&amp;ldquo;120&amp;rdquo;
height=&amp;ldquo;120&amp;rdquo;}&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;autumn-close.2.html&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;autumn-close.2.small.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;{width=&amp;ldquo;120&amp;rdquo;
height=&amp;ldquo;120&amp;rdquo;}&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;autumn-close.5.html&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;autumn-close.5.small.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;{width=&amp;ldquo;120&amp;rdquo;
height=&amp;ldquo;120&amp;rdquo;}&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;autumn-close.8.html&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;autumn-close.8.small.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;{width=&amp;ldquo;120&amp;rdquo;
height=&amp;ldquo;120&amp;rdquo;}&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;autumn-close.6.html&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;autumn-close.6.small.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;{width=&amp;ldquo;120&amp;rdquo;
height=&amp;ldquo;120&amp;rdquo;}&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;autumn-close.7.html&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;autumn-close.7.small.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;{width=&amp;ldquo;120&amp;rdquo;
height=&amp;ldquo;120&amp;rdquo;}&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;autumn-close.9.html&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;autumn-close.9.small.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;{width=&amp;ldquo;120&amp;rdquo;
height=&amp;ldquo;120&amp;rdquo;}&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;autumn-close.4.html&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;autumn-close.4.small.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;{width=&amp;ldquo;120&amp;rdquo;
height=&amp;ldquo;120&amp;rdquo;}&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;autumn-close.11.html&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;autumn-close.11.small.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;{width=&amp;ldquo;120&amp;rdquo;
height=&amp;ldquo;120&amp;rdquo;}&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;autumn-close.14.html&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;autumn-close.14.small.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;{width=&amp;ldquo;120&amp;rdquo;
height=&amp;ldquo;120&amp;rdquo;}&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;autumn-close.13.html&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;autumn-close.13.small.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;{width=&amp;ldquo;120&amp;rdquo;
height=&amp;ldquo;120&amp;rdquo;}&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;autumn-close.12.html&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;autumn-close.12.small.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;{width=&amp;ldquo;120&amp;rdquo;
height=&amp;ldquo;120&amp;rdquo;}&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;autumn-close.17.html&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;autumn-close.17.small.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;{width=&amp;ldquo;120&amp;rdquo;
height=&amp;ldquo;120&amp;rdquo;}&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;autumn-close.18.html&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;autumn-close.18.small.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;{width=&amp;ldquo;120&amp;rdquo;
height=&amp;ldquo;120&amp;rdquo;}&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;autumn-close.15.html&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;autumn-close.15.small.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;{width=&amp;ldquo;120&amp;rdquo;
height=&amp;ldquo;120&amp;rdquo;}&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;autumn-close.16.html&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;autumn-close.16.small.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;{width=&amp;ldquo;120&amp;rdquo;
height=&amp;ldquo;120&amp;rdquo;}&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those close-ups were extracted from the image below. Each of them contains enough detail to make a sharp photograph on its own. Click on them to view.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;autumn-reflections.html&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;autumn-reflections.small.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;{width=&amp;ldquo;300&amp;rdquo;
height=&amp;ldquo;214&amp;rdquo;}&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[]{#lf}&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For landscapes, I prefer &lt;a href=&#34;../canham/canham.html&#34;&gt;this large format (LF)
camera&lt;/a&gt;, because it produces an image which
matches my perception of a visually rich world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, because the size of the film is 5x7 inches (12.7cm x 17.8cm), the
camera records an amazing amount of detail, 25 times what is contained
in a regular 135 (24mm x 36mm) frame. Everything which I saw is on the
film, and even more. When I examine my transparencies under a lupe, I
notice from time to time details which escaped me when I was looking at
the scene.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that what I display here does not even capture the full detail in
the original transparency, but only a quarter of it: the scanning was
done only at a resolution necessary to produce a 24x30 inches (60 x 75
cm) print, which is 6000 x 9000 pixels. However, the transparency has a
resolution of at least 50 lpm, is 5x7 inches (12.7cm x 17.8cm) and
therefore could have been used to produce a quality digital image file
at least four times larger (12000 x 17000 pixels). Such a file would
have been close to 1 Gigabye. At the resolution used, there is
absolutely no fuzziness and no grain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, the LF camera is not rigid because the lens is connected to the
film plane with a bellows. This let me control the perspective and the
distribution of sharpness in a way which cannot be achieved with a
regular camera:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I remember the trees as beeing parallel to each other. The LF camera
renders them that way. However the camera is looking down since the
lake fills up more than two-thirds of the frame. With a regular
camera, this would cause the trees in the background to lean towards
the edge of the frame, which would not be quite right.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I remember each part of the scene with the same clarity. The LF
camera looks at the close objects sharply and looks at the horizon
sharply at the same time: notice that the grass in the foreground,
only a few feet in front of the camera, is seen as clearly as the
distant trees. In contrast, a regular camera has to focus either
close or far.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For this particular photograph, those adjustments were quite simple and
intuitive. It was getting dark fast. I didn&amp;rsquo;t want to make the
photograph in full daylight, because I knew that the colors would be
lost to the contrast, and instead I chose to wait for the quiet and soft
light of dusk. After leveling the camera, I lowered the lens using front
fall to obtain the composition I wanted. I then tilted the lens, which
tilts the plane of sharp focus, until it became horizontal. I was lucky
that day because the air was quite still, so even in the 15 second
exposure (necessitated by the f 22 aperture and the slow speed of Fuji
Velvia), there was only minimal blurring of the grasses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;.&#34;&gt;More large format landscapes&lt;/a&gt; - &lt;a href=&#34;../&#34;&gt;More about technical aspects of
large format photography&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Large Format Photography primer: equipment</title>
      <link>http://lflf.surge.sh/matos-begin.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 1999 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lflf.surge.sh/matos-begin.html</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;This article discusses what you need to start large format photography:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a camera&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;lens(es)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;film holders and film&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;tripod&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;accessories: darkcloth, focussing lupe, cable release, meter&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For an example of kit, see &lt;a href=&#34;camera-bag/&#34;&gt;inside my camera bag&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-camera&#34;&gt;The camera&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Think first about your intended application. 35mm cameras are universal, MF cameras and LF cameras are really more specialized. What kind of work are you going to do, and in which conditions ?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;which-format-to-use&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Which format to use ?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;roll-film&lt;/strong&gt; Shooting roll-film with a view camera is an interesting combination. There are cameras and backs which let you shoot 6x7, 6x9, 6x12, 6x17. Compared to 4x5, you don&amp;rsquo;t have to deal with sheet film, the cost is very low (lower than for 35mm actually, if the surface is considered), and there is a very wide choice of film. If you chose a 2x3 view camera, it can be actually cheaper than a lot of MF systems, and might not be heavier, especially if you buy lenses with small coverage. However, compared to convenentional MF systems, you gain &amp;ldquo;only&amp;rdquo; camera movements (their effect is not always very easy to judge on the small image area) and you loose a lot of ease of use (this might be a plus for folks willing to &amp;ldquo;slow down&amp;rdquo;). Another option that I find more interesting is to use a &lt;a href=&#34;#roll-film&#34;&gt;roll-film back&lt;/a&gt; with a 4x5 camera. There are 4x5 lightweight cameras wich are not much more heavy than 2x3 cameras. Then you can have the option of doing 4x5 if the opportunity looks very good. Speaking from my own experience and that of other folks, when you come home the 2x3 images will look a bit small if you have shot 4x5, and you will probably think that given the burden of carrying and operating a view camera, you&amp;rsquo;d rather have the big image. If you use a panoramic format like 6x12, this comparison might not apply.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4x5&lt;/strong&gt; This is in practice the smaller format where you can use sheet film (2x3 sheet film exists but is marginal). It is by far the most popular format, with lots of cameras, lenses (from 45mm to as long as the bellows will accomodate), film, different type of holders (including roll-film, polaroid, preloaded). For most people that&amp;rsquo;s the format of choice.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;5x7&lt;/strong&gt; The equipment is not really heavier than for 4x5: the lenses are most of the time the same, there are 6lbs cameras. It is mostly the holders which are bigger: they produce an image which is almost two times as large, but is more rectangular, in a format homothetic to 35mm and 6x9. It is large enough to produce decent contacts. but still small enough that it is relatively easy to enlarge. The only significant drawback comes from the scarcity of the film (as of summer 96, the only slide film available in the USA are Kodak EPP and EPR. Euro or Japaneese photographers have Fuji emulsions). One thing that I am really missing is the possibility to use Polaroid film, and quickloads. Processing and printing is more difficult to obtain with labs, and if you want a new color enlarger, you might have to buy a 8x10 enlarger. However, all these problems do not affect b&amp;amp;w photographers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;8x10 and larger&lt;/strong&gt; These formats gives you beautiful contact prints. Contact printing is required for some alternative process (like Platinium). The marginal quality over 4x5 or 5x7 obtained in enlargements is probably noticeable only for the extreme enlargements. The drawback is the size and weight of the equipment, as well as its cost. Older 8x10 cameras can be have for (relatively) cheap, and a Philips camera is not much heavier than some 4x5 cameras. However larger formats (sometimes called Ultra LF) require a considerable amount of work.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-features-to-look-for-in-a-camera&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;What features to look for in a camera ?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are a few things to consider. There are more discussions about the various trade-offs (wood vs metal, monorail vs flatbed, etc&amp;hellip;) elsewhere on the &lt;a href=&#34;./&#34;&gt;LF page&lt;/a&gt;. Remember that YOU have to find out what your priorities are first, and that not every camera, no matter how highly praised, is for everyone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Portable enough.&lt;/strong&gt; Whereas all the folding cameras are portable and have a reasonnable weight (3lbs - 7 lbs), some monorails are too heavy and bulky to be used in the field. There is a tradeoff here between portability and and versatility (possibility to use many focals and movements), and also rigidity. Usually, for the same features, a wooden camera will be lighter, but often less compact than an equivalent metal field camera.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Allow you to use your focals of choice&lt;/strong&gt; All the cameras do what they are designed for with a normal lens. However, with shorter and longer lenses difficulties might arise:

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Short focals&lt;/strong&gt;. Some flatbed cameras have very limited wide-angle abilities, due to:

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;large minimum extension,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;fixed bellows (the bellows compression will make movements impossible unless you have a wide-angle bellows which is shorter and more flexible)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;beds showing in the field of viewA recessed lensboard can make up for some problems by allowing a larger lens to film distance than the focal length of your lens. However, they are expensive ($150) and the controls of the lens become hard to reach. A monorail is usually more flexible, since all of them have a small minimum extension, wide-angle bellows. Depending on the nature of the tripod mount attachment, the rail showing in the field of view might or might not be a problem, but there are sometimes optional short rails.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Long focals&lt;/strong&gt;. A camera with bellows which are too short will not allow you to use long lenses, or to do close-ups. The cure for this problem are very limited. You can use on some cameras a combinations of front tilts, or get an extension board (opposite of a recessed board), but this will give you only a few additional centimeters. Here, again monorails are more flexible, since you can usually purchase a longer rail and extension bellows.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Enough movements for your type of photography.&lt;/strong&gt; The monorails have all the movements, whereas some type of flat bed cameras have almost none. Studio photography usually requires a great deal of image control, architecture requires shifts to maintain correct perspective. Landscape require the less movements, although to obtain adequate depth of field due to the fact that longer focals are needed for a given field of view, some tilts are often necessary.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rigidity and precision of alignment&lt;/strong&gt; This is all about sharpness. To shoot in windy conditions you need a camera which is rigid enough so that the standards won&amp;rsquo;t move (resulting in unsharp pictures). The locks have to be strong enough so that the standards don&amp;rsquo;t move when you insert the holder. Misalignements between standards or within the back standard to the film plane might cause misfocus in some areas of the image (although this is critical for reproduction work, I doubt that for real shooting it matters). Generally speaking, the metal cameras are more rigid and precisely aligned than the wooden cameras. The lighweight cameras are more likely to have problems here.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ease of operation.&lt;/strong&gt; Geared controls, positive and well placed locks, spirit levels, various scales, zero detents, smooth operation, rear focussing (very important for macro work), etc.., all help. If complicated adjustments are used, a &lt;a href=&#34;yaw.html&#34;&gt;yaw-free&lt;/a&gt; design might help. This feature is not relevant otherwise.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;which-is-best-wood-or-metal&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Which is best, wood, or metal ?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main advantage of wood (besides being cheaper to work) is that it is lighter. A consequence is that for the same weight you can make a bigger camera, which in turn will provide you more movements and more extension. A typical example are the Wisner and Canhams which are quite bulky (for 4x5 cameras) but offer more movements and bellows than any other field cameras. A metal camera using the same design would weight more than 11 lbs. Wood is also much better at dampening high-frequency vibration than any metal or metal alloy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Metal has technically many advantages. It is more rigid, which result in less flexing and low frequency vibrations. This is good for long extensions. It is more solid, resulting in a more durable camera. If your tripod is knocked over by the wind, a metal camera is quite likely to remain functional with a few scratches, whereas a wooden camera could be totally destroyed. My reversible wooden back broke at the edge, which would have been unlikely to happy with metal. The stability with respect to environmental conditions like humidity and temperature is also better (one day my Canham would focus quite smoothly, one day it would be quite sticky). Last, it is easier to implement small features on metal. Therefore metal cameras tend generally to be more compact, and to offer greater accessory systems like reflex hoods, etc&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;which-cameras-to-consider-to-get-started-on-a-budget&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Which cameras to consider to get started on a budget?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is best to buy used equipment. Shutterbug (dealers advertisements, classified, swap announces) and the net are good sources. Some recommended used stores with knowledgeable and honest people are Midwest Photo Exchange and Lens and Repro. There is not much which can go wrong on a large format camera which has not been seriously abused, since there are no delicate small high precision parts or electronics. Older cameras are well usable, but usually lack the convenience of more modern designs. Some of them are so beat-up that they lost their original rigidity. Another thing to watch for is pinholes in the bellows. A new bellows can always be installed, but the price might be a significant fraction of that of the cheaper cameras. Here are some suggestions (refer to the reviews for more details):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cheapest.&lt;/strong&gt; A Speed or Crown Graphic press camera (at the expense of movements, not a good choice if you are interested in perspective control or depth of field control. A basic monorail like Calumet CC-400, Omega, Graphic View II (at the expense of portability, at about 8 lbs., they are a little heavy and bulky for hiking), Bender (if you like woodworking). A Burke and James (good movements, more portable than a monorail, might be a bit ratty). $250.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cheap.&lt;/strong&gt; A new Calumet Cadet (a monorail camera). $400. Toyo 45cx. $450. A used lightweight wood-field (such as the Tachihara). $400-$500. A Technika III (metal, flatbed, adequate movements). $600.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Still reasonable.&lt;/strong&gt; A new lightweight wood-field (around $700), a used Wista, a used Zone VI. The new Arca-Swiss discovery (maybe too recent to find used) and the Sinar A1 (monorail cameras).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-lenses&#34;&gt;The lenses&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-to-look-for-in-a-lens&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;What to look for in a lens ?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Focal.&lt;/strong&gt; You are probably familiar with 35mm. Pick up your favorite focals and find the equivalent LF focals either using &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.mat.uc.pt/~rps/photos/angles.html&#34;&gt;Rui Salgueiro&amp;rsquo;s field-of-view calculator&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&#34;http://www-swiss.ai.mit.edu/philg/photo/lens-table.html&#34;&gt;Ed Scott&amp;rsquo; comparison tables&lt;/a&gt;. Note however that while 5x7 is homothetic to 35mm, 4x5 and 8x10 are both more squarish. More folks are happy with just one lens in the LF world than in 35mm. Personnally, I would tend to err on the wide side, since cropping is not too much of an issue.&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Coverage.&lt;/strong&gt; A lens projects an image circle which must be large enough to cover the film area without vignetting. The absolute minimun which is required is the diagonal of the format. If some movements are used, the diameter of the image circle has to be larger to cover the film area. The larger this circle is, the more movements you can do. In particular, it is easy to calculate how must shift you can get knowing the image circle and the format. The image circle is usually expressed in a millimeter diameter, at infinity, and at a specific aperture of f/16 or f/22. Stopping down might increase its diameter. Focussing to closer distances always does.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For general use, make sure to get enough to be able to do some movements, maybe around 180mm for 4x5 and around 230mm for 5x7. Applications like table top and architecture photography often require extensive movements and therefore larger image circles. Lenses with more coverage than you need will be heavy, big, and expensive.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Maximum aperture.&lt;/strong&gt; You won&amp;rsquo;t use a LF lens wide open, however a large maximum aperture ( f/4.5 or f/5.6) makes viewing and focussing easier, especially if you are indoors or like to photograph in low light. However, for a given focal length, the faster lens will be larger, heavier and more expensive.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Portability.&lt;/strong&gt; Be careful here. Lenses of same focal lengths vary &lt;em&gt;considerably&lt;/em&gt; in size and weight ! Make sure to see the lens before buying. Generally speaking focal length, coverage, and speed contribute to a big lens, all other factors being equal. That&amp;rsquo;s where modern lenses don&amp;rsquo;t necessarily shine. A significant portion of the weight and bulk can be due to the shutter. Longer focal lengths and/or faster lenses often come with a big #3.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Optical quality.&lt;/strong&gt; Basically all the modern lenses (current models from Fuji,Nikon, Rodenstock, Schneider) are good enough, and very difficult to distinguish from each other at the apertures used in practice. For color work, it is generally recommended to stick to those, or to relatively recent multicoated lenses, although a single coated lens properly shaded might work fine. This is less critical for B&amp;amp;W. For details, see &lt;a href=&#34;lenses-general.html&#34;&gt;a general discussion&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fit.&lt;/strong&gt; Some big lenses cannot be used with some field cameras or with some lensboards. Also, make sure you have enough belows. When using long focal lengths you may consider choosing a telephoto design lens (usually designated with a &amp;ldquo;T&amp;rdquo;) rather than a regular design lens of the same focal length. These lenses require approximatively &lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; of the bellows a regular lens would. However, they are usually more expensive, have less coverage, and behave a bit weird with respect to tilts. They are not necessarily more compact or lighter.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Working shutter.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a list of recommendations and tests, see &lt;a href=&#34;http://greenspun.com/ct/qtluong/photography/lf/lf.html?send_to=http://www.hevanet.com/cperez/testing.html&#34;&gt;http://www.hevanet.com/cperez/testing.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;film-and-holders&#34;&gt;Film and holders&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conventional-vs-preloaded-film-quickload-readyload-polaroid&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Conventional vs preloaded film (Quickload, Readyload, Polaroid)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can either use film that you load yourself in cut-film holders or preloaded film.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the first case, you need a dark and relatively clean place to load your film holders (might be a problem when travelling), and to unload them. Dust might be a problem, you have to clean your holders carefully. You cannot have too many holders. With a large number of holders, not only you&amp;rsquo;ll be sure not to run out of film ready to shoot, but you&amp;rsquo;ll have to reload less often, and you can keep exposed film in holders, which makes tracking easier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Readyloads are from Kodak, Quickloads from Fuji. The readyloads from Kodak hold two sheets of film, the Quickloads hold one. The film is in a paper packet that you put in a special holder (they are made by Kodak, Fuji, Polaroid). Polaroid film can be processed instantly or latter, inside the holder. The other films are processed normally in the lab. Here are the advantages of preloaded film:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No need to load and unload. Especially nice in the field.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Almost dust-free. Because they&amp;rsquo;re factory loaded in a clean room, the only dust you get on the film is the dust that lands on it after you pull the envelope/darkslide.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lighter/Less bulky. Preloaded film allows you to carry more ready-to-use film (although in the long run, if you are using lots of film, it will end up being heavier) since you don&amp;rsquo;t have the weight of individual film holders.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Easier to track after exposure. You can just write information on each packet.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main disadvantages are&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;more expensive (a sheet of conventional Velvia 4x5 costs $1.7 vs $2.6 for preloaded)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;only a limited number of emulsions are offered by Fuji (in particular no B&amp;amp;W film), Kodak, and Polaroid (the non-instant film is Fuji film).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Kodak system is known to suffer from light leaks&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Less sharp (maybe). In a Camera and Darkroom article, J.Englender writes that the preloaded system do not yield as sharp results as conventional holders due to film flatness problems (the best results are obtained with Graphmatics, then conventional holders, Fuji and Kodak holders, and Polaroid holders). Many people ignore that.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;if you have a lot of film to carry on a long trip, the enveloppes end up adding up.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The best results for the preloaded films seems to be obtained using the dedicated holder (Fuji and Kodak), although the Fuji Quickload work OK with the Polaroid holder. The new 545i holder is significantly lighter than the old 545 which was all metal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conventional-cut-film-holders&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Conventional cut-film holders&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you decide not to use the preloaded systems but instead buy your film in sheets and load it, you have the choice between regular film holders which hold one sheet on each side, and Grafmatics. Generally speaking, if you buy used holders, check them carefully for dust and light leaks problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wooden holders tend to slide better in wooden cameras, and are slightly lighter than plastic holders, but they cannot be found new. As far as new holders are concerned, most people use Fidelity or Lisco holders, which are the cheapest. Some brands make more expensive holders, but nobody has been able to prove that they yield sharper pictures in usual working conditions. The extremity of the dark slide is marked with two colors (black and white) and raised dots so that you can remember whether they contain blank film or exposed film. In addition, there is a tab which is supposed to keep the dark slide locked and prevent you from removing it accidentally, as well as help you identified loaded vs empty holders, but I have found that it tends to be quite unreliable. Riteway makes a holder with a button instead of the tab, which is an improvement, but it is not compatible with some cameras.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;holders.html#grafmatics&#34;&gt;Grafmatics&lt;/a&gt; are more light and compact, and allow you to shoot in a sequence, but the loading is more difficult, esp. if you want to unload after using a holder only partially. They can be bought only used.&lt;a name=&#34;roll-film&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-name-roll-film-roll-film-backs-a&#34;&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;roll-film&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Roll-film backs&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;roll-film&#34;&gt;Roll film backs are available for all roll-film sizes to 6x12 the most common being 6x7 and 6x9. There are two types of roll-film holders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Graflock-type holders&lt;/strong&gt;: Some 4x5 cameras have a back (Graflock, this standard was introduced on the Graflex cameras) where you remove the ground-glass assembly and replace it with a roll-film back. There are plenty of brands to chose from: Graflex, Singer, Linhof (super-rollex), Mamiya RB, Horseman, some of which can be found for quite cheap.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Slide-in type holders&lt;/strong&gt;: These holders are flat because the film spools are at one end. They can be inserted under the ground glass like a sheet film holder. Almost all the cameras accept them, but be sure to check for compatibility. The Calumet holders are quite cheap and are now produced in 6x7, 6x9, 6x12 (the latter is quite expensive actually). Sinar has a vario holder which allow you to switch format (from 6x4.5 to 6x12) at any time, for $2500 new.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Personnally I prefer the second type, because I find them faster to use and it is said that the film flatness is better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;polaroid-film&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Polaroid film&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Polaroid film is a great learning tool because you get instant feedback. Some people recommend that when you start 4x5 you expose Polaroids to begin. Another special application is proofing, to check composition, exposure (esp. with flash), and focus (by luping the negative). But Polaroid material has its own photographic merits, and can yield beautiful prints and negatives. It has been used as a medium by some masters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To use Polaroid film, all you need is a 4x5 camera, and a Polaroid holder. The sheet film holders are model 545 (older, metal construction) or 545i (current, plastic construction, lighter). They are reasonnably sized so they can also be used with Quickload (and maybe Readyloads, although the failure rate is catastrophic). There are two other Polaroid holders, for pack film, the 550 which accepts 4x5&amp;rdquo; pack film and the 405 which uses 3 1/4x 4 &lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;&amp;rdquo; pack film. Packs film are cheaper, but the film area is smaller than 4x5, so that makes them useful mostly for checking exposure. Personally I would just go for the 4x5 image given by the 545 (which is already a bit smaller than 4x5)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Polaroid also makes material for 8x10 cameras, but it is quite pricey and you also need a special processor, unlike in 4x5 where the holder serves as the processor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;roll-film&#34;&gt;For more information, call Polaroid to get a free guide to their film. I have personally found type 52 (gives a beautiful print), type 54 (gives a print not as beautiful, but which does not require coating), and type 55 (gives a print AND a negative), and type 56 (gives a beautiful sepia print) useful. Unfortunately with type 55, the negative is about 1.5 stops slower than the print, so you cannot get both well-exposed. The negative needs also a good cleaning to remain usable.&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;polaroid55.html&#34;&gt;More details on 55&lt;/a&gt;. All these materials are B&amp;amp;W. I don&amp;rsquo;t have too much experience with the color materials, but I heard they are quite sensitive to heat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-tripod&#34;&gt;The tripod&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-to-look-for-in-a-tripod&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;What to look for in a tripod ?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;portability&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;stability/rigidity&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;working height&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ease of use&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first and second points are contradicting, and therefore you have to compromise. A reasonnable choice would be something like a Gitzo series 300 or equivalent. A Gitzo series 400 would hold any view camera. A series 200 would be considered by many to be marginal, but I find it quite usable (see below). Quite a few people use wooden tripods. While it is said that they damp vibrations better than metal tripod, I find that their only real advantage is ruggedness (due actually to a simpler construction, rather than material), and warmer feel. On the other hand, with respect to the four previous points, for a given weight, the metal tripod is always better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;do-i-have-to-get-a-monster-tripod-for-this-large-format-camera&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Do I have to get a monster tripod for this large format camera ?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You don&amp;rsquo;t necessarily need a tripod bigger than the one you use for your small camera. I used to have a very heavy tripod (Zone VI, 16 lbs, ouch !) that i used next to the car, and a Gitzo 226 for hiking and traveling. Since then, i have sold my Zone VI, and use exclusively the Gitzo 1228 with a Linhof Profi II ball head. The combination weights 4lbs, and is quite usable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reasons why I think that a light tripod such that the 1228 is plenty adequate for my LF use are the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The real issue is the rigidity of the legs, NOT the weight of the tripod. With this respect, the Gitzos are pretty good. For the weight, I carry plenty enough. I have put a ring at the bottom of the center column, and attach by camera bag to it. The combo has a heavy weight that cannot be beat !&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Some medium format or even 35mm settups are in fact heavier than my LF, but I see NO reason why a heavier camera would require a heavier tripod (as long as it does not collapse, of course). Since regardless of the format, blur due to camera shake is mostly a function of focal length, I would tend to say that very stable tripods are needed mostly for very long lenses. Thus if the 1228 is sufficient to hold a 300mm lens for a 35mm camera (and it is), then it is also sufficient to hold a 300m for a 4x5 in still conditions. Most of my LF photography is done with 120 and 210 mm lenses.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;tripod-head-with-qr-system&#34;&gt;Tripod head with QR system&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A pan-tilt head is more convenient, because it is more easy to level the camera, and you can tilt the camera front to back without unwanted sideway tilt. If your camera does not have levels, it would be useful to have them on your head. A quick release system is very nice to have. Unfortunately the smallest PT head made by Manfrotto which meets all these requirements is the 3047, and although it is nice to use, it weights almost as much as my Gitzo 1228. I also have a smaller PT head, the 3029, but it does not have a built-in QR system, and i find it becomes quite bulky if I attach one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mostly because of the weight and bulk savings, many photographers use ball heads. An other benefit is that they work better for 35mm and MF if you use a second format. The Linhof Profi II is good enough for most lightweight LF cameras, however, the heavier and more expensive Arca-Swiss B1 is more rigid, smoother, and has an elliptic ball to prevent flip-over.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A Quick Release (QR) system is not absolutely necessary, but very nice to have, especially if you switch between different formats. You can buy a Manfrotto/Bogen adaptator to use the Bogen hex plates with several ball heads by replacing the stock platform. The spring-loaded Bogen QR system is inexpensive, quick and easy to operate, lock positively and well thanks to the hexagonal shape. If tightened enough, the plates won&amp;rsquo;t slip. However, if you are using at the same time smaller cameras, you might prefer the Arca Swiss system, where you slip the camera plate into a dovetail. With that system, camera plates can be custom made for each camera, which ensures a better fit, while the Bogen plates tend to stick out from small camera bodies. Don&amp;rsquo;t get the generic plates from Arca-Swiss. That would negate most of the advantages of the system ! Really Right Stuff is generally thought to make better fitting plates than Kirk Enterprises.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;accessories&#34;&gt;Accessories&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;darkcloth&#34;&gt;Darkcloth&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can use a jacket, but a dark cloth is preferable and does not cost much anyway compared to the price of the rest of the equipment. A cloth with a white exterior is nice on hot days or if photographing on a busy site. Personnally I don&amp;rsquo;t like those which have weight (ie Zone VI) because if it gets really windy they can fly around and break the ground glass, plus they tend to add weight. A Velcro on the side which is used arround the camera is nice to maintain it in place. For good viewing of the image with slow lenses, I have found that a second velcro is called. One part of the velcro is on the left side of the cloth, the other one on the right side, so that you can close totally the cloth (light coming from under the cloth is otherwise quite distracting). Darkroom Innovations have taken this idea seriously and makes a darkcloth with an elasticized collar that fits around the camera and a velcro-closed slit that you can close totally for excellent darkness. The choice of material makes it light and windproof. It&amp;rsquo;s better than any other darkcloth that I have seen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;focussing-aid&#34;&gt;Focussing aid&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Except maybe in 8x10, don&amp;rsquo;t trust the naked eye to focus critically. A lupe with a medium magnification, not too big, not too expensive, is the best here. This eliminates the lupes which are usually used for viewing slides on light tables. Unlike in that situation, to focus the view camera you don&amp;rsquo;t need a high quality lupe. On the other hand, there are a few practical requirements: its skirt does not prevent from viewing the corners, it is focussable so that you can make sure it is focussed on the ground glass, and it has attachement for a string so that you can dangle it around your neck. I like the Calumet lupe (7x) for its small size and good magnification. It works well with my very fine-grained Boss Screen but when I had the coarser Canham stock screen, I found it easier to focus with the Toyo (4x). Some people like cheap +4 dioptre glasses. Ron Wisner uses (and sells) a linen tester (an inexpensive folding magnifier that you put in your pocket, and which can be angled for good corner viewing). &amp;ldquo;Hastings Triplets&amp;rdquo; used by geologists are similar, but more powerful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;cable-release&#34;&gt;Cable release&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to avoid loosing them or spending time to screw/unscrew them, I have a cable release permanently attached to each of my lenses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;meter&#34;&gt;Meter&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Pentax digital spot meter seems to be popular with large format photographers. It is relatively small and light, reliable, and has easy controls and viewfinder readings. Recently the multi-purpose Sekonic Zoom-master has been succesfull, because it combines incident and flash with spot. However it is more complex and does not have viewfinder displays.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Personnally I use my 35mm camera. I like to have the small camera to be able to shoot quickly should something change suddently and produce many images for stock. I also use it as a viewfinder so I don&amp;rsquo;t have to move the tripod around. When I am in a hurry, I use the matrix metering, otherwise I use the a built-in spot meter with the &lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; stop analog scale in the viewfinder. I just set the same shutter speed and f-stop I intend to use on the LF camera, and then see where different part of the scene fall. Cameras with such a scale include the Nikon N8008s, F4, F5, F100 (N90 has only a f1 stop scale), and most canons, including the Rebel 2000 and the EOS 3. If I use the polarizer on the LF camera, I just put a polariser on my 35mm lens. The 24-120 or 24-85 lenses matches all the 4 focals that I commonly use on the LF camera.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;better-focussing-screen&#34;&gt;Better focussing screen&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can replace the focussing screen which comes with your camera, or supplement it with a fresnel lens to obtain a brighter and/or sharper image. After several screens, I have found the Boss screen to be by far the best.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>http://lflf.surge.sh</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lflf.surge.sh</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Large Format Photography: On the 11x14 format&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;on-the-11x14-format&#34;&gt;On the 11x14 format&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Compiled by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.terragalleria.com/&#34;&gt;Q.-Tuan Luong&lt;/a&gt; for &lt;a href=&#34;.&#34;&gt;the
Large Format Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;Wisner, Phillips and maybe Canham make 11x14 cameras.  A number of older
11x14&#39;s were available and can be found used (Kodak, Deardorff and others).
 (John Sparks)


Since you are not enlarging the film, just about any lens you can find
that will cover 11x14 is sharp enough.  I have a lens I bought for $75
(without a shutter) that will cover it and have two others that I
bought for 8x10 that would work as well (though not exactly cheap).
 There are several new lenses from each manufacturer that will cover
the format and many older ones including quite a few in the 12&amp;quot;-14&amp;quot;
range that often sell for less than $200.  One that is convertable
might be all you really need (the single cells of a 12&amp;quot; lens are
probably in the 18&amp;quot;-28&amp;quot; range).  Long lenses for 11x14 are pretty rare
and rather expensive (24&amp;quot; Artars are about the longest commonly found
which is about like a 210mm on 4x5 and they go for about $1200 these
days).  Besides the 800mm Apo- Tele-Xenar, there are some Zeiss
Apo-Germinars in 450mm, 600mm, 750mm and 1000mm that would cover
11x14.  The 750mm is about $3000 or less than half the price of the
Schneider :-).  Even the 600mm is supposed to cover 20x24.
 (John Sparks)


Which b&amp;amp;w-films for 11x14&amp;quot;?

1.Kodak Ektapan
2.Kodak T-Max
3.Ilford HP5
4.Ilford FP4
(Burkhardt Kiegeland)

The fidelity holders are quite good and there are at least 4 other
producers that I know of (Wisner, Hoffman,Brubaker,Great Basin)
(Richard Kuzniak)

Actually you need to know a bit about the holders and the camera. Not all
holders (old and new) are designed to fit all cameras -- 11x14 and above, we
are talking about both physical size (x,y dimensions) but more importantly--
the distance from the front surface of the holder to the film plane is
critical and VARIES WITH EACH MAKE OF HOLDER. (This isn&#39;t the mass production
and standardized world of 4x5-5x7 and 8x10). Just because that new film
holder fits in your camera does not ensure the dimensions are correct...
Have the holder and the camera measured to assure that the holder puts the
film at the same location as the ground glass surface for focusing.
Fidelity 11x14 follows the ANSI standard....  (but does your F&amp;amp;S or Corona or
whatever camera. expecially if it is really old??).
Alan Brubaker (AWB enterprises) makes outstanding holders for 11x14 and
up. I know you won&#39;t be disappointed. Great Basin also makes holders, but IMHO
not at the same quality level. We&#39;ll leave the Wisner holder discussion to
those that have already converted their Wisner 4x10 cameras to Keith Canham&#39;s
4x10 Fidelity holders....
(Don Nelson)

Nikkor 360 W, Schneider 355 G Claron,19&amp;quot; Red
Dots and  alot of Dagors cover the format beautifully and are
available used at a decent price.
(Richard Kuzniak)

Lenses:  They&#39;re out there.  I missed a fabulous opportunity to pick up
a 14&amp;quot; tessar-formula Wollensack for _$100_ at a swap I didn&#39;t think I
needed to go to.  This would&#39;ve come close to covering.  Also, I passed
on an 18&amp;quot; HugoMeyers WITH Packard shutter for $250 this past fall.
(Chris Perez)

&amp;gt;Theres a guy in Florida name of Clyde Butcher who shoots (I believe
&amp;gt;20x24).  He made a camera from an old process camera.  He shoots
&amp;gt;exclusively huge format i.e. &amp;gt;8x10 and makes all his own equipment.  I
&amp;gt;have wanted to take a workshop with him but have not yet done so.

Mailing address:
        Big Cypress Gallery
        52388 Tamiami Trail (Rte. 41)
        Ochopee, FL 33943.

You can buy his books from:
        Shade Tree Press,
        5647 Shaddelee Lane, West
        Fort Myers FL 33919 Phone 813-433-0222
(Robert Hudyman)



----------------------------------------------------------------------------
kuzniak@inforamp.net (Richard Kuzniak)

                  I worked with a 12x20 for a year and sold it because
I was frustrated by the limitations of a 60 year old banquet camera
(mostly bellows draw,also problems with film holders etc.) I did
learn a lot though and agree that the big negs are addictive...
I am hoping to win a lottery and buy a NEW camera either
a Wisner or Canham (his ideas for 16x20 are different from Wisner&#39;s
and intriguing...) I would like nothing better than a 20x24 but first
I want to research how to assure absolute film registration and
also film flatness (this is not adequately dealt with except maybe
by the Phillips 12x20 which uses a magnetic strip around the
perimeter of the film  to hold it down-I rented this camera and that
system worked fine) . As far as I know Wisner&#39;s 20x24 does not
have any special provision to ensure film flatness.I think that
one would almost have to have a Phillips type system or a vacuum
holder.A big piece of film like that is bound to sag just from its own
weight...
Also I would like to acquire good lenses that would cover that format
(probably 19,24&amp;quot; Dagors)Gary Adams worked with that format but
had focus problems.Doug Busch has worked with formats up to 40x50
(I would love to see some of THOSE prints!)  and could probably advise
on the film problem.With the disappearance of XX and possibly Azo I
think that maybe we fanatics should organize and get a few runs of
these materials to last us till we (gulp) die...but first I&#39;ve got to
win  that damn lottery, come up with foolproof film
flatness/registration and then 20x24 here I come!!


sanking@hubcap.clemson.edu (s carl king)


I guess you must first decide whether you want to spend $5k plus on
a new model (Wisner, and others) or about $2k on one of the older
banquet cameras, of which there were four I believe (Burke James,
Deardorff, Folmer &amp;amp; Schwing, and Gundlach Korona. There is an
interesting article on the banquet cameras in the November/December
issue of View Camera (1990). This issue also has some
good information about lenses for these cameras. If you can
not locate the article send me a dollar bill and I will be happy to
make you a copy and send it to you.
For your information, I have a Gundlach Korona 12X20 and am very pleased
with it, though I think the Former and Schwing is a tad better.

&amp;gt;I&#39;d love to move to 11x14 (eventually) but I work exclusively in
&amp;gt;the field. Are these things pratical to lug around on the trail ?
&amp;gt;I&#39;m a backpacker/hiker but try to limit my loads to about 30 to
&amp;gt;35 pounds. It seems to me that an old wooden 11x14 and a good
&amp;gt;tripod that could support the camera would exceed 30 pounds.

An 11x14 Deardorff weighs about 28 lbs.  I&#39;d guess a Kodak or B&amp;amp;J 11x14
would be a bit lighter, but probably still around 24 lbs.  Phillips
makes new 11x14 cameras that are the lightest available but still 17.5
lbs (ignoring their horizontal only version that probably weighs 12-15
lbs).  Holders weigh about 2 or 3 lbs, most lenses in shutter that cover
11x14 probably weigh at least 1.5-2 lbs (a #3 Copal or #4 Ilex shutter
weighs 1 lb without a lens and most 11x14 lenses will be in a shutter at
least this big).  A tripod that can hold a camera this large and heavy
weighs at least 10-12 lbs with a head but sturdy tripods this light are
not cheap.  So starting with a 24 lbs camera, you are at about 38 lbs
minimum with only one holder and one lens and that doesn&#39;t count
darkcloth, light meter, filters, etc.  You could make 35lbs with a
Phillips, one lens, tripod, one or two holders, lightweight darkcloth
though this still doesn&#39;t count the backpack (5 lbs?).


&amp;gt;I don&#39;t have the money for a new technical field
&amp;gt;(if Wisner makes one).

Wisner&#39;s literature says their 11x14 weighs 30 lbs!  This is their old
brass construction so there is a possibility of an aluminum design at
about 22-25 lbs.  Canham also makes an 11x14 that&#39;s probably between the
weight of the Phillips and the Wisner a maybe 20-22 lbs.  I think the Phillips
was about $2500 in 1993, the others are probabably twice as much.

(John Sparks)

The best choice would be a new (or used) 11x14 Phillips view - compact
and very light weight. If you could find a used older 11x14 Improved
Empire State view, this would a good alternative for probably a lot less
money. It&#39;s not as stable, not as many movements, BUT extremely compact
and lightweight. They&#39;re getting hard to find though. As for
backpacking, the biggest hurdle might be the filmholders - they just
might take up more space than the camera itself.

(Gregory A Kriss)

KBCanham&#39;s 11x14, of which 4 are under construction as we speak, is specified
to be 16.5 lbs with 48&amp;quot; bellows (max).

(DON NELSON)

        If you can find an older 11x14 they weigh in at 10 to 15
        lbs. My Rochester Universal weighs 14.5 lbs and it has a
        laminated bed.
        Street photographers tripods were made of thin aluminum
        and were fairly sturdy with large columns and big
        platform clam heads. Mine weighs in at 9 1/2 lbs.
        I do B&amp;amp;W landscapes so I get along with barrel lenses
        Protar Series 4 WA , 14&amp;quot; Dagor and one lens board with
        a adjustable len flange holder. The three weigh in at
        3 lbs...................

(William Franko)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;view-or-add-comments-http-www-greenspun-com-com-qtluong-photography-lf-11x14-html&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.greenspun.com/com/qtluong/photography/lf/11x14.html&#34;&gt;View or add comments&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>http://lflf.surge.sh</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lflf.surge.sh</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h2 id=&#34;scanning-black-and-white-negative-film-with-the-microtek-artixscan-1800f&#34;&gt;Scanning black and white negative film with the Microtek Artixscan 1800F&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.srosenberg.com/&#34;&gt;Scott Rosenberg&lt;/a&gt; © 2005 for
&lt;a href=&#34;http://lflf.surge.sh/&#34;&gt;largeformatphotography.info&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Introduction:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;T&lt;/strong&gt;he digital workflow is pretty much ubiquitous in the world of fine
art color photography these days. The technology has gotten so good that
we are now able to produce prints with a vibrancy and clarity never
before possible. Modern scanning and printing technologies have gotten
so good, in fact, that for the first time since slide film has been
available, prints are actually starting to rival transparencies. While
reflected media will never look exactly like transmitted media, the
digital workflow of today is enabling photographers to produce prints
closer to their originals than ever before.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
After seeing what was possible with the new digital darkroom, I quickly
embraced the workflow for my color printing. Initially, however, I was
less enthusiastic about making black and white prints using these same
technologies. To my eye, I still preferred prints made in a traditional
darkroom. However, after recently seeing black and white prints from the
latest in digital printing, I feel like that gap has been bridged
considerably, and set out to determine how best to scan black and white
negatives using my Microtek Artixscan 1800F.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
To gather a list of best practices, I spoke to several photographers
whose work I admire and who are printing black and white images from
digital files made from film. While most are using the same scanner as
I, their individual methodologies shared little else. I therefore
decided to start from square one, consider every possibility I could
think of, and let the results speak for themselves. It should be noted
that there will always be sources of variation that can not be
controlled, and my findings are specific to the equipment, myself
included, in my personal workflow. In other words, your mileage may
vary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Experimental Design:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;H&lt;/strong&gt;aving not much else to go on, I decided to scan a sheet of black
and white film every way my scanner was capable of:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
                     1. As a Black and White Negative&lt;br /&gt;
                     2. As a Black and White Positive&lt;br /&gt;
                     3. As a Color Negative&lt;br /&gt;
                     4. As a Color Positive&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Since I set out to determine the scanning workflow that will lead to the
finest print, and not the amount of input required post scanning, I
worked with each file until I got that individual image to look just as
I would want it to before having it printed, taking care to get all the
files as closely matched as possible. Positive scans would have to be
inverted; color scans would have each of their three channels (Red,
Green, Blue) evaluated to determine which one yielded superior results.
I worked on each file as I would any other in preparation for printing,
and while no prints were made, these master files were then scrutinized
and a best practice was decided upon.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Since I was primarily interested in assessing my scanners capability
regarding tone and resolution of fine detail, I selected the image shown
below, as it contains a full range of tonal values, from the deep
shadows found under the porch to the bright whites of the dogwood
blooms, as well as some very fine elements in the detail of the
rough-cut timbers and the bark of the trees.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.srosenberg.com/Website7/images/dagorbarn1800f.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Farmhouse and Dogwood&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A Comparison of the Color Channels:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;T&lt;/strong&gt;he first thing I wanted to check was if there was a difference in
the red, green, and blue channels in the color scans. Since the final
print would be black and white, I could use any one of these three
channels independently of the other two, or use all three simply by
converting the RGB image to greyscale. Shown below are detail scans
illustrating each channel, as well as the RGB image once converted to
greyscale.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.srosenberg.com/Website7/images/ChannelsQT.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Red, Blue, Green, and RGB Channel Comparison&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The green channel, while a little grainier, clearly has retained the
most detail. Remember, these scans represent a very small area of the
overall image, and as such, the increased grain apparent in the green
channel is not really a concern, as it will be completely undetectable
in the final print.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Now that the sharpest channel of the color scans has been determined, we
can take a look at how the black and white scans compare to the green
channel of the color scans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Detail Scans and Conclusions:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;H&lt;/strong&gt;aving determined that the green channel from the color scans was in
fact the sharpest, I now set out to compare it to the black and white
scans. Shown below are detail scans illustrating how the black and white
scans compared to the green channel alone of the color scans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.srosenberg.com/Website7/images/dagorbarnbarkQT.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Detail Scans Comparing All Four Master Files&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These scans are slices from the tree to the right of the farmhouse. The
slices from the color scans clearly show more texture and detail than
those scanned as black and white. It is difficult to tell at this size,
but when enlarged further, the color positive scan shows the most
detail.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These scans are slices from knotty boards just above the window on the
farmhouse. Again, the slices from the color scans are sharper and
exhibit more detail than the black and white scans, with the color
positive scan showing the most detail when enlarged yet further than
what is shown here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.srosenberg.com/Website7/images/dagorbarnwoodQT.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Detail Scans Comparing All Four Master Files&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As can be seen in the detail images above, there was little difference
observed in the tonal range of the scans. There was, however, an
appreciable difference in the amount of detail captured, the master file
containing the most detail comes from the green channel when the film
was scanned as a color positive. This surprised me, as these are the
settings farthest from what was actually scanned - a black and white
negative. It was my initial belief that scanning the film as a black and
white negative would yield the best scans. So surprised was I by these
findings that I duplicated this experiment with an entirely different
black and white negative, this second experiment returning precisely the
same results.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
For my particular workflow, that is to say my scanner with me at the
wheel, the best scans of black and white negative film are obtained by
scanning the film as a color positive, inverting the file, and then
using only the green channel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;view-add-comments-http-largeformatphotography-info-lfforum-topic-504762-html&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://largeformatphotography.info/lfforum/topic/504762.html&#34;&gt;View/Add comments&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>http://lflf.surge.sh</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lflf.surge.sh</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Large format photography: about the 4x10 and film holders&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;about-the-4x10-format-and-film-holders&#34;&gt;About the 4x10 format and film holders&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;By &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.thalmann.com/&#34;&gt;Kerry Thalmann&lt;/a&gt; for
&lt;a href=&#34;http://lflf.surge.sh/&#34;&gt;largeformatphotography.info&lt;/a&gt; (compiled by QTL)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-4x10-format&#34;&gt;The 4x10 format&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I shoot 4x10 and love the format. I shoot color transparency film in two
different fashions. The first is &amp;ldquo;true 4x10&amp;rdquo; - meaning I cut the film in
half in the dark prior to exposure, load it into 4x10 holders and shoot
it with a 4x10 camera. The second is to shoot two 4x10 images on a
single sheet of 8x10 film using conventional 8x10 holders, a split
darkslide, and an older 8x10 camera (Eastman Commercial All-Metal).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like the aspect ratio of the format, and I also like the fact that
many lenses I already had covered the format. It&amp;rsquo;s possible to assemble
a very wide range of lenses that cover this format, and still avoid the
heavy, bulky #3 shutter necessary for many 8x10 lenses (much like 5x7
in this regard). Like I said above, there are many very good, reasonably
compact lenses, both new and old, that barely or don&amp;rsquo;t quite cover 8x10.
These make wonderful choices for use on the 4x10 format.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For prints, I &amp;ldquo;enlarge&amp;rdquo; to either 8x20 or 12x30 digitally using a
flatbed scanner and an Epson 2200 printer. One nice thing about the 4x10
format is that you can get rather large prints using a relatively
affordable desktop inkjet printer. On the other hand, I&amp;rsquo;ve seen a number
of 4x10 contact prints from other photographers. With the right subject
and materials, the results can be exquisite. A print doesn&amp;rsquo;t always have
to be huge to hold one&amp;rsquo;s attention.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Drawbacks: with light leaks (see next section), a lack of a market for
my stock images (6x17 is BY FAR the preferred format for panoramic stock
sales), a lack of supporting products (4x10 transparency sleeves,
Quickmounts, etc.), at one point I gave up on the format in favor of
6x17.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;*4x10 &amp;ldquo;sees&amp;rdquo; the same way that 8x10 does. David Fokos. That is to say,
if you use a 210mm. lens for 8x10 (I use a Rodenstock Sironar-S, which
just barely covers), your 4x10 shots will have the same wide-angle
perspective. A 90mm lens would be *incredibly* wide-angle on the 4x10,
roughly the equivalent of a 45mm lens on a 4x5. &lt;strong&gt;David Fokos&lt;/strong&gt;*&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;David makes a very good point. I bought the 115mm Grandagon specifically
for 4x10 (even before I bought the camera). This decision was made based
on the mentality prevelant on many panaorama cameras: stick the widest
lens on the camera that will cover the film format and call it a
panorama. Once I actually started using the camera, I found that in most
situations, the 115mm on 4x10 was just too wide for my tastes. Although
in some situations, it was the only lens that would work (when you need
it, you NEED it). A 115mm or 120mm would probably be a good 4x10 focal
length for architectural interiors or large group photos in the banquet
tradition, but I found that I didn&amp;rsquo;t use it as much as I thought I would
for 4x10 landscapes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On a related note, compositionally, 4x10 (or any panoramic format) is
much different than the traditional 4x5 or 8x10 formats. In 4x5, I like
to use wide angle lenses (75mm or 90mm) to emphasize the foreground to
draw the viewer into the photograph. This is especially effective in
vertical compositions. In 4x10, the main compositional elements tend to
lie in middle third vertically acrossed the entire 10&amp;rdquo; width of the
film. In my experience, strong leading foregrounds just don&amp;rsquo;t work well
in a panoramic format. Therefore, I found myself using the ultrawide
focal lengths less that I do in 4x5, and found myself using the less
radical wide angles (165mm and 210mm) along with the more normal 300mm
focal length. The 450mm focal length was especially interesting. I use
my 210mm lens a lot on 4x5 (probably my most used focal length in that
format along with the 135mm). The 450 gave similar horizontal coverage
in the panoramic format. It provided some interesting compositions in
4x10, but I didn&amp;rsquo;t rely on it as much as I do the 210mm in 4x5. It is
interesting to note that if I was limited to one focal length in the
4x10 format I would choose the 210mm, the same focal length I would
choose for 4x5. Although the 210mm Nikkor W I had for 4x5 was adaquate
for 4x10, I would recommend something with a larger image circle (210mm
Super Symmar HM, 210mm Sironar W if you can afford it, 210mm Fujinon W,
210mm Angulon or 210mm f9 Computar or even 190mm Wide Field Ektar if you
are on a more modest budget) if you plan to shoot a lot of 4x10.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;4x10 is a wonderful, neglected format. Unfortunately, there are two
competing standards for the film holders and that adds to the confusion
(can you imagine what it would be like if different brands of 4x5 or
8x10 cameras required custom made holders of differing dimensions).
There aren&amp;rsquo;t a lot of us out there shooting in this beautiful size - so
you can consider yourself part of an exclusive, elite group of
photographers determined to do something just a little bit different
than most.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;4x10-vs-split-8x10-vs-4x5-stitched&#34;&gt;4x10 vs split 8x10 vs 4x5 stitched&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;8x10 holders and a lot easier to find and cheaper than 4x10 holders.
There are plenty of used 8x10 holders available on eBay at reasonable
prices. To me, that&amp;rsquo;s the key to shooting 4x10 is getting holders. The
Canham 4x10 holders are well made and the most reasonably priced new
holders (about \$95 each). For comparison, new 8x10 Fidelity holders are
about \$60 each - and you only need half as many for the same number of
shots. Of course, if you can get an ultralight 8x10, like the Phillips
Explorer, you can have the best of both worlds - a lightweight camera
and affordable holders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Split darkslides are sold by
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.benderphoto.com/4x10pa.htm&#34;&gt;Bender&lt;/a&gt; and
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.toho-machine.co.jp/Panorama.htm&#34;&gt;Toho&lt;/a&gt;, but &lt;a href=&#34;http://largeformatphotography.info/lfforum/topic/497643.html&#34;&gt;it is easy to
make it
yourself&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The procedure would be more lengthy but not more complicated than
normal:&lt;br /&gt;
For image 1:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;frame the scene using the top 4x10 half of the 8x10 ground glass
(assuming horizontal panorama),&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Put in 8x10 film holder.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pull dark slide and replace with special half fram dark slide with
the openning at the top.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make exposure.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Replace normal dark slide.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For image 2:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;frame the scene using the bottom half of the 8x10 ground glass&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Put in the same 8x10 film holder with the same side to the lens.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pull dark slide and replace with special half fram dark slide with
the openning at the bottom.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make exposure.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Replace normal dark slide.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This way you get two 4x10 exposures on each 8x10 sheet of film (both
will likely be processed the same, though you could cut the film after
exposure and before processing). A single holder gives you 4 exposures.
All equipment is standard except for the extra homemade cut darkslide.
&lt;strong&gt;Sandor&lt;/strong&gt;. Todd Caudle (spliting 4x5 into 2x5), recommends &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.photo.net/bboard/q-and-a-fetch-msg?msg_id=003xgh&#34;&gt;rotating
the back&lt;/a&gt;
instead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Deardorff also made 4x10 slider boards for their 8x10 camera backs. In
fact, that&amp;rsquo;s how I got started shooting 4x10. When I sold my Deardorff,
I kept the 4x10 slider board. I still have it. It also fits some 8x10
Kodak backs. It&amp;rsquo;s a very simple piece of wood, painted black with a
simple rabbet joint on each end, and two recessed &amp;ldquo;thumb holes&amp;rdquo; (not
really holes, as they don&amp;rsquo;t go all the way through the board) for
sliding it back and forth. If you have a Deardorff camera and are even
slightly handy, you could make one yourself. If I remember correctly,
the grooves for the 4x10 slider are offset from the grooves for the 5x8
slider. This would allow using one of each to shoot four 4x5 images
(minus margins) on a single sheet of 8x10 film. Kind of a poor man&amp;rsquo;s
reducing back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found two minor, but irritating problem with this method. First, 8x10
cameras ARE bigger, bulkier and heavier. Granted the Deardorff at about
13 - 14 lbs. isn&amp;rsquo;t exacty a lightweight 8x10, but still, given
comparable designs, a 4x10 camera will save you a few pounds and a fair
amount of bulk. The dedicated 4x10 I had was a Wisner Technical. The
basic chassis was the same as a 4x5 Technical (actually, I bought the
camera as a 4x5 Technical and bought the 4x10 back/bellows as an
accessory). Again, the Wisner Technical isn&amp;rsquo;t exactly a lightweight 4x5
by current standards, but in the 4x10 configuration weighed about 7 lbs.
I believe Wisner now has 4x10 converstion kits for his lighter weight
models (Expedition and/or Pocket expedition). These models, in 4x10
configuration should be a couple pounds lighter than a 4x10 Technical
(the Technical is Wisner&amp;rsquo;s heaviest 4x5). By building around a 4x5 base,
and having a back that&amp;rsquo;s &lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; the size, a 4x10 camera can be
significantly smaller and lighter than an 8x10. Not important for
everyone, but an issue for those who hike (I ONCE did a 23 mile day hike
with my 4x10 Wisner, big heavy tripod, holders, lenses, etc. It was hard
enough with the 4x10, I wouldn&amp;rsquo;t wanted to attempt it with an 8x10).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second issue I had was that it was necessary to shift the lens up
and down to center the image on the &lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; of the 8x10 film I was using.
This then limits the amount of effective front rise you have left. If
you have lenses with huge coverage, you can probably just shoot both
halves with the lens in its normal neutral position. Or, if you have a
camera with gobs of front rise, this isn&amp;rsquo;t an issue. I was using lenses
that didn&amp;rsquo;t quite, or just barely, covered 8x10 (115mm Granadgon-N,
165mm Angulon, 210mm Nikkor W, 300mm Nikkor M), so it was always
important that I recentered the lens for each shot to avoid vignetting.
Not a show stopper, just a little convenient.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In spite of these issues, for me, the dedicated 4x10 solution was even
more of a hassle. At the time, the only 4x10 film holders I could get to
fit my Wisner were the Mido II type. These were small and light, but
were very prone to light leaks (some operator induced, most due to
manufacturing defects in the holders). I sent my holders back twice to
have them repaired/replaced. Each time the problem got better, but was
still unacceptable. Cutting my own film was a hassle I was prepared to
live with, but cutting my own film and then having &lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; the exposures
ruined by light leaks, was not. Of course, now there are better 4x10
holders on the market, so this is probably a non-issue for anyone
entering this format these days. BTW, the 4x10 Wisner was a fine camera,
it was just the hodlers I disliked. The Canham 4x10 holders were MUCH
better, but bulkier and heavier. The current wooden Wisner holders
should be much better than the old Mido IIs I was using.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, cutting the film WAS a hassle. Not impossible, not even
difficult, just tedious. And, it exposed the film to a much greater
likelyhood that dust would settle on it during the cutting, notching,
loading process. At the time I entered the 4x10 format, Ilford sold
pre-cut FP4 and HP5 film, but I was shooting color transparencies, so I
had to cut my own Velvia. When I bought my camera, I was hopeful that
4x10 was an emerging standard (Wisner had just entered the market as the
second major manufacturer to offer a 4x10 camera, Ilford was selling
precut 4x10 film&amp;hellip;). I hoped the format would catch on and Fuji, Kodak,
etc, would start offering precut 4x10 film. Well, history tells us I was
naively optimistic in this regard. I don&amp;rsquo;t believe Ilford still offers
precut film in the 4x10 size (or maybe they do, but it&amp;rsquo;s special order
only). If not, and you don&amp;rsquo;t want to cut your own, Photo Warehouse will
do it for you at prices that are quite reasonable (at least they are in
other oddball sizes like 6 &lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; x 8 &lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;*I&amp;rsquo;ve done stiched panoramas before, and they are fun. The main problem
is ensuring that the pivot point is centered on the nodal point of the
lens. Not too many view cameras have a mounting point below the lens. If
this isn&amp;rsquo;t done, close objects in the scene will not stich together
well. If the camera has rear shift, this would be a better option,
assuming the lens can cover the new virtual format. &lt;strong&gt;George Steward&lt;/strong&gt;*&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I contemplated getting back into 4x10, I seriously considered this
method. As I already had a 4x5 camera with rear shifts and a number of
lenses that cover 4x10. The initial investment would be relatively small
(the cost of the stitching SW, and either a new desktop scanner - which
I&amp;rsquo;ll probably get anyway - or the price of paying someone else to do the
scans). However, I happened to get a great deal on some slightly used
4x10 holders. I then assembled my own hybrid 4x10 camera from bits and
pieces I picked up from a number of sources. So, the method of using
rear shift and stitching got put on the back burner. George&amp;rsquo;s reply
jogged my memory and got me thinking (always dangerous) about this
again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although I have a 4x10 camera and holders, there are times when I want
to go lighter (backpacking). My 4x10 camera and lenses are reasonably
light, but the weight and bulk of the holders can add up quickly
compared to 4x5 Quickloads or Readyloads. For that reason, I have
considered using rear shift to shoot two 4x5 images and stitch them
together to produce something close to a 4x10 image (maybe 4x9 with the
overlap between the two frames). This would allow me to carry an
ultralight camera, like the Toho, leave the 4x10 holders at home and use
Quick/Readyloads. This would be the ideal set-up for backpacking. I
could also use this same method with my ARCA-SWISS if I&amp;rsquo;m out in the
field and don&amp;rsquo;t have any 4x10 holders with me (or run out of loaded
holders and don&amp;rsquo;t have time to reload).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You need to use lenses capable of covering 4x10, but I have a number of
reasonably lightweight lenses with ample coverage. One possible issue I
see is asymmetric light fall-off when using wide angle lenses. If this
does show up, I assume it can be evened out in SW. Anybody have any
experience they can share?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, since there should be little distortion using this method
(compared to rotating the camera), I would think the amount of overlap
between the two frames would be small. In general, I prefer working with
a camera in my intended format. I prefer composing the entire image on
the ground glass and exposing it on a single sheet of film. There are
certainly advantages to this method. However, for times when it&amp;rsquo;s
impractical or impossible, using rear shift and stitching two images
together seems to be a viable alternative. As my interest in 4x10 has
been rekindled, I&amp;rsquo;ll probably give it a try in the next couple months
and see how well it works. In the mean time, if anybody else has tried
it, please share what you&amp;rsquo;ve learned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;holder-standards&#34;&gt;Holder standards&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I highly recommend you consider the holders first. IMHO, in
non-mainstream formats, the availability of affordable (or at least
attainable) holders is of paramount importance. For me, while choosing a
camera may be more exciting, getting the holders is far more important.
I learned that the hard way the first time I tried 4x10. The second time
around, I bought the holders first, before I even started looking for a
camera. The most beautiful camera in the world is useless without
holders for your film.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;BTW, in 4x10, there are TWO different &amp;ldquo;standard&amp;rdquo; sizes for the holders.
The Wisner 4x10 cameras use holders based on the older 4x10 X-Ray
holders (made by Lisco, Fidelity and Kodak more than 30 years ago). It
can be REAL hard to find holders in this size. The most common are the
Mido II holders (that are not the best holders ever made) that were sold
for the Wisner cameras about 10 years ago. While the concept is good,
the quality of construction wasn&amp;rsquo;t the best and light leaks can be a big
problem (I speak from experience). The Mido holders were discontinued
several years ago after the death of their maker. Ron Wisner does have
4x10 wooden holders listed on his website, but I haven&amp;rsquo;t seen any in
person, nor have I talked to anybody who has. So, I can&amp;rsquo;t comment on the
quality or availability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All the other commercially available 4x10 cameras (Canham, Lotus and
Altview) use holders that are wider than the Wisner X-Ray style holders.
Holders in this size are readily available from Keith Canham (as
mentioned above ~\$95 each and very well made) and
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lotusviewcamera.at/accessories/sheetfilmholder_e.html&#34;&gt;Lotus&lt;/a&gt;
(wooden, beautiful, well-made and expensive), &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.filmholders.com&#34;&gt;AWB Alan
Brubaker&lt;/a&gt; (check out Alan&amp;rsquo;s web site for
some nice photos of his holders in various sizes) and S&amp;amp;S (Sandy King
and Sam Wang) will custom make wooden holders in a variety of formats.
Such custom made holders are justifiably expensive (the labor involved
in making 4x10 or 5x12 holders is the nearly the same as making 11x14 or
12x20 holders). I was fortunate to purchase several used Lotus 4x10
holders at a very reasonable price. If I was looking to buy new holders
today, I&amp;rsquo;d buy the Canham holders as they are readily available and
represent the best value.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;more-on-options-available-to-wisner-camera-owners&#34;&gt;More on options available to Wisner camera owners&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;4x10 Fidelity/Kodak/Lisco X-Ray Holders - Evidently these were popular
at one time in the ancient past for x-raying animal paws and infant
limbs. The medical/veterinary industry switched to a different style
x-ray cassette decades ago. I spent YEARS trying to track some of these
down, calling all my local vets, x-ray supply houses, manufacturers,
begging another photographer to sell me his, etc. Finally, someone at
Fidelity searched through some old catalogs and said they&amp;rsquo;d discontinued
their 4x10 x-ray holders over 30 years ago. In over 14 years of looking,
I&amp;rsquo;ve only seen three of these for sale (4x10 Lisco X-Ray Holders).
Unfortunately, this was the standard Ron Wisner chose to use when he
introduced his 4x10 camera. As you are aware, this makes the Wisner 4x10
cameras uniquely incompatible with the Canham style holders that
everybody else uses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;4x10 Mido II Holders and Clamshell - When I bought my 4x10 Wisner
Technical Field in early 1992, these were the holders Wisner was selling
with the camera. I bought the camera, five holders and a clamshell. The
holders leaked light like a sieve. I was losing more shots to light
leaks than not. I sent the holders back to Mido multiple times to be
reworked/repaired/replaced. Each time they came back, there were
incremental improvements in the failure rate - but it was still too high
to be acceptable. Mr. Mido seemed determined to make the holders work.
His concept was a good one, but quality and consistency of the
construction of the holders was lacking. In August 1996, I gave up and
sold my entire 4x10 outfit (4x5/4x10 Wisner Tech Field, Mido holders and
several lenses). The Mido II holders do occasionally show up on the used
market. They may have improved the quality after I sold mine, or with
some patience and skill, it may be possible to rework the holders and/or
clamshell to improve the success rate. Unfortunately, I learned a year
or two after selling my camera that Mr. Mido had become ill and
eventually passed away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oddly, B&amp;amp;H still lists 4x10 Mido holders and clamshells on their web
site. They are listed as a special order item. I wonder if that means
there are some new, old stock 4x10 Mido holders still in existence
somewhere, or if they have just neglected to update their web site in
the last six or seven years. They list the clamshell (focus spacer) with
one holder at \$159.95 and additional holders at \$79.95. I&amp;rsquo;ve been
curious what would happen if someone attempted to order some 4x10 Mido
holders from B&amp;amp;H (but not curious enough to try placing an order as I no
longer have the Wisner 4x10 camera).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;4x10 Lotus Holders (Wisner Form Factor or Canham form factor) - I sold
my 4x10 Wisner outfit to a gentleman from Austria named Burkhardt
Kiegeland. He immediately shared my frustration with the Mido II
holders. Mr Kiegeland had the resources and commitment to do something
about it. He had a craftsman make some 4x10 holders to fit the Wisner
camera and formed a new company, Lotus View Camera to manufacture and
sell these holders. Lotus immediately became a supplier of holders to
Wisner. In November, 1996 I saw one of these Lotus 4x10 holders at a
Wisner dealer in Sacramento. The quality appeared to be quite good. and
at \$95 the price was competitive. Lotus also began manufacturing 4x10
holders in the Canham form factor, as well as other banquet and ULF
sizes. Soon thereafter, Lotus also introduced their own line of cameras
from 4x5 - 20x24. I&amp;rsquo;m not sure when the official Lotus/Wisner holder
relationship dissolved, but if you can find some of the Lotus holders in
the Wisner size, they should serve you well. Lotus will still custom
make 4x10 holders in the Wisner form factor, but the price is
considerably more than the original \$95 retail price. The dollar is
much weaker now than it was in the late 1990s, and this would now be
considered a special custom made item, not something normally in stock.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wisner 4x10 Holders - I have not used any of the Wisner wooden holders,
but the ones I&amp;rsquo;ve seen did not look nearly as well made at the wooden
holders I&amp;rsquo;ve seen from S&amp;amp;S, Lotus or AWB (Alan Brubaker). Of course,
thay also cost a LOT less. The Wisner holders have the advantage of
being, by far, the least expensive of the wooden 4x10 holders. If Emile
can get them for you without delay at \$95 each, it may be worth a try.
As I haven&amp;rsquo;t used them, I can&amp;rsquo;t specifically recommend them one way or
the other. Perhaps somebody who has used Wisner holders could chime in
with their experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Custom Made Holders - As I mentioned above, Lotus will still custom make
4x10 holders in the Wisner form factor. As they were once an official
supplier to Wisner, you are assured the holders will fit your camera
properly. I haven&amp;rsquo;t used any 4x10 Lotus holders in the Wisner size, but
I am fortunate to have fifteen of their holders in the Canham form
factor and can attest that they are light tight, beautifully made, and
smooth to operate. Others have mentioned the S&amp;amp;S holders supplied by
Sandy King and Sam Wang. I have seen these holders in person, but not
used them. They appear to be of excellent quality, and other
photographers I know who&amp;rsquo;ve used them are very satisfied. The nice thing
about S&amp;amp;S is they seem very willing to make custom made holders in any
size you desire at a reasonble (for custom made holders) price. I have
also not used the AWB holders, but they also come highly recommended.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you do get custom made holders, I&amp;rsquo;d recommend getting them made in
the Canham form factor and getting your camera modified to match. The
Canham standard is the more common of the two. In addition to the Canham
4x10 camera, cameras in this format from Lotus and Patrick Alt also use
the Canham style holders. Holders in this size are more readily
available, both new and used. The cost of getting your Wisner camera
back modified will be, IMHO money well spent. The REAL key to shooting a
non-mainstream format, like 4x10, is the availability and cost of
holders. Getting your Wisner modified to accept Canham style holders
will increase your options.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;4x10 Canham Holders - This is probably the most practical option. Canham
holders are made from parts he gets from Fidelity. They look and feel
just like regular Fidelity holders. At \$95 each, they cost considerably
more than standard, off-the-shelf 8x10 Fidelity holders, but in the
oddball world that is 4x10, they are a relative bargain. I have never
heard of any problems with light leaks from anybody using 4x10 Canham
holders. If you&amp;rsquo;re looking for the lowest cost, least hassle option,
this would be the way to go. Some people may prefer the elegant look and
feel of fine wooden holders over the plastic and aluminum of the Canham
holders. I can&amp;rsquo;t say I blame them - like a fine wooden camera, fine
wooden holders are pleasing to the eye and to the touch. However, if
you&amp;rsquo;re just looking for holders that are reliable, attainable, durable
and affordable, it&amp;rsquo;s tough to beat the Canhams. I have no idea what it
would cost today, but 8 years ago before I sold my 4x10 Wisner, Keith
Canham quoted me a price of \$100 to modify my Wisner camera to accept
his holders. Even if the price has tripled in the last 8 years, I still
think it would be worth it in the long run.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m now on my second go around with 4x10. My first attempt ended in
frustration over the lack of quality holders to fit my camera. I got
tired of sending my holders back to Mido for &amp;ldquo;tune-up&amp;rdquo;, wating a few
weeks for them to come back and still losing a large percentage of my
best shots to light leaks. It just wasn&amp;rsquo;t worth it. In hindsight, I
should have taken Keith Canham up on his offer to modify my camera,
bought five or ten of his holders and gone happily about my business.
Rather than face the same frustration, this time around, I bought the
holders FIRST, before I even started looking for a 4x10 camera. I told
myself I didn&amp;rsquo;t care what camera they fit, I was going to snap up the
first quality 4x10 holders I found at a reasonable price, and then buy a
camera to match. This strategy worked much better. I was fortunate to
find fifteen 4x10 Lotus holders at an extremely agreeable price. I
snapped them up, and haven&amp;rsquo;t looked back. They happened to be the Canham
form factor - all the better. If I need additional holders to fit my
camera at some time in the future, I know I can get them from Canham at
a reasonable price.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I owned my 4x10 Wisner Tech Field, I never had a single complaint
about the quality or usability of the camera. It was actually a
beautiful camera that was a joy to use (except for the Mido holders). It
is also the most affordable of the full-featured 4x10 cameras - by a
fair margin. Don&amp;rsquo;t let the holder situation scare you off. Bite the
bullet and get some good holders (even if it means modifying the back of
your camera). You&amp;rsquo;ll be glad you did. Welcome to the 4x10 format.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;more-info-and-comments&#34;&gt;More info and comments&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This article was put together by QTL using Kerry Thalmann&amp;rsquo;s replies in
the following Q&amp;amp;A threads with minor editing:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://lflf.surge.sh/lfforum/topic/498501.html&#34;&gt;Fishing for long and skinny&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://lflf.surge.sh/lfforum/topic/189903.html&#34;&gt;4x10 format questions&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://lflf.surge.sh/lfforum/topic/498002.html&#34;&gt;Poor Man&amp;rsquo;s 4x10&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://lflf.surge.sh/lfforum/topic/498926.html&#34;&gt;Need 4x10 film holders for Wisner TF&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>http://lflf.surge.sh</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lflf.surge.sh</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-5x7-format-in-practice&#34;&gt;The 5x7 format in practice&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;By &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.terragalleria.com&#34;&gt;QT Luong&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; for
&lt;a href=&#34;%20/&#34;&gt;largeformatphotography.info&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once popular, the 5x7 format has fallen far behind in popularity behind
the 4x5 and 8x10 formats. This article looks at the advantages and
disadvantages of the 5x7 format, and gives a few practical pointers to
the resources available to the 5x7 photographer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-size-and-format-advantage-of-5x7&#34;&gt;The size and format advantage of 5x7&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Compared to 4x5, 5x7 is almost twice as large. The image on the ground
glass is nice and big to look at, but not so big that it becomes
difficult to see as a whole, like in 8x10.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The additional size makes it easier to make high quality large prints.
Since you need to enlarge two times less, imperfections in equipment or
technique are less likely to show up. Some photographers find that the
improvement in B&amp;amp;W quality is quite visible at 16x20 (a 4x enlargment
from 4x5). In color, if digital printing is used, based on an on-film
resolution of 40 lpm and a requirement of 5 lpm for critical sharpness
at normal viewing distance, one would begin to notice a difference
between 4x5 and 5x7 starting from 30x40, which is large, but not
uncommonly large. I have made prints at the largest Lightjet size
(50x70) with excellent results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, it is when you are not enlarging that the larger negative
counts the most. Contacts from 5x7 are large enough to view comfortably,
whereas contacts from 4x5 appear small. If you are a B&amp;amp;W photographer
using 5x7, all you need to create satisfying visual gems is a lightbulb
and a contact printing frame. A 5x7 transparency on a light box displays
a sharpness and a brillance which are far more impressive than a 4x5
transparency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other difference is in aspect ratio. 5x7 is more elongated than 4x5.
For that reason, I find it more satisfying for photographing large
landscapes. Others have reported that the format fits architecture and
the human figure well too. However, photographers more interested in
abstracts will probably like the more squarish aspect ratio of 4x5
better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like many photographers, I learned using 35mm, and since the aspect
ratio of 35mm and of 5x7 are practically the same, I felt immediatly
comfortable composing with a 5x7. When using both formats
simultaneously, there is no aspect ratio confusion. I find 5x7 to be the
perfect companion to a 35mm system. In addition, with the advant of
high-end digital cameras, the gap between 35mm (digital) and 4x5 (film)
is narrowing. Using 5x7, I still have two systems with widely different
capabilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-5x7-camera-versatility&#34;&gt;The 5x7 camera versatility&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you move to 8x10, you&amp;rsquo;ll almost certainly find yourself wanting a
ligher system to use on long hikes, backpacking trips, or travels. Then
you will have to maintain two systems, with the different lenses and
film holders, and think about which one to take on any given trip. On
the other hand, it is quite possible to do all your large format
photography with 5x7.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;5x7 gear is not much more heavier or bigger than 4x5 gear that it
becomes difficult to work with. The tripod and camera can still be moved
with one hand, and it is still possible to backpack. I have traveled in
Europe on public transportation with my 5x7. I have backpacked
extensively with it, including on a week-long trip into one of the world
ultimate wilderness areas, Gates of the Artic National Park in Alaska,
and a trip down to the river (and up !) from the North Rim of the Grand
Canyon. I have fit it inside a kayak for two weeks in Glacier Bay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With a reducing back, a 5x7 could be used as a nice 4x5 camera. It has a
longer extension, bigger bellows to reduce internal flare, and more
generous movements. Furthermore, a 5x7 can be used as a 6x17 (cm)
panoramic camera with an appropriate back. Such backs were rare (only
Art Pan made one, that you had to custom modify). However, recently
Keith Canham has presented a new model, with a battery operated advance
system. Weighting 2.2 lbs, and costing around \$1000, it will fit behind
the ground glass of many 5x7 that have 1 &lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; inches of clearance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the surface area is almost double, depending on the design, 5x7
gear is in general not twice as heavy as 4x5 gear. In some cases, the
difference in size and weight with 4x5 models is quite small, while 8x10
cameras are significantly heavier and bulkier. For instance, my own
Canham 5x7 weights less than popular 4x5 cameras such as the Zone VI,
Wisner Technical Field, Linhof Technika, and Arca-Swiss F-line.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One way to get started in the 5x7 camera is to use a 5x7 extension back
for 4x5. This was the route I initially took. However, these backs are
quite cumbersome, and have limitations, such as internal vigneting (you
are using bellows and a back opening made for 4x5) and the difficulty to
use very wide lenses, because of the additional depth of the back. Once
look at transparencies on the light table, it will be difficult to use
4x5 again, and you may be tempted to sell your 4x5 ! This is what
happened to me in 1995, after buying a 5x7 for my 4x5 in 1993. I&amp;rsquo;ve used
almost exclusively 5x7 since then, except for a couple of projects on
Polaroid film where I used the 4x5 reducing back on my 5x7.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;cameras-and-lenses&#34;&gt;Cameras and lenses&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The lightest 5x7 weights only 3 lbs and can be ordered from Peter
Gowland. Some fully featured 5x7 cameras (eg the Canhams, Lotus, Wisner
Pocket Expedition) are lighter than popular 4x5 cameras (eg Linhof,
Wisner Technical, Arca-Swiss). However, if you optimize 4x5 gear for
portability, you will usually get to &lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; of the weight of a 5x7 system
of comparable capacity. Over the past few years, manufacturers seem to
have realized that weight matters, and a flurry of lightweight camera
designs has emerged. While five years ago, you couldn&amp;rsquo;t find a fully
featured 4x5 field camera for less than 6lbs, now there are plenty in
the 4lbs-5lbs range, and the lightest ones are under 3lbs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 4x5 Canham DLC metal is 4 lbs. 11 oz. while the 5x7 Canham MQC is 5
lbs. 11 oz. On the other hand, the 5x7 versions of the Tachihara and the
Toho, two of the lightest 4x5 cameras, are both about twice the weight
of the 4x5 version.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While five years ago there was only a couple of field 5x7 made,
offerings have increased recently, with new flatbed cameras available
from Canham (classic woodfield T657 and metal MQC), Ebony
(SV57,SV57E,SV57UE,57SUE), Fine Art Photo Supply (Artworks, similar to
Tachi), Gandolfi(Traditional, Variant, All movements), Lotus (their most
popular camera: Rapid Field 5x7), Osaka, Shen-Hao (HZX57), Tachihara,
Walker (ABS 5x7 wide), Wisner ( Traditional, Technical Field, Pocket
Expedition). New monorail cameras available from Arca-Swiss (F-line,
Metric, Monolith), Linhof (Kardan), Sinar, Peter Gowland (all movements,
light), Toho (FC-57).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of the most affordable cameras on the used market such as the
Kodak, Burke and James, and Korona were made at a time when 5x7 was
still a popular format. They come with 4x5 and 5x7 backs, like the the
4x5 Canham wood, which is actually a 5x7 with a reducing back. Worth
noting on the used market are the Nagaoka and Anba Ikeda, which weight
only 3.75 lbs, less than almost all 2x3 cameras ! Nagoaka still makes
ultralight 5x7, but they are not imported to the US.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lenses to cover 5x7 are plenty, and range from the Schneider 72XL
(equivalent to a 15mm lens in 35mm) to the Nikkor 1200 T, with plenty of
choice in between. Most of the 4x5 lenses, especially in the longer
focals, will cover 5x7. Taking into account the usable surface area of a
sheet of 5x7 film, you&amp;rsquo;d multiply your 35mm focal length by 4.7 to get
your 5x7 focal length. Most photographers will find that, with a few
exceptions, the lenses that they use in 4x5, starting from 90mm up, will
cover the 5x7 format.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The focals for 5x7 are 1.4 as large as those for 4x5 for the same angle
of view, which translates into larger lenses. However, a lot of 4x5
photographers use lenses which have more coverage they need. Examples of
such lenses are the &lt;sup&gt;120&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;8&lt;/sub&gt; wide angle lenses (which are being displaced
by the Schneider 110XL), and the &lt;sup&gt;210&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;5&lt;/sub&gt;.6 plasmats, which all cover the
5x7 format with plenty of spare image circle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;film-and-holders&#34;&gt;Film and holders&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The cost is automatically higher due to larger size. This is the one
area where the choice in 5x7 is much less than in 4x5.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No preloaded film (ie Fuji Quickloads or Kodak Readyloads) are
available, so you have to use double cut film holders. These are
bulkier, heavier, require you to spend a significant amount of time
loading and unloading (usually at a time you&amp;rsquo;d rather go to bed to get
rested for that 5am sunrise), are more prone to catching dust, and more
difficult to track. You cannot use Polaroid film in this format either
(it&amp;rsquo;s available for 4x5 and 8x10). All the digital scanning backs are
designed for 4x5.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main problem for many is that the number of emulsions available is
extremely limited in color in their country. In particular, those
emulsions can be difficult to get in the US market.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kodak recently dropped several of their 5x7 emulsions. As of 2005, in
the US, you can get only Kodak Ektachrome Professional EPR 64 and EPY
64T as transparency films. Those are pretty old films which have a
following for product photography but that few landscape photographers
would find satisfying. In addition Kodak 160NC (negative) is also
available in 5x7.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fuji makes Velvia, Astia, and Provia F in 5x7, but it is not officially
imported in the US. International sources include:
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.unicircuits.com/shop/&#34;&gt;http://www.unicircuits.com/shop/&lt;/a&gt; (in Japan) &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bobrigby.com/&#34;&gt;http://www.bobrigby.com/&lt;/a&gt;
(UK) &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.robertwhite.co.uk/&#34;&gt;http://www.robertwhite.co.uk/&lt;/a&gt; (UK) however, note that in any case
the price will be above \$5/sheet. In the US the most convenient source
is Badger Graphics, however, they have to buy it retail in Japan, and as
a result, you&amp;rsquo;ll also pay \$5-\$6/sheet (Jeff says they don&amp;rsquo;t make money
on the transaction). Note that due to lack of demand, Badger doesn&amp;rsquo;t
import Astia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In B&amp;amp;W, the choice is better, with Kodak Tri-X, TMX, Ilford FP4+ and
HP5+, and Bergger BPF200, to choose from in the US. Other available
European films in 5x7, all currently imported by J and C, nclude Forte
400, Efke PL25, Efke PL100, and Rollei R3. B&amp;amp;H offers Fomapan 100 and
200 in 5x7 by special order. Arista films from Freestyle in Los Angeles
have been found to have identical characteritics to Ilford films. T-Max
100 film in 5x7 size is available as Nov 2001 a special order in single
50 sheet box qualities from a Kodak registered sales dealer (the Kodak
order number is #822-6334). The same 5x7 sheet film in T-Max 400
requires a 30 box minimum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Europe, both 5x7 and 13cmx18cm coexist and you can get both sizes
(but metric is easier to find). The size of the film is different (5x7
is 12.7cm x 17.8cm and the difference is beyond the internal dimensional
tolerance), therefore the holders are too, however, the exterior
dimensions of the holders are the same so you don&amp;rsquo;t have to modify the
camera. In the US, Calumet sells 13x18 film holders (that are actually
makes by the same factory that produces 5x7 holders), and J and C photo
sell European 13x18 film. There is also the option of buying over the
internet over suppliers such as Nord Photo in Germany. The choice of
13x18 film is quite large and includes Kodak Portra 100 T,E100G, E100VS,
Agfa RSX 100, Fuji NPS (negative), Provia F, Astia F, Velvia F, Velvia.
Prices are comparable to the retail price for 5x7 film in the US before
it was discontinued in the late 1990s, eg. 40-50 Euro. Using 13x18 film
may possibly be the best option for color photographers. Ted Harris has
offered to &lt;a href=&#34;http://largeformatphotography.info/lfforum/topic/502165.html&#34;&gt;facilitate a group
order&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I chose to cut myself the film from 8x10. This is done neatly with a
Rotatrim Mastercut II, a rotary blade cutter, and while it sounds a
delicate task at first, it is in fact very easy to do. I wouldn&amp;rsquo;t use
anything else, as precision is critical. One tip: I&amp;rsquo;ve found that it is
difficult to align the film with minute precision, I cut slightly
smaller than 5x7 to be sure there won&amp;rsquo;t be problems to fit holders.
Because of that, you&amp;rsquo;ll need to cut a sheet of 8x10 three times to make
two 5x7. If you use only one kind of film, it is not necessary to punch
a new notch. I just keep the film emulsion facing the top of the film
box. I have misloaded film only one time, out of more than a thousand of
sheets cut. It takes me between 30 min to one hour to cut 25 8x10
sheets. It&amp;rsquo;s not that tedious if you listen to music at the same time.
The problem is that while you don&amp;rsquo;t have to worry about finger marks
which are washed away by the developper, you increase significantly the
chance of getting dust on your film, which in turn can cause surface
scratches as you are traveling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With this method, you can use any emulsion which is available in 8x10.
The cost of a sheet of color transparency film is \$3-\$4 if 8x10 is
bought in boxes of 50. Personally, I located a large batch of
out-of-date, cold-stored 8x10 Astia that I bought at a very low price,
so I won&amp;rsquo;t have to look for film for maybe one more decade. At this
point, my main problem is that I have only 5x7 film boxes that date from
the good old eays days when EPP and Velvia were available in the US, and
although I have a large number of them, each year they get more worn
out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;processing-viewing-scanning-and-printing&#34;&gt;Processing, Viewing, Scanning, and Printing&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All commercial labs will process 4x5, but there are a number of them
which don&amp;rsquo;t have racks for 5x7. The price of processing 5x7 is often
twice as much as 4x5, and comparable to processing 8x10. Most will find
it necessary to use mail order processing, especially with the closure
of many E6 commercial labs caused by the widespread adoption of digital.
I have used Flatiron Color Lab, Holland photo, and Fleshtone LA.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The price of commercial scanning and printing is independent from the
transparency size. An excellent drum scan on the Heidelberg scanners,
resulting in a 300 MB file can be had for \$80 from several sources,
including West Coast Imaging and Pictopia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to scan yourself, for 5x7, the good news is that you don&amp;rsquo;t
need the same scanning resolution as for 4x5 to get equivalent results.
1800 dpi, within reach of most current flatbed scanners, will yield that
300MB file with 5x7. Although the choice in scanners for 5x7 film is
adequate, 4x5 photographers have more choices. Introduced in 2004, The
Epson 4870 was the first popular unit that had a transparency unit large
enough for 5x7. Replaced by the 4990, which can scan up to 8x10, it can
be had for less than \$400. Prior to that, the Epson units were limited
to 4x5 for many years. The recent Microtek i900 scanner in the same
price range will also handle 5x7. I choose the Epson over the Microtek
because its digital ICE (automatic dust removal) works on
transparencies, while Microtek&amp;rsquo;s ICE works only for reflective
materials, however I was not able to get this feature to work on large
scans. The advantage of the Microtek would be a drawer for glassless
scanning. Up to a budget of \$1000, there are a few 8x10 scanners (such
as the Microtek 1800) which are said to be better than the Epsons. While
there are other options available in 4x5 in between, for 5x7, the next
step are the high-end Imacon scanners. However, note that with the
Imacons the resolution drops with film size. So if you have a piece of
5x7 film, the largest file you can produce is about 230MB. This might
suffice in practice, but it is not very satisfying for a scanner of that
price. The FT848 scanner will scan the 5x7 transparencies at a maximum
resolution of 1600 dpi. Their latest and greatest, the FT 949 will only
scan up to 4x5.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you buy a flatbed scanner, you will most likely find that while it
comes with holders for 4x5, and maybe 8x10, there are no holders for
5x7. My solution is to cut a piece of matboard with a 5x7 opening, and
tape the transparency by its four edges with some stretch. The tension
helps with film flatness, to the point that some 4x5 users have reported
obtaining sharper scans with such custom holders than with the stock
holder. Just laying out the transparency on the glass is not optimal for
two reasons: the possibility of Newton rings, and the fact that the
focus distance of the scanner is above the glass. In fact, this focus
distance is not carefully controlled on consumer scanners, and some
users have found that while it is close to the distance to the stock
holders, it is not exactly equal. To experiment with various holder
thickness, matboard is too thick, and a possibility is to use thin
sheets of black plastic from a clear book folder, sold in stationary
stores.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To view 5x7 color transparencies, I recommend the Hakuba KLV-5700
viewer. It is ultra slim with even illumination, and can be used either
with an AC adaptor or on batteries. The viewing area is exactly 5x7, so
there the distracting bright border is minimal. The only drawback of
this viewer is that it is not as bright as some thicker ones. Hakuba
products are not widely sold in the US, so see
http:/&amp;gt;www.hakubausa.com&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you work in B&amp;amp;W, you&amp;rsquo;ll most likely do your own processing, so you
won&amp;rsquo;t incur high costs. You can easily find a 5x7 B&amp;amp;W enlarger on the
used market. The Zone VI enlarger will work with this format, and seems
to be the most popular new 5x7 enlarger.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;in-conclusion&#34;&gt;In conclusion&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;5x7 is an interesting compromise between 4x5 and 8x10.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are a B&amp;amp;W photographer, I believe that by steping up to 5x7,
you&amp;rsquo;ll lose only the portability of some lightweight 4x5 systems, and
you&amp;rsquo;ll have much to gain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The color 5x7 photographer faces additional problems related to scarcity
of film and processing, which do not affect the 4x5 photographers. The
gains from the larger transparency are less tangible, unless you plan to
make huge prints.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, if you are still tempted by a larger format than 4x5, 5x7 can
replace entirely 4x5 and 8x10 so that you can work in a single format,
and not worry about which camera to take regardless of whether you are
shooting next to your car, or backpacking for a week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;view-add-comments-http-largeformatphotography-info-lfforum-topic-503911-html&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://largeformatphotography.info/lfforum/topic/503911.html&#34;&gt;View/Add comments&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>http://lflf.surge.sh</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lflf.surge.sh</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Large Format Photography: 8x10 cameras&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;8x10-cameras&#34;&gt;8x10 cameras&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;By John Sparks for &lt;a href=&#34;.&#34;&gt;the Large Format Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For new cameras, there are about 3 field cameras that make sense.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Phillips makes some really interesting cameras that are very light
weight but have somewhat limited bellows extension. If you are not into
long lenses, they are one of the best choices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Canham makes a really good camera (I have one) that is also very light
(slightly heavier than Phillips) but had much longer bellows extension.
There are some things I don&amp;rsquo;t really like about it (mostly that it&amp;rsquo;s not
as rigid as I would like for long bellows extensions but it&amp;rsquo;s hard to
have great rigidity and low weight at the same time, I also get pinched
at times with the lever locks, I generally prefer knobs). It is
unfortunately very expensive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The third good choice is the Wisner Traditional L. It&amp;rsquo;s about \$900 less
than the Canham. It weighs about 1 lb more. I don&amp;rsquo;t know about it&amp;rsquo;s
rigidity at large extensions, but suspect it might be better because of
it&amp;rsquo;s construction. It wasn&amp;rsquo;t available when I bought my Canham, but I&amp;rsquo;d
probably buy it instead if I were doing it over now (mostly because of
the lower price for a very similar camera).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;view-or-add-comments-http-www-greenspun-com-com-qtluong-photography-lf-8x10-html&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.greenspun.com/com/qtluong/photography/lf/8x10.html&#34;&gt;View or add comments&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>http://lflf.surge.sh</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lflf.surge.sh</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h2 id=&#34;large-format-photography-site-affiliate-links&#34;&gt;Large Format Photography Site Affiliate Links&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have Affiliate Links, shown below, for B&amp;amp;H and Amazon. Accessing
those sites with these links produce a small commission to the forum, at
no additional expense to you, should you purchase something during the
session. Those commissions will be used to offset out-of-pocket forum
and server expenses, and as a reserve fund for forum operations. For
your convenience, we have made them more accessible from the main forum,
or you may choose to bookmark them as your main link to those sites
within your browser, if you&amp;rsquo;d like to do so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bhphotovideo.com/?BI=1620&amp;amp;KBID=2184&#34;&gt;B&amp;amp;H Photo Video&lt;/a&gt;
(&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bhphotovideo.com/?BI=1620&amp;amp;KBID=2184&#34;&gt;http://www.bhphotovideo.com/?BI=1620&amp;amp;KBID=2184&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/exec/obidos/redirect-home/alargeformatphot&#34;&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt;
(&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/exec/obidos/redirect-home/alargeformatphot&#34;&gt;http://www.amazon.com/exec/obidos/redirect-home/alargeformatphot&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>http://lflf.surge.sh</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lflf.surge.sh</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Large Format Photography: Arca Swiss 4x5 cameras&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;arca-swiss-f-line-4x5&#34;&gt;Arca Swiss F-Line 4x5&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Part of &lt;a href=&#34;.&#34;&gt;the Large Format Page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Contents:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#review&#34;&gt;Review of the F-line by Barry Sherman&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#comparison&#34;&gt;Differences between models&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#more&#34;&gt;More info, including Arca Swiss product litterature&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[]{#review}&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-review-of-the-f-line&#34;&gt;A review of the F-line&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;by Barry Sherman, Copyright © 1994&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve been using this camera for a little more than 1 year, have used it
on several one and two week photo trips and have little inclination to
use anything else.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please note that throughout this there&amp;rsquo;s a noticible prejudice against
folding field cameras and that this is not intended to be a
pronouncement of a universal law, but merely my own preference showing
through.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Arca Swiss F-Line provides full monorail movements while weighing
and bulking no more than most of the more capable folding field cameras.
I like the camera a lot and have yet to find a camera for which I&amp;rsquo;d
trade it. (Well, maybe a Carbon Infinity, but I&amp;rsquo;d hesitate for fear of
not being able to get that one repaired. Besides which, I haven&amp;rsquo;t won
the lottery yet.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The camera just does what it&amp;rsquo;s supposed to do quickly, easily and
doesn&amp;rsquo;t get in my way. It&amp;rsquo;s hard to ask for more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;what-i-was-looking-for&#34;&gt;What I was looking for&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wanted a 4x5 camera light enough to carry in a backpack for distances
up to a few miles, rugged enough to carry thusly and with enough
movements to use for architectural and table-top photography as well as
landscapes. I wanted a &amp;ldquo;one-camera-does-everything&amp;rdquo; camera because I
didn&amp;rsquo;t want to have to buy another view camera for a good long while.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition, the camera needed to be quick to set up, something which
most folding field cameras appear to me not to be (IMHO, of course).
(Note: John Sparks reports that it takes him no longer to set up his
Canham 8x10 than it does me to set up my Arca Swiss 4x5, except that the
Arca Swiss can be stored with lens attached.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The major contenders for my interest were the Wisner Technical and the
Linhof Technikardan. The Linhof Technika would have been a contender
save for the price of the more recent models. I chose the Arca because
it has movements equal to or greater than any of these cameras, weighs
in the same ballpark and, while it will not focus lenses as long as will
the Wisner or the Technikardan, it has the advantage of being part of a
monorail system, allowing expansion of its capacities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s where I&amp;rsquo;ll try to offend as many people as possible :-) :&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn&amp;rsquo;t consider the Sinar A1 because it&amp;rsquo;s just too bulky for my
tastes, didn&amp;rsquo;t consider the Zone VI because of reports from too many
people that the fit of the pieces and quality control aren&amp;rsquo;t up to snuff
(but boy they sure are purty! :-), didn&amp;rsquo;t consider the Horseman, Toyo or
Wista metal field cameras because their movements and bellows draw are
more restrictive than I want and didn&amp;rsquo;t consider the Toyo VX125 (sp?)
because it hadn&amp;rsquo;t been introduced at the time and besides which it costs
far more than I&amp;rsquo;d be willing to spend.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;specs&#34;&gt;Specs&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;NOTE:  the &amp;quot;normal&amp;quot; position of the front and rear standard rise/fall
       is all the way down.  Thus the spec. for rise/fall is actually
       for rise alone for each standard, although one may certainly
       chose to zero each standard at the midpoint of this movement.

NOTE:  When I went to write this I found that I no longer have the
       factory specs on this camera and so everything that I state here
       is from my own manual measurements.  Thus there may be some
       discrepency from published factory specs.


Max. Flange Focal Length:  (bellows draw)     15 5/8 inches  (382mm)

Min. Flange Focal Length:  (bellows draw)     2 inches (50mm) with
optional wide-angle bellows installed

Rise:              + 4 inches (98mm) both front and rear

Shift:             +/- 3.25 inches (75mm) either side of &amp;quot;zero&amp;quot;
           both front and rear

Swing:             limited by bellows front and rear

Base Tilt:         +/- 30 degrees front and rear

Axis Tilt:         none

Geared Movements:  front and rear focusing only.

Back type:         graflok

Back movements:    switches between horizontal and
           vertical in seconds but doesn&#39;t rotate

&amp;quot;Zero detents&amp;quot;:    All movements except for rise, which
           is normally in the full-down position

Weight:            7.5 lbs.  NOTE:  Specs say that the Linhof Master
                                    Technika weighs 7.0 lbs and the 
                                    Wisner Technical weighs 6.5 lbs.

Cost:              I paid $1,900 for the body, new
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;how-it-works&#34;&gt;How it works&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I carry this camera the way that others carry a folding field camera and
am able to do this because of the way that it disassembles. The monorail
actually consists of three pieces. There&amp;rsquo;s one piece about 12 inches
long which attaches to the tripod. Atop this, sliding in &amp;ldquo;dovetails&amp;rdquo; in
the bottom piece, are two shorter pieces each about 6 inches long. Each
of these is locked in place by a cam-action lever and can be slid to the
front or rear as appropriate and then locked in place to increase the
overall length of the monorail. Thus you can leave the two upper
segments touching and have a 12 inch monorail or slide them apart and
have one nearly 18 inches long.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The front and rear standards of the camera slide onto these upper
monorail pieces and move along them to provide focusing. Thus, you can
move the front standard onto the upper front monorail segment, move the
rear standard onto the upper rear monorail segment and then separate
these segments by sliding them forward and backward as appropriate to
attain the full 15 &lt;sup&gt;5&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;8&lt;/sub&gt; inch (flange focal length) extension.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When it&amp;rsquo;s time to put the camera away, you slide the two upper monorail
segments together so that they form one continuous rail and then slide
both the front and rear standard onto one of the upper segments. After
locking the standards in place with the focus lock, you can unlock that
upper monorail segment itself and remove it, with front and rear
standards attached to it, from the lower monorail arm. This reduces the
camera to a size very little larger than most folding field cameras, be
they wood or metal. Next the lower monorail segment, with the remaining
upper segment attached, is removed from the tripod and put in the
backpack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Obviously, setup is the opposite of this operation and goes very
quickly. Just attach the lower monorail segment to the tripod, slide the
upper segment with both standards attached onto the lower segment, move
the two standards the appropriate distance apart and the camera&amp;rsquo;s ready
to go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Very few people can get a folding field camera set up in the 15 seconds
that it usually takes me to set up the Arca Swiss. (not counting setting
up the tripod, of course) This speed is abetted by the fact that I can
leave the lens attached, something that one cannot do with most folding
field cameras.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the down side, the camera doesn&amp;rsquo;t fold up into a box, and doesn&amp;rsquo;t
provide protection for the groundglass. But I&amp;rsquo;ve only had one problem
with damage to the camera and that was caused by improper packing on my
part when I checked the camera in its soft backpack as airline baggage.
I now load the entire backpack and tripod into a very large hard-sided
suitcase and then check *that*. And I find that a Calumet groundglass
protector prevents damage to the groundglass quite nicely since I
reinforced it with a second thickness of ABS plastic. (No, it wasn&amp;rsquo;t the
Arca groundglass that was broken before I reinforced the protector - it
was the Bender Kit groundglass.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;what-i-like&#34;&gt;What i like&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The camera&amp;rsquo;s really rigid. My previous two cameras were a Bender Kit
which was not very rigid at all and a Calumet 400 series which was
also not very rigid. By comparison, this thing&amp;rsquo;s a tank. Of course,
it&amp;rsquo;s pretty wobbly compared to a 15-20 lb. studio monorail, but few
people will carry a studio monorail into the field. Anyway, nothing
moves out of alignment when locked and when inserting film holders.&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Movements work very nicely. I don&amp;rsquo;t really notice the lack of
gearing on them. Controls are well thought out and logical in
placement. Nearly mnemonic. Locks lock without having to use
excessive force.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve been caught in a sandstorm while photographing with the Arca
and 1) Was able to continue working afterward, despite definite
grittiness in the movements and 2) was able to clean the sand and
dust out of the mechanisms easily later that day back at the motel.
The mechanisms are easy to disassemble and reassemble if you have
the right tools - just a couple of small hex-wrenches and
screwdrivers.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The wide-angle bellows is a dream. This is not a bag but rather a
pleated leather bellows made from incredibly soft leather and with
really large pleats. It&amp;rsquo;s so supple that even at the minimum flange
focal length of 2 inches I can get 2 inches of rise from the
standards. That&amp;rsquo;s incredible! Granted, that&amp;rsquo;s far more rise than any
short lens could provide in its image circle. I mention it only as
an illustration of how supple the bellows is. In addition, it
extends long enough to use it with a 210mm lens provided that only
modest movements are being used.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similarly, the regular bellows is usable with lenses down to 135mm,
provided that only moderate movements are used or with a 90mm lens
if very minimal movements are used. What this means is that I don&amp;rsquo;t
have to change between the two bellows very often.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even better, the wide-angle bellows doesn&amp;rsquo;t protrude into the light
path as have some bag bellows that I&amp;rsquo;ve used. I&amp;rsquo;ve used bag bellows
which had to be carefully pulled and adjusted after the camera was
set up because they&amp;rsquo;d deform and protrude into the light path. This
Arca Swiss wide-angle bellows, through some magical properties of
physics unknown to me, never does this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now for the downside: the price of the wonderful leather wide-angle
bellows was \$500. Ouch! They also make a synthetic wide-angle
bellows for &lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; that price but I couldn&amp;rsquo;t locate any when I bought
the camera and so bit the bullet and got the leather one. Now that
I&amp;rsquo;ve absorbed the cost I&amp;rsquo;m glad that I did as it&amp;rsquo;s really a joy to
work with, but it really hurt at first.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An extension bellows, required if lenses longer than 300mm in a
normal lens or 500mm in a telephoto design are to be used, costs,
you guessed it, about \$500. This has kept me from extending the
capabilities of the camera to date. That and not having the money
for a longer lens anyway.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The camera comes with a built-in fresnel lens which works better
than those which I&amp;rsquo;ve used in the past.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Camera has &amp;ldquo;zero detents&amp;rdquo; on all movements. A delightful convenience
after the Bender which has zero detents on no movements and the
Calumet, whose zero detents were inoperable due to rust. (Apparently
the zero detents were the one place that I failed to clean after the
Calumet went swimming in the Pacific Ocean. :-)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I was worried that, after being accustomed to center tilts, I&amp;rsquo;d find
base tilts difficult to use. Not only do I not find this to be the
case, I really like the ease of being able to combine both swing and
tilt on the same standard without getting weird distortions caused
by yaw. Certainly, with my other two cameras with their center tilts
I can avoid yaw by using the cameras tilted 90 degrees on their
sides, but that&amp;rsquo;s a pain in the neck.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The person who sold the camera to me commented that I&amp;rsquo;d be surprised
at how quickly the camera would just kind of fade into the
background and do what I wanted it to, compared to some of the
hassles that I&amp;rsquo;d had with the Bender and the Calumet.
He was right.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;what-i-dislike-about-it&#34;&gt;What I dislike about it&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The lens boards are ludicrously large - nearly 7 inches square! Way
to large to store several lenses in a backpack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All is not lost, however, as Keith Canham, maker of the Canham view
cameras, has produced an adaptor which allows one to use Linhof
Technika style lens boards on the Arca Swiss. So my lenses are
mounted in Technika style (actually they&amp;rsquo;re labeled Wista) lens
boards. This adaptor is on the one Arca lens board that I have which
stays mounted on the camera at all times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Naturally, the cost of the adaptor was \$250 (rather a lot, I
think). And I&amp;rsquo;m not completely satisfied with the quality of the
adaptor as a couple of anodized studs and a leaf spring both show
signs of rust after spending a couple of weeks in Hawaii. This
doesn&amp;rsquo;t seem to reflect the level of quality that I expected, given
the name of the manufacturor and the price. But the adaptor
*works* just fine and I&amp;rsquo;m pleased with it overall. I&amp;rsquo;d never have
considered using this camera in the field without being able to use
smaller lens boards and this makes it possible.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I cannot remove the fresnel lens if I want to as focus shifts
minutely when I do. The fresnel lens and groundglass are mounted
such that the fresnel lens is *not* acting as a spacer for the
groundglass, but for some reason focus definitely shifts when I try
to remove it. Fortunately, it&amp;rsquo;s one of the better groundglass
brightening systems that I&amp;rsquo;ve used so I don&amp;rsquo;t mind it too much, but
I&amp;rsquo;d prefer to have options here.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Support sucks. This may have improved, however. But at the time that
I bought it, there was no official Arca distributor in the U.S. The
person from whom I bought it, a salesman in a camera store near
Phoenix AZ, assured me that his connections with people at the
manufacturor in Switzerland would allow him to obtain parts easily.
And he was most prompt about shipping the camera and other
accessories to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But when the camera was broken by airline baggage handlers (actually
by my own poor packing), it took 6 months and several phone calls to
get the repair parts. As it happened, I was able to mend it
immediately on my own but I felt more comfortable having officially
unbroken parts and was not at all pleased with the slow response. It
appeared strongly to me that my broken camera was not a high
priority with this person and my view of hims is somewhat jaundiced
as a result. (I.e. he did not appear to me to pursue matters with
the people in Switzerland with any great zeal.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, I&amp;rsquo;ve seen ads in magazines which indicate that there is now
an official Arca Swiss distributor for the U.S. so accessories and
parts may now be easier to come by. Plus, the person from whom I
bought it has told me that he&amp;rsquo;s a distributor for the SW U.S. so I
have some hope.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s a little heavier than I&amp;rsquo;d like. Like about 3-4 lbs heavier. But
most every other camera which has the features that I want weighs in
the same ballpark so I&amp;rsquo;m not really complaining. And if I want to
walk more than a few miles then I can always trade the Arca for the
Bender Kit which only weighs 3 lbs.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notice that I&amp;rsquo;m not coming up with any real user complaints? That&amp;rsquo;s
because I don&amp;rsquo;t have any!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[]{#comparison}&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;differences-with-other-models&#34;&gt;Differences with other models&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;differences-with-the-discovery&#34;&gt;Differences with the Discovery&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;12&amp;rdquo; rail, no fresnel, only levels on one side (2) and rear(1), No front
focus (just slide and lock), knobs on function blocks are cream-colored.
Comes with case (optional backpack straps) Has tiny (1.5&amp;rdquo;) tripod block.
You can add all Arca Accessories to the Discovery to upgrade including
fresnel, additional rail/bellows, etc. &lt;strong&gt;Don Nelson&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;an-older-arca-swiss-compared-to-a-f-line&#34;&gt;An older Arca Swiss, compared to a F-line&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It has axial tilts instead of base tilts.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It has serrated plastic knobs instead of rubberized ones.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The metal surfaces are not black-anodized.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The rail doesn&amp;rsquo;t collapse/expand.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There are flash shoes on the front and rear standards(!).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No fresnel.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No grid lines.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No serial numbers(?).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The standards have rounded edges instead of sharply-squared ones.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It doesn&amp;rsquo;t have any scales except for rise, and only at .5 cm
intervals at that.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The lens boards and rails are supposedly compatible, but the bellows are
not. Worse, I rented a 90mm lens (Caltar II-N) on a recessed lens board
and discovered that the construction of the camera won&amp;rsquo;t permit infinity
focus with this lens! &lt;strong&gt;Alvin Chia-Hua Shih&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;older-and-newer-f-line-models&#34;&gt;Older and newer F-line models&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The older style F-line standards definitely fit on the newer high
profile rails.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, you might contact Rod Klukas at Photomark. He currently has a
bunch of the older style rails and bridges at a good price (a couple of
folding low profile rail). Photomark is at 602-244-1133. Patience is
sometimes necessary as he&amp;rsquo;s got a lot of business&amp;hellip;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is at least two folding low profile rails(from two FC cameras) and
a longer bridge with a section of low profile rails. (Excellent
condition)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is at least two folding low profile rails(from two FC cameras) and
a longer bridge with a section of low profile rails. (Excellent
condition)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;BTW here&amp;rsquo;s the differences between the older and newer style F-line Arca
Swiss Rails: (bridge = the unit that the rail goes into for attachment
to the tripod. It comes in many sizes, from about 3 inches up thru a
meter long section)(sometimes the bridge is called a bracket in the
literature).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;                        OLD     (low profile)   NEW (high profile)

Clamping mechanism    Compression via         Compression by pulling down
                      adjustable clamp        on slot on bottom side of
                      on side of bridge       new rail
                      (Bridge clamp is a      Bridge clamping mechanism is in
                     screw across the inside  the bottom of the inside of the
                        of the bridge)          bridge.

RAIL                    Short height            tall height
                        solid rail              rail has a T-slot in bottom
                                                (this slot is where the bridge
                                                attachment mechanis goes)
And the compression on the older profile bridges occurs when the sides
are pulled together by a lever on the rail. 
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Don Nelson&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[]{#more}&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;more-info&#34;&gt;More info&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;As of Jan 2001, Arca-Swiss doesn&amp;rsquo;t maintain a web site&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Arca Swiss product litterature: &lt;a href=&#34;ARCA.zip&#34;&gt;zipped file (2 megs)&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&#34;ARCA.pdf&#34;&gt;PDF file (4 megs)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Review of the &lt;a href=&#34;arca23.html&#34;&gt;Arca Swiss F-Line 6x9&lt;/a&gt; which can also be
used as a 4x5 camera.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;comparison.html#sinar-vs-arca&#34;&gt;A comparison of the Sinar F1/F2 and the Arca-Swiss F
cameras&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.greenspun.com/com/qtluong/photography/lf/arca-swiss.html&#34;&gt;View or add
comments&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>http://lflf.surge.sh</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lflf.surge.sh</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Arca Swiss 6 x 9 FC: a review&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;arca-swiss-6-x-9-fc-a-review&#34;&gt;Arca Swiss 6 x 9 FC: a review&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;By &lt;a href=&#34;mailto:jocome@cris.com&#34;&gt;J. C. Metcalf&lt;/a&gt; for &lt;a href=&#34;.&#34;&gt;the Large Format
Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For some reason the Arca Swiss 6 x 9 FC view camera tends to be
overlooked in reviews of this format. It shouldn&amp;rsquo;t be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Arca Swiss 6x9 is a very high quality, easily transportable full
featured monorail camera. The camera is extremely compact. The &amp;ldquo;FC&amp;rdquo;
designates a monorail that folds in half for easy storage. For use, the
two monorail sections screw easily and quickly together. The front and
rear standards ride on geared blocks on the monorail. The monorail
itself slides into a 3.25&amp;rdquo; dovetailed rail clamp that screws to the
tripod. An adjustable lever on the side of the clamp tightens it against
the monorail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Arca 6x9 FC has front and rear base tilts, front and rear side to
side sliding movements, 3&amp;rdquo; of front rise and 3&amp;rdquo; of rear rise, front and
rear swings. There are built in levels both front and rear. All
movements are smooth, sold and precise. In five years of pretty
demanding use I have never had a problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All movements can be locked with nicely designed and easy to use round
knobs that have never stuck. It comes with flat and recessed lens
boards. The standard rail is 12&amp;rdquo; long and additional, longer, rails are
available. The standard bellows is 10&amp;rdquo; and is an extremely flexible soft
pleated leather that is useable for the shortest lens I have (47mm
Schneider Super Angulon) to the longest I have (270mm Nikon Telephoto).
Longer bellows are available as is a wide angle bellows. The standard
bellows is really enough. The camera weighs just over 5 lbs. and is
easier to deal with than a Hasselblad. Why ?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the 6x9 Arca itself packs up in less room than the Hasselblad (I&amp;rsquo;ve
tested it!)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;view camera lenses on lens board take up less room than comparable
slr lenses. Compare, for example the volume of Hassie 250mm with the
Nikon 270 tele or compare either the the 47mm schneider (very small)
or 58mm schneider (bigger but still smaller than 50mm Hassie) with
the 50mm Hassie. 6x9 normal lens is the Nikon 105mm, noticeably
smaller than Hassie 80mm standard lens. View camera lenses all stop
down further than slr lenses (due to simpler shutter design). If
you&amp;rsquo;ve got standing aspen trees from 5 feet in front of the camera
to infinity you are glad to be able to stop down to f45. View camera
lenses, though certainly not cheap, cost less than comparable slr
lenses, again due to simpler design.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No extra close up attachments are needed with view camera - with
Hassie you need one or two extension tubes that do take up room.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the roll film backs for the Arca are about the same &amp;ldquo;volume&amp;rdquo; as the
Hassie - no real diff there.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ground glass viewing on the 6x9 view camera is much easier than
ground glass viewing on the Hassie. If you use one of the Hassie
viewing attachments you add significant weight and bulk. The ground
glass on the 6x9 Arca is small enough that rarely do I feel the need
for a focussing cloth, and when I do, I&amp;rsquo;ve got a 2&amp;rsquo;x2&amp;rsquo; piece of dark
blue waterproof cordura nylon that works fine.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Not having view camera adjustments is, to me, a true inconvenience -
converging lines in buildings, out of focus foregrounds and
backgrounds are burrs under my saddle - maybe idiosyncratic, but I
can&amp;rsquo;t help it!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the one feature the Hasselblad system has that I&amp;rsquo;ve not been able to
duplicate with a view camera is the superb Hasselblad bellows lens
shade and the same diameter bayonet attachment on the front of all
lenses from 38mm to 250mm. To me this is very minor.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;FILM. Roll film backs are &amp;ldquo;graflock&amp;rdquo; style. To use the film back the
ground glass is removed. The roll film back then attaches to a roll film
back holder which then locks onto the camera back. The process of
removing the ground glass and attaching the film back to the holder and
camera takes less than 10 seconds. I use four backs (b &amp;amp; w for &amp;ldquo;normal,&amp;rdquo;
&amp;ldquo;plus,&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;minus,&amp;rdquo; development and one back for color.) One holder for
the film backs is adequate. Polaroid film packs are easily used with the
NPC Polaroid adapter or the Arca Swiss Polaroid adapter. The NPC I have
has been trouble free for 5 years and was about half the price of the
Arca Swiss item.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Conversion to 4 x 5 is a snap. The Arca Swiss 4 x 5 F and FC are
virtually identical (except size) to the 6x9. The 4x5 uses the same
monorail and monorail clamp as the 6x9. Therefore, to use 4x5 all you
need is a 4x5 back and the available tapered bellows that allows use of
the 6x9 front standard with the 4x5 back. You can then use the much
smaller 6x9 metal lensboards (4.25&amp;rdquo; square). The 4x5 back is &amp;ldquo;graflock&amp;rdquo;
style meaning it can use roll film holders as well as standard sheet
film holders. Now Arca Swiss is offering something called the 4 x 5 FC
line Field. This new 4 x 5 is described as being a 4 x 5 camera with a 6
x 9 front and a tapered bellows. I assume this means that a camera one
could assemble by purchasing accessory parts is now offered as a unit. I
saw this &amp;ldquo;new&amp;rdquo; camera advertised by &amp;ldquo;the F Stops here&amp;rdquo; in Shutterbug -
but I haven&amp;rsquo;t seen it in person. It does offer another &amp;ldquo;off the shelf&amp;rdquo; 4
x 5 option that will be somewhat more compact and lighter than the
previous off the shelf Arca Swiss 4 x 5. &lt;em&gt;NdE: I met on an Olympic NP
beach a photographer from Switzerland who was using the mixed 4x5 / 6x9
F-line camera with roll-film. He said that although he uses only
roll-film, he still prefered to use 4x5 so that he could do 6x12 (he had
a Sinar zoom back that the seemed to like a lot). His reason for using
the 6x9 camera was to save one pound of weight, and the smaller
lensboards.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have had five years of experience with this camera. It has gone to
Europe four times. The camera, five lenses, four roll film holders,
eight screw in filters fit securely into a small Lightware medium format
case that can be carried on to your airplane and put in the overhead
luggage bin. The camera has made a number of domestic flights, been
backpacking around the Rocky Mountains, travelled the high plains, the
Utah desert, New Mexico and the Olympic Penninsula rain forest. I use it
often in the studio, especially for portraits and figures, in preference
to 4x5 and 8x10. Results? It has never disappointed. Modern lenses and
TMX 100 film (EI 64) developed in TMX RS give great results. 20&amp;rdquo;x12.5&amp;rdquo;
enlargments are astonishingly sharp - individual hairs, skin blemishes,
grass, twigs, leaves are crisp.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Price today is probably around \$2,500.00. Less expensive than Horseman
or Linhof medium format view cameras. Toyo is probably a little less
expensive. Horseman is less versatile. Linhof is comparable though not
quite as versative. Toyo is comparable in movements and versatility but
weighs 8.5lbs and is not as compact. Support - Calumet (&lt;sup&gt;800&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;225&lt;/sub&gt;-8638)
now supplies and supports Arca Swiss. Calumet is reliable, trustworthy,
and if they don&amp;rsquo;t have it they&amp;rsquo;ll get it. The Calumet prices are better
than most retail outlets and the difference in price between Calumet and
New York discounters reflects the enhanced service and competence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;view-or-add-comments-http-www-greenspun-com-com-qtluong-photography-lf-arca23-html&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.greenspun.com/com/qtluong/photography/lf/arca23.html&#34;&gt;View or add comments&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>http://lflf.surge.sh</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lflf.surge.sh</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Large Format Photography: Bruce Barnbaum workshop - trip report&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;bruce-barnbaum-workshop-trip-report&#34;&gt;Bruce Barnbaum workshop: trip report&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;By &lt;a href=&#34;mailto:bjs@oes.amdahl.com&#34;&gt;Barry Sherman&lt;/a&gt; for &lt;a href=&#34;.&#34;&gt;the Large Format
Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;CAUTION:   The following posting contains non-sacreligious profanity.

CAUTION:   The following posting challenges some cherished notions.

CAUTION:   This is *really* long.

NOTE:      At times below I&#39;ll &amp;quot;quote&amp;quot; Bruce Barnbaum.  Mostly these
           aren&#39;t precise quotes but are used to try to capture the spirit of 
           what he said and how he said it.


I just returned from a 5.5 day workshop with Bruce Barnbaum and Don
Kirby.  Since there are occasional queries about good workshops to
attend, I thought I&#39;d do a big write-up about this one.  I&#39;m not going
to go into great detail about techniques as I think that attending the
workshop, or at the very least buying Bruce&#39;s book, will be of more
benefit than the sketchy details that I could discuss here.

Cost:   $475 + $75 lab fee.  I understand that the lab fee is going up to
        $150 as of now.  This cost is exclusive of lodging, food and 
        transportation and inclusive of use of Bruce&#39;s outstanding darkroom,
        equipped with 7 Saunders 4500 enlarger.  Lodging 
        at the nearby Mountain View Inn runs $20 per night if you&#39;re willing to    
        room with someone (recommended as there are 12 students in the workshop
        and only 6 rooms at the motel, the only motel around).  I, however, 
        made it known that I really wanted a private room and was able to have 
        one.  (thereby saving some poor soul from utter exhaustion from being 
        kept awake by my snoring  :-)  This made my lodging $40 per night.
        The lab fee includes all the 8x10 Kodak Elite paper that you want to 
        use during the lab sessions.

        Come to think of it, there are camp grounds nearby and people with
        campers are welcome to stay on their grounds and use their shower.

Where:  At Bruce&#39;s home in the Northern Cascade mountains in Washington
        state.  He lives outside of Granite Falls.  Beautiful location.
        People flew and drove in from California, Michigan, Texas, Nebraska,
        Arizona, New Jersey and, even, Washington (state).

Title:  &amp;quot;Complete Photographic Process&amp;quot;  Bruce does many workshops.  This
        one is devoted to black/white photography from exposure of the
        negative to mounting/spotting of the print.  Although there are
        3 field sessions during which you can expose film, and darkroom
        time allotted to negative development, students are encouraged
        to bring negatives with them, especially &amp;quot;problem negatives&amp;quot;,
        so as to be able to rework old images under the instructors&#39;
        tutelege.  Printing in his great darkroom using Saunders 4500
        enlargers with Dichro heads is a promiment feature of the workshop.

        BTW - this was my first actual use of the Saunders.  Great enlarger.  
        Nice bright bulb, easy to use controls, very, very rigid and all around
        a pleasure to use.  If I get a second enlarger I&#39;ll give very serious 
        thought to this one.

When:   Four times per year - Winter, Spring, Summer and Fall.

Contact:  Photographic Arts Workshops
          P.O Box 1791 
          Granite Falls, WA 98252
          (206) 691-4105

Who they are: 
--- ---- ----

  Bruce Barnbaum is one of the world&#39;s most highly acclaimed b/w landscape 
  photographers.  His work is available in galleries throughout the U.S.  I 
  was interested to learn that he has made stunning color (Ilfochrome) images 
  as well.  If &amp;quot;money is the most sincere form of appreciation&amp;quot;, then 
  consider:  his UNlimited edition 16x20&#39;s now command $750 and his limited 
  edition 20x24&#39;s go for $2,500.

  But if you don&#39;t believe in price as a measure of one&#39;s work, then:

  He showed us his work every evening after dinner.  Beyond belief.  This guy 
  is incredibly good.  Image after stunning image after exquisite image.  He 
  showed us between 80 and 100 prints throughout the course of the workshop 
  and, while some were not really to my personal taste, the quality was always 
  wonderful.  One might say &amp;quot;What is this?  I pay hundreds of dollars to stare 
  at someone else&#39;s photography?&amp;quot; But these &amp;quot;exhibitions&amp;quot; involved lots of 
  questions and discussion ranging from technique to philosophy and were 
  highly worthwhile.  And just plain interesting.  Some of his anecdotes about 
  photographing in slit canyons (and just missing a horrendous flash flood)
  were fascinating and downright frightening.  And I can&#39;t wait to hike the 
  length of Buckskin Gulch!

  Bruce is one of the most dynamic people I&#39;ve ever encountered.  He seems
  to bring an enormous passion to everything he does.  I&#39;m certain that
  this is a large part of the reason for his success.  It doesn&#39;t matter 
  whether he&#39;s exposing film, printing, listening to classical music, 
  fighting the proposed quarry which may destroy his lovely community or 
  fighting the clear-cutting which is destroying so much forest habitat. 
  Whatever he does, he does with every fiber of his being.  At some times I 
  found his intensity somewhat off-putting but at the same time I developed 
  great admiration and respect for him.  Plus, he has an inexhaustable supply 
  of really great jokes and anecdotes, which he shares at every opportunity.  
  Incredible supply of &amp;quot;groaners&amp;quot;.  Really terribly funny &amp;quot;groaners&amp;quot;.  :-)  
  E.g:  &amp;quot;You gotta pity poor David Koresh.  All his life he wanted to be a 
  priest but in the end he was only a friar.&amp;quot;  All together now:  
  Grrrooooooaaaaaannnnn.  :-)

  Don Kirby is, perhaps, less well known but is a marvelous photographer as 
  well.  Similarly, every evening he showed us his work and it was humbling.  
  His interests seem to be largely Anasazi ruins, which he&#39;s explored
  extensively for the last 10 or more years, wheat fields in their 
  infinite variety of form, and abstract patterns in rock.  Don is more
  laid back but I detect a passion for the natural world as deep as
  Bruce&#39;s.  Don&#39;s printing, like Bruce&#39;s, combines the bold with the subtle
  in a wonderfully expressive way.  Like Bruce, he&#39;s an excellent teacher,
  able to explain the complex, patient and genuinely interested in helping
  people to grow.

  I&#39;m impressed with Don in another way.  He not too long ago realized
  a 10 year goal:  early retirement and delving completely into his
  photography.  For the last decade he&#39;s worked at building a body of work
  and taken much time off from work without pay in order to photograph and
  to assist other photographers in teaching their workshops.  He is now
  co-instructor of this workshop and others with Bruce and will be leading
  his own in the near future (exploring Anasazi ruins in So. Utah).  I&#39;m
  really happy to see as good a person as Don being able to realize his
  dreams.

  All in all, two very remarkable people.  Oh, and for those of us in the Bay
  area, the work of both photographers may be viewed at the Photographers 
  Gallery in Palo Alto.  I&#39;ve not been there since Bruce&#39;s exhibit opened 
  there 1.5 years ago but will get there soon to see Don&#39;s work.

What the workshop is NOT:  
---- --- -------- -- ---

  It&#39;s *not* about any of the following:

  * Lenses
  * Cameras
  * Lp/mm
  * &amp;quot;Rules of composition&amp;quot;
  * Rules of pretty much any sort - Mr.&#39;s Barnbaum and Kirby are happy to
    tell you how they do things while maintaining that the student should
    be comfortable doing things completely differently if that&#39;s what works
    for the student.  For example, Bruce doesn&#39;t permit anything that beeps 
    in his darkroom.  But if you prefer a metronome, mechanical or electronic, 
    then use one.  Just find what works for you and then do it.  (As long as
    you don&#39;t try to bring chirpers or beepers into Bruce&#39;s darkroom. :-)
  * Introductory darkroom procedure
  * Mathematical formulae
  * A &amp;quot;fun photo tour&amp;quot;
  * A light skimming-over of everyone&#39;s work at the critique.
  * An ego building &amp;quot;soft-soap&amp;quot; praising of mediocre images during the 
    critique.
  * Slides.  Although I do think that a &amp;quot;strictly slides&amp;quot; photographer or a 
    color printer could benefit greatly from the workshop, it&#39;s really oriented
    toward b/w printing.  My color work, and I was the only person in the class
    who showed color work, was well received by both Bruce and Don, but, as I 
    said, the real purpose of the class is b/w prints.

  Not once during the 85 hours that I was around Bruce and Don did they 
  mention gear other than wrt darkroom stuff and in response to questions.  
  They would discuss equipment in response to questions and at great length.
  But rarely did they raise the subject themselves.

  Bruce, btw, uses the old-style &amp;quot;Time-o-Light&amp;quot; timers on the enlarger, 
  refuses to have anything that beeps in the darkroom, and seems to time
  his dodging and burning by intuition.  With incredibly consistent
  results.  I made a point of not mentioning my two-memory, multi-mode, beeping,
  digital electronic enlarger timer.  Nor my Zone VI Compensating
  Developing Timer.  :-)

  They are concerned with the production of images and seem to have little 
  interest in gear, per se.  I found this refreshing.  I gather that Bruce 
  uses a Linhof Technika (from photos of him with his camera) with a Tilt-all 
  tripod.  He&#39;s becoming quite enamored of his Mamiya 645, although he 
  considers the image to be of insufficient quality to replace the 4x5, 
  deeming it more appropriate for &amp;quot;hand-held&amp;quot; work.  Don uses a Technika
  as well.

What the workshop *is*:
---- --- -------- ----

  * Intensive.  We went from 7:00 a.m. until 11:00 p.m. every day except
    the final day which as a half day.  Monday morning through Saturday
    noon.  I normally drink 50/50 real and decaffeinated coffee as the pure 
    stuff really affects me strongly.  But during the workshop I was drinking 
    the real thing all day and most of the evening and hardly noticed the 
    caffein.  Not a place for those who cannot function on less than 8 hours 
    of sleep per night.  Nor a place for those for whom photography is a minor 
    part of their lives or whose interests lie more in hardware than in images.

  * A place at which people who are committed to this form of artistic 
    expression have the opportunity to grow.

  * As much about what&#39;s going on inside the photographer as about 
    specific techniques.

  * Excellent in every respect.  Oh, BTW, Bruce&#39;s wife, Karen, was a 
    wonderful hostess, making everyone feel welcome and comfortable
    in their home.  I&#39;ve come to think that once one leaves the urban
    areas it becomes impossible to find a cup of coffee that tastes like
    coffee instead of warm water.  But they served really great (and really
    strong) coffee and great goodies to munch on during the long sessions
    and this added to the pleasure of the class.  Even their dogs and cats 
    added a lot of enjoyment to the class. 

What they teach:
---- ---- -----

  * Composition and light.  But he never once mentioned &amp;quot;rule of thirds&amp;quot;
    or other &amp;quot;rules&amp;quot;.  BTW - if you ask &amp;quot;then what is there to discuss about 
    composition?&amp;quot; then you *really* need to take this workshop.  I did.

  * Intro to the zone system 101.  Or advanced study, depending on the
    group.  But he&#39;s not a fanatic about it.  He believes in making images,
    not in spending a lot of time testing materials.  He notes that he&#39;s yet
    to see an exciting image from those people who are heavy into testing
    of materials.  He didn&#39;t mention names, but I&#39;d already noticed the
    same thing in the articles on materials testing by the &amp;quot;big names&amp;quot; that
    I see in the magazines.  (Well, John Sexton might be an exception, but
    there are always exceptions.)

  * His film development techniques.  Basically he uses Tri-X in HC110,
    exposed at EI of 160, although he&#39;s switching to HP5 because he thinks
    that it&#39;s &amp;quot;smoother&amp;quot; and he can expose it at EI 300.  He uses hangers/
    tank development and uses extremely dilute HC110 for &amp;quot;extreme contraction
    and compensation&amp;quot; development, such as for his exquisite slit canyon
    images and his awe-inspiring series on the interiors of the great 
    cathedrals of England.  These go down to N-6 but the prints are 
    marvelous.

    I questioned them because I noticed in some test prints that Don showed
    featuring extreme contractions that highlight contrast was really low.
    The highlights printed along with the shadows on #2 paper but were very
    flat and lifeless.  I was puzzled because I knew that the highlights in
    their fine prints are lively and full, even in those cathedral interiors
    where I knew that extreme &amp;quot;-&amp;quot; development had been given.

    The answer was that you just have to use a higher grade of paper so as
    to get the sparkle in the highlights and then you live with having to 
    dodge the shadows and burn and flash the highlights.  

    Bruce went on to say that he considers it a major error to try to select
    paper grade based on what will allow both highlights and shadows to
    print without dodging or burning:  paper grade should be selected on
    the basis of local contrast and overall effect, not by an arbitrary 
    standard based on how much manipulation you have to do.  He said that
    when people do select contrast grade based on overall density range in 
    the negative, the prints seem to be flat and uninteresting.  I wouldn&#39;t
    make so general a statement about other&#39;s printing, but have noticed 
    that to be true in my own printing.

    This was very heartening for me as I used to think that I had problems
    with highlights because I had to burn them a lot if I chose a contrast 
    grade high enough to make local contrast look pleasing.  Now he&#39;s 
    confirmed what I&#39;ve been coming to realize on my own:  it&#39;s just in 
    the nature of the medium.  My &amp;quot;problem&amp;quot;, always having to do lots of
    burning of highlights, is this master printer&#39;s normal way of working.

    He had a &amp;quot;self-published&amp;quot; copy of his text book (which will be formally
    published in the near future) and it contained his development times for 
    both N +/- and compensating (extreme contraction).  I&#39;ll not post them 
    now as this is available from him in either the workshop or in his book.

    I bought a copy of this self-published version for $20 and think that
    it&#39;s worth far more.  The formally published version, complete with
    photographs and other illustrations, should be an outstanding text,
    delving into the philosophy of photography and composition as well
    as the mechanics of the process from exposure through mounting and
    spotting.

  * His sophisticated printing techniques.  We watched him print three new
    negatives for the first time.  In 1.5 hours he had created  what I
    consider to be a masterpiece, far beyond anything I&#39;ve ever accomplished,
    regardless of how many weeks I&#39;ve worked on a print.  He employed the 
    following techniques:

    - contrast grade selection (he works with Oriental Seagull graded and
      O.S. VC Select almost exclusively and for this print he used
      the graded).

    - Split developing to fine-tune contrast using both Selectol-Soft and
      Dektol on the same print.  (Using his personal system of diluting the
      stock solutions double what the manufacturor recommends and then
      doubling development time.)  With his long development times he doesn&#39;t
      worry about timing things.  Just goes with how the image looks and
      his own (very accurate) internal clock.  His intent is to develop
      to completion and as long as that happens he figures that timing isn&#39;t
      terribly important.  He also doesn&#39;t measure terribly accurately.  When 
      he thinks that the developer is getting a little exhausted, he just 
      picks up the jug of stock solution and &amp;quot;pours a bit in&amp;quot; without 
      measuring.  Yet he gets very consistent results.  Methinks that there&#39;s 
      a certain amount of intuitive genius going on here.  And maybe my 
      mechanistic, timed, measured approach is not really needed.  Might even 
      be distracting me from the important parts of printing?

      More than anything, I think that he was trying to wean us (or some of
      us? :-) from our mechanical aids and toward a more intuitive and
      sensing approach to photography.  He was very disgusted with the
      &amp;quot;focus gauge&amp;quot; that I&#39;ve been using, for example.  &amp;quot;Too mechanical!&amp;quot;
      &amp;quot;Gadgetry won&#39;t make your photos interesting!&amp;quot;  (Not real quotes,
      just attempts to capture the spirit of his comments.)

    - Dodging and burning using some really neat home-made burning tools.
      I&#39;ve used something similar but he&#39;s refined the idea.  I&#39;ll be
      making some for myself asap.

    - Selective pre-flashing of dense (in the negative) highlight areas.
      Hmmmmm.  Actually it was &amp;quot;post-flashing&amp;quot; as he gave the flashing
      exposure after the main exposure.

    - Ferricyanide (aka Farmer&#39;s Reducer) bleaching of selected areas of 
      the final print.  This, btw, is different from dodging.  Dodging reduces
      density overall in the area dodged.  Bleaching increases contrast by
      affecting lighter areas more than darker ones.  Select your tool
      as the individual case suggests.  Also, bleaching can affect a far
      smaller area than can dodging.

      I&#39;ve used this technique myself but never had any idea that you
      could do the things that this guy does.  The difference between
      the unbleached and the bleached print was subtle but dramatic.
      The difference between a &amp;quot;nice print&amp;quot; and a masterpiece.

      I&#39;ll not discuss bleaching in greater detail, but will note that both
      Bruce&#39;s textbook and Ansel Adam&#39;s &amp;quot;The Print&amp;quot; give good pointers to get
      you started.

    - Print washing:  he&#39;s somewhat cynical about the entire archival
      ruckus.  He pointed out that every time you turn around there&#39;s some
      new theory about what&#39;s going to produce an &amp;quot;archival print&amp;quot; and
      how to wash, etc.  Plus he has, as do I, minimal confidence in
      accelerated aging tests.  Putting it all together, he didn&#39;t quite
      say that &amp;quot;archival processing is a crock of s***&amp;quot;, but came very near
      to doing so.  And, being a fairly earthy person, that&#39;s pretty close
      to how he would have expressed it.

      I didn&#39;t really know quite what to expect from him but was pleased 
      and made to feel quite comfortable when 1)  He commented that &amp;quot;if
      this isn&#39;t an archival wash I don&#39;t really give a s***&amp;quot; and 2)  First
      thing at dinner was to get the carafe of red wine *NOW*!!.  This
      guy I can identify with.  :-)

      He puts his prints in a holding bath for anywhere from several hours
      to a day or so.  Ack!  We&#39;re leaching out all those brighteners,
      right?  He contends that he can see no difference between a print 
      soaked for 24 hours and one soaked for 10 minutes.  Personally I&#39;ve been
      thinking the same for some time now.  His prints glow.  Absolutely glow.  
      Unexcelled luminosity, especially in the highlights.  If this what a 
      print looks like after it&#39;s lost its brighteners, then you can remove 
      all brighteners from my paper, thank you very kindly.

      After the holding bath he selenium tones and uses an HCA bath.   BTW -
      he uses quite dilute selenium to minimize his use of heavy metals
      and soaks prints for a long time.  At that point he figures that there 
      can be virtually no fixer left in the paper.  So his final wash consists 
      of soaking each print individually in a try of water for at least 10 
      minutes and then pouring the water out.  He goes through this loop 3 
      times, squeegees the prints and air drys them on screens.

      Yup.  He doesn&#39;t own an archival print washer.  And here I just
      bought one!

      I also note that experts agree that using his &amp;quot;soak-drain&amp;quot; method
      of washing for an hour will produce an &amp;quot;archival wash&amp;quot;, whatever
      that means.  He&#39;s only doing so for 30 minutes, but with all the soaking
      that they&#39;re getting before the final wash, I strongly suspect that
      he&#39;s, unwittingly :-), getting an &amp;quot;archival wash&amp;quot;, whatever
      (once again) that is.

  - There is no drydown!  Basically, drydown is an artifact of viewing
    prints with dark-adapted eyes under overly bright lights.  He has an
    article on just this subject in a recent edition of Darkroom Techniques
    so I won&#39;t belabor it.  But he demonstrated his &amp;quot;two light&amp;quot; viewing system
    and it worked.  The print, wet, looked no better than the dry print did.
    I *did* think that I saw a little more detail in some highlights in the
    dry print, but the sense of luminosity seen in the wet print was not lost 
    in the dry print.  Highlights did not look darker in the dry print than
    in the wet one.

    Get the Darkroom Techniques article.  It&#39;ll explain it all.

    BTW - I was gratified to at last find in Bruce someone else who has 
    noticed the incredible amount that FB paper swells when wet and who has 
    theorized that some of the accentuation of detail in highlights of a dry 
    print may be due to the print shrinking back to its dry size, compacting
    all the little specks of black silver. I&#39;ve measured 16x20 paper 
    to be, indeed, 16x20 when dry but 16x20.625 when wet.  That&#39;s a large
    dimensional change.

  - In addition, many of his images are composites of two negatives.  We
    watched him create a new one.  A slit canyon image where two negatives
    had interesting stuff but also boring stuff.  He combined them into
    one print (using two enlargers and easels) so well that you could
    never guess that the image was &amp;quot;manufactured&amp;quot;.  He did it in less
    than two hours &amp;quot;from scratch&amp;quot;, never having printed it before, and did so
    without benefit of a scanner or computer.  :-)

* Don Kirby demonstrated using split filtration with VC paper to print
  a difficult negative (making a great image of a wheat field with storm
  clouds above it) and also printed an abstract in rock forms which he
  selectively bleached extensively, producing a huge change in the
  final image.  I was amazed.  I&#39;d never known that you could use bleach
  to effect that great a change in a print.

* Dry mounting of prints, including fixing defects (dimples and pimples) in 
  the mounted print.

* Spotting of dust specks and etching out of black marks (from scratches on
  negatives and from dust on negatives at exposure time) on prints.

Other things that I learned:
----- ------ ---- - -------
  * Paper storage:  he removes the inner light-tight envelop and just 
    trusts the box to protect the paper from light.  Seems to work just fine.
    I find the inner envelope to be a pain and put my paper in a paper safe
    while working with it.  But this is a pain if I&#39;m switching contrast
    grades often.  I&#39;m considering trying his techinique.  After all, all I
    have to lose is a few hundred dollars worth of paper, right?  :-)

  * One of the &amp;quot;bibles&amp;quot; often cited here in rec.photo, &amp;quot;Overexposed&amp;quot;, the book
    on photo darkroom hazards, contains at least one notable error.  One of 
    their previous students was director of the USC Medical School.  The issue 
    of toxicity of selenium toner came up during that workshop and when he got 
    home he had a research team look into it.  They concluded that selenium 
    powder is, indeed, extremely dangerous if the dust is inhaled.  As we
    all knew.  But in solution it will not penetrate the skin.  Period.  
    So I&#39;ve been wearing rubber gloves when toning for no reason.  Guess I 
    should probably refrain from drinking it, though.  :-)

    Although Bruce didn&#39;t go into the details, he also said that the 
    researchers found that the book contains several blatant errors on toxicity
    (all on the side of saying that things are more dangerous than they really
    are) and that it comments on the toxicity of at least one compound which 
    just doesn&#39;t exist.

    He notes that he&#39;s found that mixing developer, stopbath and fix produces
    an excellent fertilizer.  He used to dump it on his lawn and it 
    seemed to thrive on the mixture.

    He does, now, use a &amp;quot;Silver Magnet&amp;quot; to de-silver his fixer before 
    discarding it.

  * Get the hell out of PSA before you&#39;re permanently warped.  (PSA is 
    Photographic Society of America - the umbrella organization for many
    photo clubs).  He constantly criticized me for following too many &amp;quot;rules&amp;quot;,
    as dearly espoused by the judges in PSA monthly competitions.  Especially 
    wrt composition.  He said that I needed to get the **** out of PSA before 
    the damage is too extensive.  Then said to forget it as it was already too 
    late and I need to spend some time seriously working to unlearn the 
    bullbleep.  That I seem to have a lot of rules floating around in my
    head, especialy wrt composition, and that they were limiting me.


    I have now consorted with maybe half a dozen top fine-art photographers at 
    workshops and classes.  Not one has had anything good to say about this 
    organization.  I also note that I&#39;ve not heard of any member of PSA who
    has attained the stature of any of these top fine-art photographers.  I&#39;m 
    starting to detect a trend. 

  * I, as was true for many other students, need to be more bold in the
    darkroom.  Make big changes, instead of tiny incremental changes.  Print
    with brighter whites and blacker blacks (I.e. more contrast.)  They 
    thought that many of my prints were muddy and liked them more when I 
    reprinted them during the darkroom sessions to have far more contrast.  
    Personally I think that they&#39;re somewhat too contrasty, but I 
    see their point.   I can see some major re-interpreting in the immediate 
    future.

  * Bruce devotes a lot of time to questioning why we make photographs.  In 
    particular, before the critique each student was required to explain what
    he&#39;s trying to accomplish with his photographs.  Make an &amp;quot;artists
    statement&amp;quot;.  Then he might ask questions like:  &amp;quot;And what is this 
    photograph trying to say?&amp;quot;  &amp;quot;Hmmm.  It doesn&#39;t really say that to me.  
    Why?  What are you trying to tell me about this subject?&amp;quot;

    The critique lasted as long as necessary to discuss each student&#39;s work in
    as much depth as required.  There was no rush.  With 12 students, there
    were 16 hours devoted to the critique.  No sense of being rushed to get
    through.  Each student had the undivided attention of both instructors.
    I&#39;ve been to workshops where the &amp;quot;critique&amp;quot; took place in a three hour
    period for all 15 students.  And was virtually useless.  This was the
    opposite.  Not necessarily completely comfortable but highly beneficial.

    I learned, maybe more than anything else in this workshop, that I need
    to work on the philosophy of my photography.  I don&#39;t think that I can
    grow much more just by exposing film and making prints.  I need to 
    understand, and to be able to verbalize, just what it is that excites me
    and how and what I want to communicate about it to the viewer.  This
    is very difficult for me but I&#39;m now convinced that I must work on it.

    One guy was asking Bruce what was wrong that he couldn&#39;t make an
    exciting print from a particular negative.  Bruce kept asking him what
    it was that he liked about the scene and what he was trying to 
    communicate about it.  The guy couldn&#39;t articulate it and was frustrated
    because Bruce wouldn&#39;t say &amp;quot;burn here and dodge there&amp;quot;.  Bruce maintained
    that the reason that he couldn&#39;t make an interesting print was because
    he didn&#39;t know why he was printing it and the student kept saying
    &amp;quot;I don&#39;t want to talk about composition, I want to talk about the
    technicalities.&amp;quot;  Interesting conversation.

    During my &amp;quot;artists statement&amp;quot; I said, rather apologetically, that I was a 
    little embarrassed by my photos as everyone else&#39;s had been a relative 
    homogeneous body of work whereas mine were &amp;quot;all over the map&amp;quot; - a still 
    life, interior architectural, &amp;quot;grand vista&amp;quot;, detail of a pond and 
    grasses, ...  Bruce asked first what was wrong with that? (I suspect
    that he detected a &amp;quot;rule&amp;quot;) and then said that he thought that there was 
    more commonality than I was recognizing.  He didn&#39;t explicitly state what 
    it was, but I have a sense that he&#39;s right.  And I think that I need to 
    figure out what it is in order to continue to grow.  I will.

  * If you don&#39;t care about your subject then you&#39;ll never make an interesting
    photo of it.  I&#39;ve been coming to this realization on my own for a while
    but we talked about it considerably.  I have now completely stopped 
    &amp;quot;exposing film because I&#39;m here, even though I&#39;m not really finding 
    anything super interesting&amp;quot;.  I realized that Bruce and Don are
    intensely involved with everything that they photograph and it shows
    in their prints.  I think that I must feel the same or there&#39;s no point
    to bothering.  As I said, I was tending in this direction before the
    workshop but this crystallized things for me.

  * Shun rules!  Avoid rules!  Break rules!  Don&#39;t do rules!  Down with rules!
    Don&#39;t justify your compositional choices by citing rules!  We don&#39;t *like* 
    rules!

  * Bruce prices his prints based on size, although he thinks that this is
    silly.  He does so because the world expects it.  But he only prints 
    each image at one size, the size which he thinks &amp;quot;works&amp;quot; best for that
    image.  He considers choice of image size to be an integral part of the 
    creative process.  

    He dislikes the &amp;quot;limited edition&amp;quot; concept and considers his bowing to the 
    demands of galleries and starting a few limited editions to have been a 
    really big mistake.

There was much, much more to be learned in this class and from these 
people.  However, by no means do I think that I&#39;ve &amp;quot;gone to the mountain and 
come down with the commandments&amp;quot;.  Nor would Bruce or Don want students to feel
that way.  What I&#39;ve learned is a little bit about how two extraordinary 
photographers work, think and feel and now I can incorporate these into
my own way of working as works best for me.  This is what they want the
students to do.  This workshop was an outstanding opportunity for growth and 
I cannot recommend it too highly.



View or add comments
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>http://lflf.surge.sh</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lflf.surge.sh</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Large Format Photography: Bellows extension exposure compensation&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;bellows-extension-exposure-compensation&#34;&gt;Bellows extension exposure compensation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Compiled by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.terragalleria.com/&#34;&gt;Q.-Tuan Luong&lt;/a&gt; for &lt;a href=&#34;.&#34;&gt;the
Large Format Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;formulas&#34;&gt;Formulas&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;mailto:bg174@FreeNet.Carleton.CA&#34;&gt;Michael Gudzinowicz:&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Multiply the marked f-stop by (1 + M), where M is the magnification on
the ground glass. Alternatively, mark &amp;amp; measure the position of the lens
at infinity focus, and then measure the ground glass to lens distance at
close focus. Divide the total extension at close focus by the former
number (near infinity, which should be close to the focal length for
most LF lenses), and the resultant f-stop factor will be the same (or
close enough).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;By &lt;a href=&#34;mailto:rkoser@worldnet.att.net&#34;&gt;Richard Koser&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the bellows is extended beyond infinity focus for close-up work, an
exposure FACTOR must be determined and applied. Two convenient ways of
finding the FACTOR are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;a) When the camera is focused at infinity, note a point on the camera
and another on the lens (e.g., diaphragm) such that the distance between
them is equal to the focal length (call it F). Then, when the bellows is
extended for close-up focus, the extension between those two points will
be greater than F (call it E). The exposure factor will be (E/F)
squared. For example, extending the bellows to twice-F to focus for an
object-to-image ratio of 1:1, the FACTOR will be 4.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;b) Measure the object width or height (call it O) and that of it&amp;rsquo;s image
on the ground-glass (call it o). The exposure factor will be (o/O+1)
squared. For example, focusing for an object-to-image ratio of 1:1, the
FACTOR will be (&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt; + 1) squared, or 4.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Applying the FACTOR:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If 4 times the exposure is required (per the examples above), open up
the lens 2 stops or increase the exposure time 4-fold.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two complications often arise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Firstly, it is hard, maybe even impossible, to measure bellows extension
when using swings, tilts, rise/fall and combinations thereof; thus the
object-to-image measurements are useful (indeed, Calumet offers a handy
plastic template, based on that principle, calibrated directly in
stops).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Secondly, FACTORs of 2, 4, 8, etc. obviously correspond to 1, 2, 3, etc.
stops; what about a FACTOR of 3?? To convert FACTORs to stops, use a
scientific calculator; (log FACTOR/log 2) or (ln FACTOR/ln 2) equals
stops. For a FACTOR of 3, (log 3/log 2) equals (.48/.3) equals 1.6
stops.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;By &lt;a href=&#34;mailto:roy@harrington.com&#34;&gt;Roy Harrington&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The formula (Extension/FocalLength) **2 is basically correct. The
focal length is basically the distance from the center of lens (where
the aperture is) to the film plane when the lens is focused at infinity.
So a 12inch lens will have 12 inches of bellows when focused at
infinity. You move the lens farther away from the film in order to focus
on something closer. The new distance of the lens from the film is the
&amp;ldquo;extension&amp;rdquo; (not the distance to what your focused on). For instance if
you move the lens to 24 inches from the film, objects another 24 inches
in front of the lens will be in focus. The image will be the same size
as the object i.e. 1:1 magnification and the bellows compensation will
be (&lt;sup&gt;24&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;12&lt;/sub&gt;)**2 = 4 or 2 stops more exposure needed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Personally, I like to do the calculation directly with the aperture and
thereby eliminate the square in the formula. For example the 12 inch
lens at 24 inch extension just doubles the effective aperture number so
f/16 is really f/32. Its very easy to use the aperture scale on the
front of the lens as a visual aid in this calculation. If you had an
8inch lens f/8 just becomes f/N when you have N inches of extension.
Many of the lenses have &lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; stop marks and if you can interpolate
between the full stop markings and use inchs, mm, cm etc you can fairly
easily figure out what compensation to make without a calculator or any
other fancy device.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some examples if my description is not clear. &lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; stop values approx:
f/8,9,10 f/11,12.5,14 f/16,18,20 f/22,25,28 f/32,36,40 f/45&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;Lens:        Extension:      Compens:
8in          12.5in           1 1/3 stops  -- f/8 to f/12.5
180mm        220mm            2/3 stops    -- f/18 to f/22
125mm        200mm            1 1/3 stops  -- f/12.5 to f/20
5in          7in              1 stop   (think f/10 to f/14)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The nice thing about this is the change can be made right on the lens
without even counting the &lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; stops.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;computing-tricks&#34;&gt;Computing tricks&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;using-the-relationships-between-f-stops&#34;&gt;Using the relationships between f/stops&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;By &lt;a href=&#34;mailto:nickdc@mail.erols.com&#34;&gt;Nicholas F. Hanks&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;re going to use the relationships between f/stops to determine the
additional exposure needed when extending the bellows. First, consider
the bellows at infinity as an f/stop type of number. That is, say your
120mm lens is &amp;ldquo;f/&amp;ldquo;120, but to bring things down to familiar f/&amp;rsquo;s, well
divide everything by 10, so call it &amp;ldquo;f/&amp;ldquo;12. We&amp;rsquo;re now dealing in
centimeters, but it doesn&amp;rsquo;t much matter. Let&amp;rsquo;s say you move your bellows
out to 160 mm. We&amp;rsquo;ll call that &amp;ldquo;f/&amp;ldquo;16. What this says is that we&amp;rsquo;ve gone
from &amp;ldquo;f/&amp;ldquo;12 to &amp;ldquo;f/&amp;ldquo;16 which is about one stop. So we&amp;rsquo;ve doubled our
exposure requirements. Either open up one stop or double your time.
Similarly, if we extend to 240mm it becomes &amp;ldquo;f/&amp;ldquo;24, which is two stops
more exposure or four times the time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This becomes a little confusing when working with odd numbers. A 90 mm
lens extended to 130mm is the difference between f/9 and f/13 which is
somewhere between familiar territory. Take a look down at the f/ scale
and make an estimate, and it&amp;rsquo;s probably good enough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s also hard to know where to measure to. It should be from the iris
to film plane, but sometimes the infinity setting doesn&amp;rsquo;t seem to
measure what I would expect it to based on the lens&amp;rsquo; focal length. It&amp;rsquo;s
best just to measure at infinity, then measure at the extension and make
the calculation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the method seems whimsical, it is based on sound engineering
principles. Remember that the f/stop is the ratio of the diameter of the
iris divided into the focal length. An f/8 with a 120mm lens would be
15mm in diameter. However, the amount of light is dependent on the area
(pi x r\^2). The area or a 15mm hole is 175.7 square mm. To double the
light you would double the area to 353.4 sq.mm. This gives us a 21.2mm
diameter hole which gives an f/ of 120mm/21.2mm which is f/5.6. If you
do the calculations for f/4 you&amp;rsquo;ll see that the hole is twice the
diameter (8 divided by 4) but four times the light area. Conversely,
f/16 is &lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; the hole diameter but &lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt; the light. Notice that there&amp;rsquo;s a
square relationship here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what?!!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As it turns, as you move the lens out from the film plane, the amount of
area on which light falls also increases in size and thus decreases in
density by a square relationship as well. Thus, as you move a 120mm lens
to 240mm, although twice the distance, the area on which light projects
is 4 times as much (2 squared) resulting in &lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt; the density.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, the f/ scale on the lens with which we are all familiar provides
us with a handy scale showing a square relationship which we can also
use as a key for our bellows extension.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;a-fast-method-to-calculate-bellows-extension-factor&#34;&gt;A Fast Method to Calculate Bellows Extension Factor&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;By &lt;a href=&#34;mailto:john12420@msn.com&#34;&gt;John A. Cook&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is an old saying that as photographers get older they don?t get
any better, but they do get faster. During my many years as a studio
product photographer, I never had the luxury of spending a lot of time
agonizing over technique. There was always a budget and a deadline
nipping at my heels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of necessity, I learned many shortcuts to get through the mountains of
products I was assigned to shoot. This is one of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This method for calculating bellows extension is predicated on the
relationship between the extension of the bellows (in inches) and common
f-stop numbers. It requires no fancy gadgets to purchase nor algebraic
formulae to memorize. You don?t even need batteries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Step One:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Make a permanent, durable list of the following F-numbers. (You can also
find them on your light meter.) Note that they are shown in &lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; stops.
Those with asterisks indicate &amp;ldquo;whole&amp;rdquo; stops:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;3.5
4 *
4.5
5
5.6 *
6.3
7.1
8 *
9
10
11 *
13
14
16 *
18
20
22 *
25
28
32 *
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Step Two:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Calculate the focal length of your lenses in inches, rather than
millimeters, by dividing by 25.4. Photography is not an exact science -
it?s okay to round off these numbers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;90mm = 3.5&amp;rdquo; 150mm = 6&amp;rdquo; 210mm = 8.26&amp;rdquo; 240mm = 9.4&amp;rdquo; 300mm = 11.8&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Step three:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you are ready to make the exposure, measure the view camera?s
extension from the ground glass to the lens board in inches. Measure
from the center of the lens board to the center of the ground glass so
as to not introduce errors from extreme swings and/or tilts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Compare this distance to the focal length (or flange distance) of the
lens and relate these two numbers to the above list of f-stops. Their
difference will indicate the number of stops you must increase the
exposure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example: a 210mm or 8&amp;rdquo; lens with 11&amp;rdquo; of bellows requires a one stop
exposure increase (the difference between f8 and f11).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A 240mm or 9.4&amp;rdquo; lens with 14&amp;rdquo; of bellows requires a one and one- third
stop increase (difference between f9 and f14).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A 90mm or 3.5&amp;rdquo; lens with 4.5&amp;rdquo; of bellows requires a two-thirds stop
exposure increase. And so on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This method is not accurate for telephoto lenses, whose optical center
is not near the lens board. To ensure always having a bellows measuring
device handy, I sewed a cloth tailor&amp;rsquo;s tape measure to the edge of my
focusing cloth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;devices&#34;&gt;Devices&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;a-tape&#34;&gt;A tape&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Making a &amp;ldquo;custom&amp;rdquo; tape measure means you can leave the calculator at
home. Stanley makes a very small (approx 1.5&amp;rdquo; x 1.5&amp;rdquo; x .3&amp;rdquo;) version of
their spring-retracting &amp;ldquo;carpenter&amp;rsquo;s&amp;rdquo; tape measure. Do the calculations,
(once) mark the back of the tape, and you can find exposure comp in a
few seconds. It is especially useful for telephoto lens designs that
don&amp;rsquo;t conform to the usual exposure comp formulas. I have one marked at
&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; stop increments using different colored marks for each lens. Works
great. &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;mailto:%0Aellinger@umich.edu&#34;&gt;Chris Ellinger&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;a-fixed-scale&#34;&gt;A fixed scale&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where I only have one lens, a 127mm (5 inch), I figured that a simple
scale on the bed next to the focusing rails calibrated in both stops and
time increase would do the job. Probably many people have already
thought of this where it is so simple but where this is all new to me,
ignorance is bliss. I used a paint program on the computer with the
measured values printed on heavy card stock which I cut to size. The
scale is held in place with the three screws that hold the bed together
so there is no modification of the camera and it is simple to change. If
I had two lenses a second scale could be put on the other side as well,
three lenses and I&amp;rsquo;m in trouble, but I probably couldn&amp;rsquo;t afford them
anyway. I&amp;rsquo;ve attached a JPEG picture to show the first revision I made
before I noticed where the screws would be so I&amp;rsquo;ve moved stuff slightly
so the screws don&amp;rsquo;t cover some of the printing on the scale. With
modification this could be used on any large format camera. &lt;strong&gt;Richard&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;bellows-scale.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;geoff-bowker-s-bellows-extension-charting-package&#34;&gt;Geoff Bowker&amp;rsquo;s bellows extension charting package&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is &lt;a href=&#34;Bell_Ext.xls&#34;&gt;a small excel spreadsheet&lt;/a&gt; that will calculate f
stop corrections for any lenses. just feed in the focal length and it
will produce a grid of f stop corrections and also a useful graph in &lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;
stop increments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;philipp-salzgeber-s-quickdisc&#34;&gt;Philipp Salzgeber&amp;rsquo;s QuickDisc&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.salzgeber.at/disc/index.html&#34;&gt;QuickDisc&lt;/a&gt; is a simple and
useful tool. The use of the QuickDisc involves no calculation, it is
lightweight, easy to replace and free for personal use. It consists of
two pieces of cardboard, the disc, and the measuring strip.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.greenspun.com/com/qtluong/photography/lf/bellows-factor.html&#34;&gt;View or add
comments&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>http://lflf.surge.sh</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lflf.surge.sh</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Large format cameras: reviews of the Bender Camera Kit&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-bender-camera-kit&#34;&gt;The Bender Camera Kit&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Compiled by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.terragalleria.com/&#34;&gt;Q.-Tuan Luong&lt;/a&gt; for &lt;a href=&#34;.&#34;&gt;the
Large Format Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Contents:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Review by &lt;a href=&#34;mailto:bjs@oes.amdahl.com&#34;&gt;Barry Sherman&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Review by &lt;a href=&#34;mailto:geoff@fribble.eecs.wsu.edu&#34;&gt;Geoff Allen&lt;/a&gt;, and
compilation of other info&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Link to the manufacturer&amp;rsquo;s site: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.benderphoto.com/&#34;&gt;Bender
Photographics&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;a-review-by-barry-sherman&#34;&gt;A review by Barry Sherman&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m of very mixed minds regarding the Bender kit. It&amp;rsquo;s definitely cheap
and definitely light. Both good things! But I think that there are some
very serious down-sides. Not too long ago the Tachihara cost about \$450
while it cost about \$250 all told to build the Bender kit and I&amp;rsquo;d have
recommended buying the Tachihara unless one absolutely required longer
bellows extension than it can provide or simply couldn&amp;rsquo;t scrape up the
extra \$200. Nowadays the Tachihara is up to something like \$600 or
\$650 and \$400 is a bigger jump in the price so I&amp;rsquo;d be a little more
hesitant about recommending it over the Bender. So. What I like about
the Bender:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s light.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s cheap.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s not bad to build. I have a lot of woodworking experience and
that helped, but I&amp;rsquo;ve no doubt that someone with none could build
one. They&amp;rsquo;d have to think about things a little more, but it&amp;rsquo;s
doable. I think that I spent around 30 hours building mine.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You can have unlimited bellows extension. The &amp;ldquo;standard&amp;rdquo; is
something like 16 inches but the bellows will allow about 22 inches
and you can buy a longer monorail for just a very few dollars as
it&amp;rsquo;s just a piece of square aluminum extrusion. It&amp;rsquo;s easy to cut one
off shorter, also, to suit your needs. If you wanted *really* long
bellows extension, Jay Bender would be happy to supply a really long
bellows and monorail and there you have it. Probably cost less than
\$100, compared to the \$150 for an extension monorail plus \$500
for an extension bellows that I&amp;rsquo;d have to spend for my Arca Swiss.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Accessories are cheap. The kit for the bag bellows cost around \$30.
I spent \$500 buying a leather wide-angle (not a bag) for my Arca
Swiss. It works wonderfully, never folding itself into the image
area like the Bender one does. Bur a savings of \$470 is not to be
sneered at. (Arca Swiss also makes a synthetic wide angle bellows
for &lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; that price but I couldn&amp;rsquo;t locate one when I got the camera
and, at that time, there was no U.S. distributor for them so I took
what I could get. Now that I&amp;rsquo;ve absorbed the shock of the price I
really love the bellows.) When I found that I was using more
movements with my 210mm lens than the standard bellows could
accomodate, Jay Bender made a special bag bellows kit for an
enormous one that would accomodate extreme movements and charged
\$35 for it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I don&amp;rsquo;t like about it:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Some of the parts are less robust than I&amp;rsquo;d prefer. There are three
&amp;ldquo;monorail riders&amp;rdquo;. Two attach the front and rear standards while the
third has the screw hole for attaching to a tripod and attaches the
monorail to the tripod head. I think that this one piece is grossly
too weak. I accidentally left the fore-and-aft lock on the pan head
too loose and the head/camera rotated forward until it stopped
abruptly at the end of its travel. The piece of wood shattered,
depositing the rest of the camera on the ground 6 inches away from a
mountain river in full spring flood. A friend with a machine shop
fabricated replacement monorail riders from Delrin, a space-age
plastic that&amp;rsquo;s pretty well indestructable. But at normal machine
shop rates of \$50 per hour, it would have cost me several hundred
dollars for the job had I not had friends do it free. In all
honesty, though, I have to say that I&amp;rsquo;m the only person who I&amp;rsquo;ve
heard of having this trouble. I also found that if I inserted a
heavy Polaroid 545 holder, the rear standard kind of sagged under
the weight. I had to reinforce part of it to eliminate the sagging.&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The monorail riders, if fitted so as to be loose enough to slide
back and forth for focusing, have a tendency to rotate just a little
when you lock them in place after focusing. You turn a clamping knob
and the torsion of turning it makes the rider rotate just a little
in a fore-and aft direction wrt the monorail and around the clamping
bolt. This is irritating but not terrible as:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Usually you&amp;rsquo;re focusing partway into the scene instead of on one
specific object so a little slop isn&amp;rsquo;t the end of the world.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You get used to it and learn to compensate when focusing so that
it rotates into exactly the right spot when you clamp it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;With practice you can minimize the movement anyway.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not a big thing, but it&amp;rsquo;s irritating.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s one lock knob for both shift and swing movements. Not a big
deal for most outdoor landscape photographers. But if you&amp;rsquo;re using
both shift and swing, then it can be irritating. First you set the
back to be parallel to the facade of the building that you&amp;rsquo;re
photographing. Now you swing the front to be parallel to the back.
But swinging the front changes where the camera lens is pointing so
you need to shift one of the standards a little to re-frame the
scene. But when you loosen the knob to do the shift you lose the
shift that you just painstakingly set using the loupe on the ground
glass. The solution is to only set the front swing roughly at first,
not bothering with the loupe. Then set the shift to get proper
framing. Then use the loupe to fine-tune the swing. Not a big thing,
but it&amp;rsquo;s irritating.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve had occasional troubles with light leaks developing around the
perimeter of the bellows. Care must be taken when changing bellows
to ensure that the little &amp;lsquo;L&amp;rsquo; screws that hold the bellows in place
are clamping firmly.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So. I think that the Bender is a fully usable camera and I&amp;rsquo;ve taken some
of my very best, and best sellling, photos with it. But I do prefer the
convenience of a real store-boughten camera. I&amp;rsquo;ve kept it and take it on
trips to carry for longer walks, but it has to be a fairly lengthy or
strenuous hike before I&amp;rsquo;ll abandon the convenience of the Arca Swiss.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;review-by-geoff-allen&#34;&gt;Review by Geoff Allen&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;DISCLAIMER: The only other 4x5 camera I&amp;rsquo;ve used is a Linhof
Technikardan, which is an amazingly cool camera, but costs a couple
orders of magnitude more than the Bender. I&amp;rsquo;ve never used a field camera
or a monstrous studio camera. You might need to take such things into
consideration as you read this. Also, I have no connection whatsoever
with Bender Photographic, other than as a very satisfied customer. As I
see it&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;executive-summary&#34;&gt;Executive Summary&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s a great camera and loads of fun. You don&amp;rsquo;t have to spend loads of
money for a view camera if you&amp;rsquo;ve got a few weeks of time available. (It
took me a year to build mine, but I actually only spent about three
weeks of actual effort.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;pros&#34;&gt;Pros&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cheap.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Movements limited only by lens coverage. You can very easily reach the
limits of most any lens with this camera, since the only physical
restriction on tilts and swings is the bellows, and rises and shifts are
a couple of inches in all directions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Light. The Bender is half the weight of the Technikardan. This should be
an important consideration when I&amp;rsquo;m trudging high in the Tetons. A three
pound camera vs. a six pound camera is no contest when one is climbing a
mountain. :\^)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You build it yourself. Pride of ownership. It&amp;rsquo;s loads of fun to tell
people you built a camera and see what reactions you get! Chances are
you&amp;rsquo;ll be the first in your neighborhood to do this! Some folks might
consider the need to build the camera a con, of course. :\^)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Attractive. I think my Bender is more attractive than donl&amp;rsquo;s
Technikardan, and I&amp;rsquo;ve told him so. :\^)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cheap.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Light.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;cons&#34;&gt;Cons&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You need to build it. Can also be considered a pro. :\^)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Friction focusing only. I&amp;rsquo;ve had no problems with this, though. Use a
loupe and stop down to f/32 or so and you&amp;rsquo;ll be fine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Little brass l-screws are used to hold the lensboard, back, and bellows
in place. I replaced them all. On my camera, I hold the lensboard and
bellows in place with some plastic window screen retainer clips. Lots
nicer. And for the back, I found some catch locks that hold it more
securely than I think the l-screws would have.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Movements aren&amp;rsquo;t ``calibrated.&amp;rdquo; But if you care about such things,
there&amp;rsquo;s nothing preventing you from marking appropriate calibrations on
the standard yourself. (There are levels for the back provided with the
kit.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Things get really tight when using a 90mm lens. With a 90mm lens, the
bag bellows is essential, as the standards are about as close together
as they can physically get. With a 135mm lens, I find I still need the
bag bellows. At 210mm, I can use the regular bellows. For anything
shorter than 90mm, I&amp;rsquo;m sure you&amp;rsquo;d need to rig up a recessed lens board.
So, if you&amp;rsquo;ve been drooling over that 58mm Super Angulon, you&amp;rsquo;d better
drool over another camera to go with it. ;\^)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;usage-notes&#34;&gt;Usage notes&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For using my camera, I leave the monorail on the tripod. This provides
the next best thing to a quick release (maybe even better, because you
can hold the camera with two hands while putting it on the tripod). When
taking a picture, I just haul the camera out of my carrying bag and
slide one standard onto the monorail on either side of the tripod mount.
For the 90mm, both standards have to go on the same side of the tripod
mount, because you can&amp;rsquo;t get them close enough otherwise. I honestly
can&amp;rsquo;t remember which way I configure things for the 135mm lens. I think
it&amp;rsquo;s the same as the 90mm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Removing the camera from the monorail also has the advantage of making
the camera fit into a carrying bag more easily. It&amp;rsquo;s certainly not as
compact as a Technikardan, though.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I keep both standards all the way down in their rise/fall adjustments
for their ``zero&amp;rdquo; position. This keeps the camera a little more
compact without sacrificing any movements, since front fall can simply
be accomplished by back rise. This means one less movement to zero when
you set the camera up (well, actually, two movements, I suppose).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;what-else-you-d-need-besides-the-camera&#34;&gt;What else you&amp;rsquo;d need besides the camera&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though the Bender is tempting as a low-cost way of getting into large
format photography, you should realize that the couple of hundred
dollars you&amp;rsquo;ll spend for the camera is the beginning, not the end, of
your capital outlay. Besides the camera, you&amp;rsquo;ll need:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Film holders &amp;ndash; You&amp;rsquo;ll use a lot less film when shooting 4x5, but I&amp;rsquo;d
still recommend having several film holders around. Maybe 5 as a
minimum. How many you want is a trade-off between how often you&amp;rsquo;re
willing to reload, how many different kinds of film you want available,
and how much you&amp;rsquo;re willing to carry. (Large format film holders hold
two sheets of film per holder.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lens(es) &amp;ndash; Here&amp;rsquo;s where you&amp;rsquo;ll spend the money. I don&amp;rsquo;t know enough
about older designs to make any recommendations, if you&amp;rsquo;re looking for
used lens deals. In newer models, Schneider, Rodenstock and Nikon are
all good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Loupe &amp;ndash; perhaps somewhat optional, but extremely helpful for getting
the focus right on. Make sure it&amp;rsquo;s a loupe that works with a ground
glass, since the image is a few mm from the end of the loupe, due to the
thickness of the glass. A loupe designed for viewing slides won&amp;rsquo;t work,
unless you can adjust the focus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A carrying bag for everything. You might try a generic daypack in the
\$100 range, rather than a \$400-500 ``photo&amp;rdquo; backpack. I use a
generic pack without any problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bag Bellows &amp;ndash; you almost certainly want to buy this when you buy the
camera kit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meter &amp;ndash; remember, this is a truly mechanical camera; there&amp;rsquo;s no meter.
You&amp;rsquo;ll have to supply your own. Any handheld meter you know how to use
will work fine. If you want to get into spot metering, check out Ansel
Adams&amp;rsquo; book, _The_Negative_.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Developing &amp;ndash; this could be where the problem lies. Your options
include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A custom lab that will develop/print the film for you.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A friend with a darkroom and 4x5 enlarger you can borrow.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A rental darkroom.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Your own darkroom and 4x5 enlarger.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Developing the film isn&amp;rsquo;t too big a deal. You can use the Jobo reels and
tanks designed for 4x5 film with or without a Jobo processor. Phil Davis
also markets his ``BTZS&amp;rdquo; developing tubes that I&amp;rsquo;ve read fairly good
things about. For printing anything, though, you&amp;rsquo;re going to need a 4x5
enlarger (you could contact print as a start). But you could just shoot
chrome film for a while to get used to the camera.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wholeheartedly recommend the Bender camera. You&amp;rsquo;ll trade some slick
features of something like a Technikardan for a lighter, though more
bulky, camera. I really found little practical difference in using the
Bender or a Technikardan. The pictures I took with donl&amp;rsquo;s Technikardan
and my Bender are of equal quality. Building it is fun (and I have no
experience in woodworking, so if I can do it, anyone can) &amp;ndash; just go
slowly and methodically and everything will be all right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;additional-info&#34;&gt;Additional info&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are comments from others that I&amp;rsquo;ve collected. I&amp;rsquo;ve occasionally
added comments enclosed in square brackets &amp;ndash; &amp;lsquo;[]&amp;rsquo; &amp;ndash; and signed with
my initials, &amp;lsquo;gwa&amp;rsquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;~~~~~
From: donl@glass.wpd.sgi.com (donl mathis)
Subject: Bender View Camera Kits
Date: 5 Apr 90 22:59:24 GMT
Organization: Silicon Graphics, Inc., Mountain View, CA

A couple of people sent me email asking for more information about the
Bender view camera kit i mentioned, one of them suggesting a general
posting might be of interest.  I talk too much, so this is rather long;
my apologies to those who are not interested.

The 4x5 kit is about $150, the 8x10 is about $250.  The primary
difference, other than size, is that the 4x5 has interchangeable
bellows (because you typically need a bag bellows with short lenses in
4x5, but not in 8x10), and more movements on the rear standard (i
believe it&#39;s built more like the front standard, where the 8x10 has
tilt and swing only, with no shift or rise).

[The prices are now $190 and $290.  The front and rear standards on the
4x5 are basically identical, except the rear standard is a little wider.
You have the same movements available on both standards. -- gwa]

It&#39;s all made of cherry.  You receive, essentially, a rather small box
full of sticks and other parts (hardware, ground glass, bellows,
etc.).  Complex wood parts are glued up out of simple rectangular
pieces, rather than having been shaped in a more sophisticated way at
the factory.  This basic principle keeps the production simple (i.e.
inexpensive), but means you have to do some fancy gluing and clamping
to get it built.  I am not a woodworker, though i know the basics.  I
had no trouble building the kit, except for one (count them, 1)
dimension that didn&#39;t quite work out quite right on the back of the
8x10 (which is built differently than the 4x5 so is a non-issue
there).  Something along the lines of &amp;quot;if this is here, and that goes
there, then this overhang is not sufficient to glue that thing to.&amp;quot;
Nothing serious; a little cleverness makes everything fit.

[I had no problems with the 4x5, and I know nothing about woodworking!
-- gwa]

Start with as many C-clamps as you can find.  I believe i had 16 -- 8
little ones and 8 big ones.  I used little patches of cut up mat board
as pads to keep the clamps from marring the wood.  If you have lots of
clamps, you can let one glued and clamped assembly dry while you&#39;re
working on the next.

[I second the motion on clamps.  If you can get some of those clamps
which hold a corner, they will be quite useful as well. -- gwa]

I used a palm sander to round off all of the corners.  I think it makes
it look a LOT better than the simple, square-edged version pictured in
the ad.  I also stained it dark mahogany before varnishing.  Finishing,
though, is entirely your option.  It can be as simple as a little oil.

[I left mine square, and stained it a golden oak.  Very attractive.  I
used some spray-on stain which requires no wiping.  Very convenient for
all those nooks and crannies.  -- gwa]

Gluing the bellows on the 8x10 was something i approached with fear and
trepidation, because it is this big old floppy thing that you can&#39;t get
a hold of and won&#39;t cooperate, and the dimensions of the flap on either
end don&#39;t really match size of the wooden frame they are supposed to be
glued to.  I called Bender and we chatted for a bit, during which time
he told me it looks harder than it is -- just give it a shot, it will
be fine.  So i did, using some (non-from-the-kit) angle and straight
brackets to help hold things together as i worked my way around.  It
was a little messy, with epoxy oozing out here and there, but otherwise
not bad.

[The 4x5 bellows is no big deal. -- gwa]

The design is such that certain parts (lens board, removeable back,
etc.) are held on by these little brass screw L-pins.  I thought they
looked a little weak; i ended up making changes such that i didn&#39;t need
them.  The given lens board, which is 6x6 i believe, is a piece of
black acrylic sheet.  Additional boards are available (or make your
own), and you use one per lens, as usual with view cameras.  The design
says that you twist the L pins to catch the edges and hold everything
in place.  I made a lens board from a heavier sheet of black acrylic
and a few additional pieces, using a Bridgeport mill, that serves only
to accept my Linhof Technikarden lens boards, which are more like 4x4,
thus permitting me to swap lenses between cameras when appropriate.
The rear film holder frame was also designed to be held on with the
L-pins.  It must be removable so that you can orient the film
vertically or horizontally as appropriate.  Rather than use the pins, i
drilled a hole in each corner of it, and put studs in the back of the
camera that poke through the holes, with a little knob on each one.  I
used 1/4&amp;quot; studs, because all of the other studs in the camera are 1/4&amp;quot;,
and they were MUCH too large and the holes ended up being rather
crude.  If i were to do it again, i would use rather small screw-in
studs to hold the back on.  They must be carefully placed so that the
back fits both vertically and horizontally over the same studs, i.e.
they must be really square.

[Some catch locks can do the job of holding the back in place also. 
Poke around in the fastener section of your favorite hardware store and
see what they&#39;ve got that looks good. -- gwa]

There were other wire pins used as pivots here and there; i replaced
them with heavier brass rod, because i like to over-engineer
everything.

They suggest gluing the various clamping studs into their respective
knobs, and screwing them into the T-nuts embedded in the parts of the
camera.  I decided i would rather strip the threads in the knob than in
the T-nuts, because the knob can be replaced, but the T-nut can&#39;t.  You
can&#39;t always glue the studs into the T-nuts because then you can&#39;t get
the camera apart if you ever need to, because of the way it is
assembled.  Usually, a healthy twist on the stud will drive it home in
the T-nut where it runs into the backing piece of wood, and it will
stay there as you loosen and tighten the knob.

[I didn&#39;t glue any of mine, and it seems to have made no difference. --gwa]

The camera focuses by loosening a clamp and sliding the front standard
back and forth on the rail, which is a 1x1 square aluminum tube.  With
the long lenses used on an 8x10, i found it a bit difficult to reach
when standing behind the camera and looking at the ground glass.  The
rear standard of the 8x10 has a pivot in the middle (at the base), and
studs with knobs running in arced slots at the left and right to clamp
it in place as you do your swings.  I left out the pivot, and enlarged
the slots a bit so the whole rear standard could actually be moved
forward and backward an inch or so, as well as swinging as necessary.
This gives me an inch or so of focusing range at the rear standard,
right there in front of me, so i don&#39;t have to reach out around to the
front of the camera when tuning the focus.  It gets a bit difficult to
reach all the way up there when using a 20&amp;quot; lens!  Standing behind the
camera, you just can&#39;t reach.  I&#39;m not sure how the 4x5 is set up;
hopefully, you can slide the rear standard and focus there.

[Yep.  Both standards slide easily.  I generally rough-focus by moving
the front and fine-focus by moving the back.  -- gwa]

I don&#39;t think there were any other major points; all in all it was
pretty fun to build, and is actually quite easy to use.

I picked up an old Turner-Reich triple convertible, 300-500-600mm focal
lengths, f/7, in an old slow shutter that i had to recalibrate (1/2,
1/4, 1/8, 1/12, and 1/30 second, with the all-important B and T
settings!).  The front and rear parts of the lens unscrew; using both
of them gives you a 12&amp;quot; (300mm) lens, which is equivalent to 150mm in
4x5, and is sort of normal, but actually slightly wide.  Using one or
the other have alone, behind the shutter, gives you 500 or 600mm focal
length, with significantly reduced image quality, which means you&#39;d
better stop way down if you expect a decent image.  Actually not a
terrific lens, but it was sort of cheap, which is the general idea.
Hindsight says i should have gotten a better 300mm lens and forgotten
about this convertible stuff.  For 4x5, you probably want to start with
a 210, maybe a 150.  There are probably lots of cheap 150&#39;s out there,
so for not TOO terribly much money, you can get started in 4x5.  Then
if you are clever, you can turn it into an enlarger by finding a way to
fasten a cold-light source on the back, behind or instead of the ground
glass, with some sort of negative carrier.  I think Bender might be
working on something like that; ask them.

I made several phone calls, and the same guy always answered the phone,
who i suspect might be Mr. Bender himself, and he was always nice and
friendly and sort of got to know who i was, so that by the time i
called him from Port Angeles, Washington, in the middle of my trip,
moaning about breaking the ground glass and needing another one, he
sort of knew who i was.  I made a cover for the ground glass out of
acrylic sheet.  It fastens quickly over the back of the camera, and is
spaced out from the glass about 1/2&amp;quot;.  Highly recommended.
--

- donl mathis at Silicon Graphics Computer Systems, Mountain View, CA

donl@sgi.com

----------

From: donl@glass.wpd.sgi.com (donl mathis)
Subject: Re: Bender View Camera Kits
Date: 10 Apr 90 23:10:10 GMT
Organization: Silicon Graphics, Inc., Mountain View, CA

In article &amp;lt;5360328@hplsla.HP.COM&amp;gt;, andyc@hplsla.HP.COM (Andy Cassino) writes:
&amp;gt; Thanks for the very informative posting, Don. You&#39;ve piqued my interest.
&amp;gt; I&#39;m wondering about some of the statistics for these cameras. Like, max
&amp;gt; bellows draw, weight, and how compact are they when closed up. Would you
&amp;gt; consider (gasp) backpacking the 8x10?

[I would take mine!  Of course, it&#39;s only 4x5. :^) -- gwa]

I have no doubt that it could be made to fit in a back pack; you will need
to fashion a cover for the ground glass.  If you remove the monorail (which
can be accomplished by loosening a couple of knobs and pulling it out), the
bellows can be compressed all the way down, and everything sort of fits
together pretty well.  I would consider it, yes, though i can&#39;t say for
sure how it would work out!  I&#39;ve been carrying it around in a canvas bag.

[A very cumbersome-looking canvas bag, I might add.  As donl has it set
up now, he wouldn&#39;t want to take it more than a few feet from the car.
:^) -- gwa]

The overall package is smaller than my 4x5 outfit; i have four 8x10 holders,
and only one lens, so there isn&#39;t much else to carry.  You tend to run lean
on holders, because they&#39;re (gasp) $40 each, new.  Get used ones.  Don&#39;t
buy very many.  Don&#39;t make exposures you aren&#39;t sure are going to be
printable.  Etc. etc. etc.  It&#39;s a time-and-effort versus money tradeoff
to load film holders a little more often!

The 4x5 kit:

    $150, 3 lbs., 10x10x4 (folded)

[Now $189.50, as noted above. -- gwa]

    rise and fall at both ends: 2 3/4&amp;quot;

[Or, as I use it, rise at both ends: 5 1/2&amp;quot; -- gwa]

    tilts and swings at both ends: 45 degrees

[The stats lie.  Physically, both of these movements are limited only by
the bellows.  Without the bellows you can swing them all the way around. 
I think that&#39;s more than 45 degrees. :^)  The only real limitation on
your movements with this camera is the coverage of the lens, and that&#39;s
what really matters anyway. -- gwa]

    front shift 3&amp;quot;, rear 4&amp;quot;.
    extension: 3&amp;quot; minimum, 22&amp;quot; maximum.

[Here&#39;s where you see the problem with short lenses.  90mm is only 3.5
inches.  You&#39;re just about as short as you can get when using a 90. -- gwa]

    interchangeable bellows; optional bag bellows.
    Interchangeable lens board.  Back rotates to vertical or horizontal.

    Cherry wood with little bits of hardware here and there.  All
    movements, including focusing, are friction locks via knobs on
    1/4-20 studs.

    The rail is a simple 1x1 square aluminum tube; appropriate lengths
    are easy to make.

The 8x10 kit:

    $250, 6 lbs., sort of big but folds up reasonably well.

[Now $289.50. -- gwa]

    rise and fall at front: 2 3/4&amp;quot;, none at the rear.
    front swings and tilts: 45 degrees
    rear swing 12 degrees, tilt 18 degrees.
    front shift 4&amp;quot;, none at rear.

    Non-interchangeable bellows (not necessary in 8x10).

    Other features the same as as the 4x5.

All swing and tilt angles are plus-or-minus.

Bender is in Albuquerque, (505) 293-1118.  Ask them for a brochure.  Nice
folks.

[They&#39;re now in Leavenworth, Washington.  You can reach them at:

    Bender Photographic
    19691 Highway 209
    Leavenworth, WA 98826

    (509) 763-2626
    (800) 776-3199 (orders only)

-- gwa]


~~~~~
From: bjs@ruts.ccc.amdahl.com (Barry Sherman)
Subject: Re: Bender View Camera Kits...
Date: 12 Jul 91 20:19:11 GMT
Organization: Amdahl Corporation, Sunnyvale CA


&amp;gt;Question:
&amp;gt;
&amp;gt;How rigid are they? 
[Description of windy visit to Point Lobos]
&amp;gt;He was very upset by the wind.  He showed me how the camera was 
&amp;gt;flopping in the wind.  It was clearly unusable.  I had no problem with 
&amp;gt;my rigid bodied 35mm.  He said that he doubted that he would have had a
&amp;gt;problem were he using his Toya view camera.  But the floppiness of the 
&amp;gt;field camera was very disconcerting.

Well, I haven&#39;t had it out in any major winds (though we get them here,
that&#39;s for sure), but I don&#39;t think the camera would be flopping in the
wind.  Of course, if there&#39;s any vegetation in the scene, you don&#39;t want
to be using large format anyway!

The camera does seem to ``give&#39;&#39; a little when I insert a film holder,
but it stays in focus, so it&#39;s obviously not slipping any.

A bigger hazard in a heavy wind might be that the camera is so light,
yet so big.  The wind may try to carry it off.  I don&#39;t know if that
would become a problem or not.

&amp;gt;I&#39;m hoping to start with large format in the next year or so and
&amp;gt;am considering a Bender kit as a starter. 

[Barry has since caved in to the temptation of that 20 square-inch piece
of film, as you may know.  He started with another camera, and has since
bought a Bender, for the weight savings.  Welcome to the club, Barry! --gwa]

&amp;gt;But somehow the
&amp;gt;friction locks on the Benders just don&#39;t look as if they would
&amp;gt;produce a really rigid assembly.  What does experience show?

I&#39;d say it locks up just fine.  The friction locks, you probably know,
are just screws.  I tighten them up pretty snugly and everything holds
together just fine.  In fact, when playing with tilts (which are held by
two screws) I usually just tighten one and leave the other loose.  This
allows me to use one hand to adjust the tilt and one to man the lock. 
Tightening down one side seems to hold it pretty well.  Of course, once
I decide everything is how I want it, I lock the other one as well. 
Then check the focus again, just to be sure. 

I haven&#39;t had any problems yet.

Another thing I wondered about the friction locks was focusing.  I
wondered how close I&#39;d be able to get focusing without a geared focusing
movement.  The answer is, ``Quite well, thank you.&#39;&#39; I do my rough focus
with the front standard and fine focus with the rear standard, and am
rather impressed with how easy it is to move the standard the tiny
little bit required to get the focus right where you want it.  I&#39;d
definitely recommend a little extra care when building the monorail
riders, which are the first parts in the instruction book.  There&#39;s a
bit of extra wood in them, which you sand away.  If you don&#39;t sand
enough, they&#39;ll be loose; if you sand too much, they&#39;ll be tight. 
Either way, focusing will be more difficult. 

~~~~~
From: donl@glass.esd.sgi.com (donl mathis)
Subject: Bender 4x5 View Camera Kit report
Organization: Silicon Graphics, Inc., Mountain View, CA, USA
Date: Mon, 9 Nov 1992 22:46:18 GMT


[I&#39;m posting this for Steve. -- donl]

-----

For the past two months, I&#39;ve been building a Bender 4x5 camera.
Given the interest in 4x5, and specifically Bender cameras, evidenced
by recent rec.photo traffic, I decided to write about my kit-building
experiences.

donl@sgi.com has graciously offered to post these articles for me;
I don&#39;t have posting ability to this group anymore (and only limited access
to read it). Send comments DIRECTLY TO ME at the Email address (way) below.

PART 1 (starts with lots of drivel about me, skip forward if you&#39;re bored):

My background:

My career is as a software engineer, but I&#39;ve been involved professionally
in photography for about eight years. My forte is atypical portraits, more
intense than typical &amp;quot;glamour/fashion&amp;quot; work, but along those lines (I tend
toward saturated colors and hard lighting, with unusual posing/props.)
I&#39;ve done some product shots, some &amp;quot;event&amp;quot; coverage, and have made one 
magazine cover. Most of my work has been done in small/medium format.
I print my own B/W and color, and process my own B/W film. It&#39;s 
more cost-effective for me to run roll film through a local minilab.

Why 4x5?

As indicated above, I don&#39;t do this full-time. The professional aspect
is really intended to finance my equipment needs for personal photography.
Of course, I still have to pay taxes on it :-(.  My personal interest is
&amp;quot;fine art&amp;quot; photography, specifically landscapes, macro flowers, and
&amp;quot;set&amp;quot; pieces. 4x5 or larger is the preferred format for this type of work.

Why a Bender kit?

It&#39;s cheap. No, actually, that&#39;s just part of it. I enjoy building things,
and I wanted a camera I could backpack with, without being overly concerned
about knocking it around. At $200.00, the Bender fits the bill. I dropped 
the serious bucks on a spotmeter and a Nikkor lense. When you
couple that with film holders, large format darkroom gear (used), and
assorted bits, minimizing costs becomes a consideration. Who knows, maybe
I&#39;ll hate large format :-). Bender kits have gotten mostly good reviews,
both on the net and in the photo media.

The Kit:

The kit is composed of an unmounted bellows, assorted hardware, a ground
glass, and, as donl accurately describes it: &amp;quot;a rather small box
full of sticks&amp;quot; (nicely machined sticks).

Features:

The Bender is basically a wooden monorail camera. It has full tilts and
swings, and substantial rise/fall and lateral shifts. Your lense coverage
is probably the limiting factor here. All movements and focus are friction
lock. There are no scales on any of the movements, but you could add them
if you really care. The back holder has two small leveling vials; front/
back, and left/right. All wooden parts are unfinished cherry. You finish
the camera however you like. The removeable parts (lensboard, back, bellows
frames) are held on with moveable &amp;quot;L&amp;quot; screws. Some people (including me)
consider this a mis-feature... however, Jay Bender correctly points out that
they DO work, and they keep the kit cost down. Most of us complainers :-)
changed these to something else, which is possible with a kit. 

Recent changes in the kit:

Bender does, on occasion, upgrade the kit based on owner feedback. The 
following improvements were made as of August 15, 1992. (Newer manuals 
should be current now; I got an old manual and a Errata/Changes sheet).
Note: most of this is meaningless if you haven&#39;t already built the kit;
I&#39;m describing it for the benefit of owners of previous renditions...

1) The groundglass holder is now attached to the back differently. The
spring wires now mount into the back at the bottom at a single point each.
Looking from the back, the wires run vertically, with inward-turning
right angles at the MIDDLE of the groundglass holder, which fit into a
small block attached to the groundglass holder. The wires extend down
to the bottom piece of the back, and turn a right angle INTO the back
(along your line of sight). About a half-inch above this turn, a small
notched block is screwed into the side piece of the back to hold the
wire down and provide the &amp;quot;springy&amp;quot;-ness. (This is as opposed to the older
style which mounted to the back in the center sides, and hooked to four
L-screws mounted horizontally into the groundglass holder).

2) Most (all?) glued-together rectangles now have screws also at the
joints.

3) The groundglass holder now has a wider part 16 on the side where the
film holder is inserted. This is done to allow you to file the underside
to a slope, to act as a combination handle and guide for film holder
insertion.

4) (I&#39;m not sure this is new) Washers are now supplied to fit between
the rise/fall locks and the frames, and between the frames and back
holder/lensboard holder (ie - between all sliding parts except the 
frames and monorail sliders).

What you need to build it:

As several previous posts have mentioned: LOTS of clamps. I bought
four twelve-inch bar clamps, and four three-inch C-clamps. If you&#39;re
really gung-ho, get more than this. Each major assembly typically requires
four clamps to hold it together. I found that each major assembly took
about all the time I had or wanted to spare on any given evening.
In addition, you need multiple sheets of sandpaper in various grades
(I used 100, 150, and 220 grit). A one-quarter-inch wood file is useful
in a few instances. The kit is assembled with brass screws and carpenter&#39;s
glue (the yellow stuff). The bellows is mounted to the bellows frames
with contact cement. Contact cement is applied to the joining surfaces,
then allowed to dry (mostly). The two parts can then be loosely positioned
without sticking together (much), then pressed together for a secure fit.

C-clamps aren&#39;t necessarily the best choice here, because they aren&#39;t
designed to clamp a narrow thing while it&#39;s lying on a flat surface
(which seems to be the majority of the kit building). The clamps tend to
want to shear off of the part being held, because the pressure isn&#39;t
centered in the jaws. An easy solution to this is to cut a board slightly
narrower than the assembly you wish to clamp, put the board on the table,
lay the assembly on that so that the to-be-clamped edges slightly overhang,
then clamp the overhanging edges. Someone (geoff?) mentioned using corner-
clamps. In my experience, corner-clamps are designed to clamp from within
the frame being glued. The majority of the kit frames don&#39;t have sufficient
interior clearance for the clamps to fit.

Well, that&#39;s enough for now (too much?). I&#39;ll describe my luck building
the sub-assemblies in future posts. Let me know if I&#39;m giving too much or
not enough information.



--
Steve Holzworth
sch@unx.sas.com
x6872
SAS Institute - Open Systems R &amp;amp; D
Cary, N.C.


~~~~~
Subject: Re: Bender 4x5 View Camera Kit report
From: mandayrv@ucunix.san.uc.edu (Prince of Wales)
Date: Tue, 10 Nov 1992 17:39:14 GMT
Organization: University of Cincinnati


Here are my opinions about the bender kit. I did mail these to people who
requested it. But since this thread appeared I felt it would be appropriate
here too. Most of the details about the kit have been mentioned by steve
(through donl&#39;s posting), so I am ignoring those aspects of the kit
building. I would however like to mention here that till about a week back I
was not fully aware of the use of the spring loaded back, not having  used
any other large format camera. My procedure for loading a film holder on the
back was to remove the ground glass holder from the spring, lay it down on
the ground or the camera bag, mount the film holder, take the shot, remove
the film holder and reinsert the ground glass holder.  It was very recently
that as I was going   through the zone VI catalog that I saw a photograph of
their view camera with the caption &amp;quot;Easy swing out bailing arm for the
ground glass&amp;quot;. That was when the THING struck me. I have, all this time,
been expending unnecessary effort on inserting the film holder. I  have 
now started loading the film holder the way it should have been done in the
first place.

This has ofcourse led to an improvement in the time to shoot (see comments
below) by about 5 to 10 percent. 

######################################################################

Experiences about the large format per se:

1) I love the image resolution and tonal/color gradation available.

2) I hate (to some extent) the time it takes to  take a shot and the
weight of the equipment that I have to lug around if I am planning on
shooting anywhere a bit farther from my car. (In my case, I do not own a
car so all the travelling is by bus and walk. I wish I could save enough
money to buy a used car -:). Other things that irk me (they are what one 
terms occupational hazards) are the fact that since I do not have a changing
bag with me at present, I have to do all the film loading/unloading at
night. In other words, I have to plan every shoot at least one day
in advance. In the next few months I plan on buying a changing room from
Calumet.




**************************************************************************

Accessories that I feel one should have for doing large format
photography:


1) A magnifying glass/slide viewer. I use my 8x agfa slide viewer to
focus the image on the ground glass. I can somehow manage because I have
20/20 vision, but if your eyesight is not so good, I would recommend one
of the slightly more expensive ones such as the CALUMET viewer that sells
for about $40.

2) A spot meter. You lose the fun in working with large format if you are
not able to analyze an image before taking a photograph of it. This is
not a big problem with roll film since one can afford to bracket.

3) I have been using a jacket as a focussing cloth. But I would still
prefer to have a regular cloth. 

4) A spirit level of some sort if you intend doing a lot of architectural
shots. The bender kit comes with two spirit levels that you glue to the
rear standards. Besides, my tripod head also has two spirit levels.

5) Other odds and ends such as lens cleaner/dust remover/brush (these are 
a must for large format). The brush can also be used for cleaning the backs
before inserting them.


**************************************************************************


The tools/consumables which IMHO one MUST have to build the Bender 4x5 kit:

1) A Drill - electrical or hand powered. The drill bits needed are 3/32&amp;quot;,
1/8&amp;quot; (or 7/64).
*** I purchased an electric drill for two dollars at a local yard sale. **

[A drill press is best if you have or can buy/borrow one. --gwa]

2) A couple of screw drivers with 3mm and 5mm blades.

3) Two grades of sandpaper: 90 and 200.

4) Clamps:  
    a) Greater than 8 inches - at least one.
    b) Greater than 6 inches - at least two.
        ( One of the above can double up for both categories)
    c) 2 inch clamps -- at least 6. (very time consuming, but could be
        done with only 2)
    d) A corner clamp.

5) Scrap wood to place between the clamps and the wood surface.

[Cardboard and mat board work as well. --gwa]

6) The smallest possible container of wood glue.

7) Contact cement that hardens to the touch in a few minutes and sets in 
about an hour or two.

8) A reasonably flat piece of material (wood or any other metal).

[I used an old piece of glass. --gwa]

9) A reasonably accurate 90 degree T-square. 

9) A hammer to fix in the T-screws for the various adjustable movements.


**************************************************************************

Tools/accessories which IMO one could use to ease the working conditions
but are not critical:

1) A drum/belt sander or a sanding drum for the drill.

2) A set of good wood working chisels or wood carving knives. (these, I
felt were the single most useful junk tools that I had collected over the
last few years.)

3) Wood working stain and brushes for finishing/polishing the wood.





BE CAREFUL ABOUT THE FOLLOWING WHILE ASSEMBLING THE KIT.

a) The single most important thing IMHO is the ground glass placement. Be
extremely careful about the dimensions that the kit mentions. (The kit is
very very accurate as far as the positioning of the glass goes. How close
you get to it is very much dependent on how patient you are in measuring
distances of about 1/32 of an inch)

b) Read the assembly for the back holder at least 3 or 4 times, do a mock
set up without actually gluing the pieces together. Keep in mind the
following :

    1) The hinge (or pivot )for the back should be towards the lens board
    and not the other way (the instruction manual is a bit fuzzy about
    this). Also, the UNEVEN ledges on the inside of the back holder
    should be away from the lens, i.e. should be facing back.

[I would recommend pre-fitting ALL of the parts, not just the back
holder.  Like I said early on in all of this, go slow and careful and
everything will be all right. --gwa]

c) Be careful with the cutting instructions for the bag bellows. Take a
couple of minutes extra in cutting. I would recommend cutting a little
less than is mentioned in the manual and then adjusting as and when
necessary. 

THERE ARE SOME MORE HINTS WHICH I WOULD RATHER TELL YOU ONCE YOU BUY THE
KIT. YOU CAN SEND ME EMAIL OR CALL ME AT (513)-281-9870.


**************************************************************************


My experiences with the Bender kit:

HITS :

1) Extremely light weight to carry. AM very pleased with this feature.

2) Is very generous in terms of movements.

3) Has interchangeable bellows (though I have never used the bag
bellows).


MISSES:

1) No geared focussing (But I do not miss them so much).

2) Am not very sure about being able to use lenses shorter than 90mm.

3) The standards have some play, but since it is wood I have realized
that they spring back to normal once external pressure  is removed. You
may have to get used to this. 

** Initially you may find that once you focus the image and then tighten all 
the knobs, the image has gone out of focus. You will then have to readjust 
every thing again. After a few attempts you will get used to allowing for
such &amp;quot;plays&amp;quot; in the focussing mechanisms.   **


4) May not be possible to rent lenses for this camera since the lensboard
is not a commonly used size. I will have to look into this sometime.

4) Some of the joints that are glued do not look/feel strong mechanically. 
I had to reinforce some of them. I use plastic window screen retainers for
holding the lens board in place  -- (an excellent piece of advice from GEOFF, 
geoff@pmafire.inel.gov  . You may want to contact him about some more 
insights about the kit) -- I have two on the top  and two on the bottom 
of the lensboard holder, besides the two L screws that Mr. Bender has 
supplied. This has given me a lot of confidence in not worrying  about 
my $500 lens falling down when the front is tilted forward.

5) Though I have not had it, light leak could be a problem if the
workmanship is not good. This is not meant to discourage anyone from
trying out the kit, just that you should take that tiny little extra care
when working on the light trapping edges such as the inside of the ground
glass/film-holder holder.


*************************************************************************

It took me about a week of intensive working (with the limited amount of
time that a PhD candidate has) to assemble the kit and test out the
focus. Plan on spending additional time if you do not do your own
darkroom processing since you may take three or four days extra if your
ground glass is not at the correct distance from the lens board. The kit
has more information about this aspect.

-- 
ramanand@pumpkin.ece.uc.edu
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whew! If you read all of this, I know a few things about you:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You have the determination needed to build the Bender kit.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You have the intelligence needed to build the Bender kit.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You are obviously interested enough in this to have read a lot of
comments from a lot of people.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you decide to go for it, remember: relax, and take thinks slow and
easy. You&amp;rsquo;ll do just fine. Happy shooting! Geoff Allen&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.greenspun.com/com/qtluong/photography/lf/bender.html&#34;&gt;View or add
comments&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>http://lflf.surge.sh</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lflf.surge.sh</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h2 id=&#34;black-jacket-focus-cloth-from-quietworks-user-review&#34;&gt;Black Jacket Focus Cloth from Quietworks - User Review&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;By &lt;a href=&#34;mailto:paulowen_2000@yahoo.com&#34;&gt;Paul Owen&lt;/a&gt; © 2005 for
&lt;a href=&#34;%20.&#34;&gt;largeformatphotography.info&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Along with the majority of large format photographers, I have spent a
great deal of time scouring the internet looking for a focus cloth that
does one simple thing - work!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a complete fool with needle and thread, making one was not an option!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;d tried different types of &amp;ldquo;horse blankets&amp;rdquo; but found that despite
various materials used in their construction, they all suffered from
more than one &amp;ldquo;problem&amp;rdquo; for me personally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Firstly if you want anything decent then you need to be prepared to
carry something large and (surprisingly) heavy. The major drawback I
came across was that unless the material was large enough to wrap
completely around the camera AND had Velcro strips to secure it, then it
was often difficult to compose the image on the ground glass as a large
amount of light &amp;ldquo;bounced&amp;rdquo; off the floor and did a merry dance on the
screen!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I thought I had found a &amp;ldquo;good&amp;rdquo; cloth in the Harrison-made &amp;ldquo;Classic&amp;rdquo;
cloth. Plenty big enough, mandatory Velcro strips, weatherproof,
light-tight and &amp;hellip;heavy! But it had to be (or so I thought) to get the
combination of size and light proofing! So I persevered with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I then came across the Ebony focus cloth. Rubberised silk, emblazoned
with the &amp;ldquo;Ebony&amp;rdquo; logo, weatherproof, very (very) lightweight, mandatory
Velcro strips &amp;hellip; by Jove I think I found it &amp;hellip; the &amp;ldquo;holy grail&amp;rdquo; of
focus cloths! However, a few outings revealed that it needed improving.
I convinced my wife to assist with converting the Ebony cloth into an
Ebony tube! Elasticated drawstring sewn into one end, Velcro strips and
there I had it - nothing to this sewing lark!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I quite happily used my Ebony-hybrid and it still serves me well.
However, recent threads on this forum mentioned a new addition to the
list of contenders. &amp;ldquo;Quietworks&amp;rdquo; was now producing a focus jacket!! I
had to take a look at this!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found their web site and was quite amazed at the ingenuity of this
design. It seemed to do everything - and doubled up as a rather nifty
silver rain jacket too &amp;hellip; for me not the camera!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Around this time I began tentative enquiries on another matter - trying
to establish free large format workshop-type gatherings here in the UK.
Surprisingly the response was overwhelming and a hastily arranged first
meeting took place in the Lake District of England. As is usual when a
group of photographers get together, there is the customary discussions
about equipment - more so with large format users!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was clear that a great many of us had yet to find an ideal focus
cloth. I must add that on previous F32 workshops that I assisted on I
saw some amazing sights - from Dracula-impersonators (one cloth trailed
behind its user who wore it tied around his shoulders like the Count
himself) to those who had sewn together a couple of black t-shirts for a
double-thickness &amp;ldquo;tube&amp;rdquo; (with short sleeves!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their owners seemed happy enough - but I thought that this may have been
simply due to the fact that there wasn&amp;rsquo;t anything commercially available
that was much better!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, despite the fact that they &amp;ldquo;worked&amp;rdquo; for their owners (especially
the t-shirt) they looked, well, ridiculous! I&amp;rsquo;m sorry but I for one find
that I become something of a novelty act when the &amp;ldquo;old wooden camera&amp;rdquo;
comes out! Disappear under a cloak or t-shirt and the Weirdo-factor is
multiplied by a bout 10. One reason the Ebony &amp;ldquo;tube&amp;rdquo; worked for me - it
was fairly discreet!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, back to the plot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the Lake District gathering and when it became clear that this was
to become a regular meeting - I decided to give Keith at Quietworks a
call (well an email actually). The result - demo 5x4 &amp;ldquo;Original&amp;rdquo; and 10x8
&amp;ldquo;Hybrid&amp;rdquo; blackjackets in the post from the good old US of A to me here
in dear old &amp;lsquo;Blighty, for our group to try out and report back!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First impression? Lightweight. In fact, super-lightweight! These things
weighed next to nothing - what it actually weighs (to me) is not
important - what is important is how easy it is to stuff in a pack and
that it doesn&amp;rsquo;t add to the bulk or weight of the (already heavy)
backpack! But for those who count the ounces the 5x4 weighs in at 8
ounces and the 10x8 weighs a mere 23 ounces!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How do they fare? Well the next workshop is scheduled for October 15-16,
2005, but I couldn&amp;rsquo;t wait that long to try them out! So a quick dash one
Saturday morning found me on a deserted beach in sunny South Wales.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Camera and tripod set up, it was time to try them both out. The 5x4
version was tried first. Problem! The fit around the camera back was
very tight - a struggle to actually get it around the frame. The Ebony
45SU I was using does have a large rear frame and this was obviously the
cause of the problem! However, a bit of jiggling and with the neck of
the cloth around the bellows of the camera it was time to try it out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;WOW! It actually worked! Nice and dark but the real boon was the fact
that I could rummage around to my hearts content with my arms in the
sleeves and it STAYED dark! There was so much room inside that I was
able to move my head way back from the screen to get the &amp;ldquo;big picture&amp;rdquo;
with room to spare. I have done this in the past with other cloths and
ended up catching the camera and tripod as I dragged it backwards!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another problem! The design of my camera means that the frame is raised
above the bed by a good inch when in the neutral position. Result - a
shaft of light across the bed of the camera and into the jacket.
Certainly nowhere near as distracting as the blanket-type cloth but
easily solved by the use of my free hand simply stuffing some of the
material under the frame!! DARKNESS!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second impression? I REALLY like this!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Onto the 10x8 version. It&amp;rsquo;s BIG!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I tried it with the Ebony and found that it was swamped by the jacket.
Not surprised really as it&amp;rsquo;s designed for 10x8 cameras! But once back at
home I fitted it to a 10x8 Deardorff and it was a perfect fit!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Likewise, at home I also tried the 5x4 Original on a Cambo Wide -
beautiful fit!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What else is there to mention?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nothing really apart from the fact that, at last, there seems to be a
focus cloth that does what it&amp;rsquo;s supposed to do - create a darkened
environment in which we can experience the beauty of the scene on a
ground glass screen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From a user point of view the Black Jackets fit the bill and they are
also surprisingly cheap for such a well-made and functional product.
They are roomy, dark and have none of the claustrophobia I found with
the regular tube-type cloths I had tried.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;What exactly makes this focus cloth so different from the competition?
I hear you ask! Well, for me its greatest benefit is the fact that at
last, here is a focus cloth that does the job we want. Unlike the
blanket type cloth the BlackJacket doesn&amp;rsquo;t suffer from those annoying
light-leaks that make focusing tricky - it really does provide the right
environment for working with a ground glass screen. Another plus is that
it doesn&amp;rsquo;t wrap itself around you with every gust of wind a problem
inherent with the blanket-type cloth - in fact I reckon EVERY LF user
must have struggled in this situation at some time or another.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, unlike the blanket-type cloth (with the exception of the Ebony),
the BlackJacket is extremely lightweight, waterproof and very compact.
Being able to stuff it into a pocket or space in your pack is a real
boon - no more trying to fold a focus cloth in windy/wet conditions!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The design of the BlackJacket shares similarities with the tube-type
cloths but with a few real advantages over this design. For one, it is
incredibly roomy inside and being able to access the screen and camera
controls through the sleeves is, for me, a very natural way of working.
I also found that regular tube-type cloths were claustrophobic - shoving
my head down a tunnel was never my idea of fun but the added space
inside this cloth is very beneficial.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One benefit that photographers in much warmer climates will appreciate
is the nature of the material used by Keith in his designs. The
&amp;ldquo;Original&amp;rdquo; version is waterproof and very light but the &amp;ldquo;Hybrid&amp;rdquo;
version, depsite being a bit heavier is actually made using a breathable
fabric. Whilst this will be of little benefit in the UK I&amp;rsquo;m sure it will
be much appreciated in warmer countries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, Keith has not forgotten us living in wetter climes, and his
web-site clearly shows the benefit that actually wearing the BlackJacket
can have in sudden downpours!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In short, the design of this cloth combines the advantages of the
blanket and tube-types rolled into one and I for one hope that
&amp;ldquo;Quietworks&amp;rdquo; sell plenty of them! This company is continually making
steps at improving and developing their line of products. At the moment
Keith is developing BlackJackets for ULF photographers using a variety
of formats and is obviously customer-driven.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All in all I found it to be a well-made and very useful product and in
my opinion a necessity rather than an accessory - although I doubt if I
would be seen &amp;ldquo;wearing&amp;rdquo; it - well not in public anyway!&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can heartily recommend either of these. The 5x4 version will fit most
field cameras but it may be worth checking out the 5x7 version as this
will offer slightly more room to fit large rear frames.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m looking forward to October when I can share this revelation with
fellow LF&amp;rsquo;ers as we do battle with the Northumberland Coast!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;link-to-the-manufacturer-s-site-with-photos&#34;&gt;Link to the manufacturer&amp;rsquo;s site (with photos)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;view-or-add-comments-20http-largeformatphotography-info-lfforum-topic-502725-html&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;%20http://largeformatphotography.info/lfforum/topic/502725.html&#34;&gt;View or add comments&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[](mailto:paulowen_2000@yahoo.com)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;paulowen_2000@yahoo.com&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>