<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Large Format Photography</title>
    <link>http://lflf.surge.sh/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content on Large Format Photography</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 01 Apr 2015 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://lflf.surge.sh/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Shooting LF is not difficult, from MF to LF</title>
      <link>http://lflf.surge.sh/from-mf-to-lf/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Apr 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lflf.surge.sh/from-mf-to-lf/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;With analog camera and lens prices down to levels no one could have dreamt of as little as twenty years ago, the introduction of digital cameras has opened the door to all kinds of exotic equipment for those who choose to shoot film. However, there seems to be a significant barrier to entry. It does not seem to dissuade easily people from getting into 35mm, but certainly holds them back when they consider buying into MF equipment. From there, even very seasoned photographers seem to view LF as a nigh impossible step. Are the barriers really that high and is the difference that large?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;the-choice-to-work-with-film&#34;&gt;The choice to work with film&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regardless of the size you choose to work with, there is a very conscious choice involved in shooting film. Quite to the contrary of the general availability and affordability of great photographic equipment, film, places that process it or stock chemicals to do it at home have become scarcer and more expensive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many photographers these days have very possibly never even owned or photographed with any analog camera, let alone system. With photographing, I mean consciously taking a picture, carefully evaluating variables such as film type and speed, lighting, aperture and shutter settings, etc. As such, this is not counting the classic 35mm point and shoot cameras offering only full auto mode. To them, LF may not be the way to go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For those who grew up with film or who shot it for artistic purposes, digital has often been a blessing or a necessary evil. Even though my first camera was a Pentax Spotmatic, followed by various Nikon 35mm film cameras, I too, at some stage abandoned film. As a wildlife photographer, the flexibility, cheap high volume workflow, and the possibility to share pretty much as soon as I shot, meant that digital was great, and film was as good as dead. Or so I thought.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As time passed and I, like many of you, kept upgrading to newer generations of digital cameras, I sometime glanced at analog gear. Remembering the luscious, saturated Velvia colors projected on the wall, I started buying and shooting analog again. First in 35mm (Nikon F6, Contax G2 kits, Leica M6), but soon I was shooting all sorts of MF equipment too (Mamiya 7 and 645 Pro TL, Hasselblad 501C, Fuji GW690II, GW690III, GA645Zi, Bronica ETRSi, GS-1, Pentax 645N and others). MF rapidly overtook 35mm for me as the creative and print possibilities it offers are much greater.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the years, I increasingly started to shoot black and white film in addition to Velvia. The satisfaction of projecting the large slides on the wall or watching them on a light table is so hard to describe. Then at some stage, you take identical or similar shots with your digital camera and on Velvia. Once processed and on the screen, there is a difference between night and day. What more reason do you need to shoot film? Motivations and purposes will differ, but we all have our reason to shoot film and I strongly feel film has a solid place in today&amp;rsquo;s world of photography.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;medium-format-or-large-format&#34;&gt;Medium format or large format&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The basic assumption for the purpose of this article is that your photography lends itself to both formats and that you currently probably shoot MF in addition to another system. Whether it is landscape, fashion, portrait or other, medium and large format have many specializations in which both could work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a nutshell, medium format gear is often comparatively portable. Add to this that quite a few cameras can be shot hand-held that eliminates the need for a tripod and offers flexibility. This makes for quite a compelling proposition. However, large format offers the big advantage of the larger negative or slide and in many cases the movements of the camera that open a whole new world of creative possibilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For those of us who are willing or routinely carry a tripod and a heavy pack of gear, large format seems to be a great choice. Still, many people do not take the leap. The hurdle appears to be high, which is a shame.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;the-large-format-hurdle&#34;&gt;The large format hurdle&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So your work could potentially benefit from the creative freedom of a large format system, or you are addicted to the big negatives and slides like many of us. You look at classifieds and eBay listings and see the greatest of gear, but just can not make up your mind to buy into it. My question is, why not? Assuming you have shot film before and are familiar with camera basics, the hurdle is much lower than you think. In random order:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Large format is expensive.&lt;/strong&gt; If you have read until here, you have probably also looked at classifieds. If you have, you will have noticed that a great LF set-up costs less than an enthusiast level digital camera (monorail cameras including a simple lens, a few film holders and some bits and bobs sell for as little as 300 euros on Ebay and locally! A full wooden LF field kit can be had for 750 euros if you are patient). The difference is that the LF equipment is not a direct write-off, but should sell for similar money in the future if looked after carefully.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Where to start?&lt;/strong&gt; There is so much gear on sale that finding a first camera can be confusing. This is true to an extend, however, if you carefully think about what you want to shoot and where, life becomes a lot simpler. If you want to shoot in a studio and want maximum movement, monorails are great and sell for ridiculously little money (cameras without accessories from anywhere as low as 200 euros). If you want portability, any of the wooden field cameras will be great (I just saw an &amp;ldquo;as new&amp;rdquo; Shen Hao field for 500 euros). And if you insist on hand held shooting, old press cameras are an option (anywhere from 150 euros and up depending on their condition), as are several modern developments. From there you can always migrate to bigger or better. Chances are that if you stick to the same format, all lenses (and probably lens boards too) and film holders will be directly compatible. Your light meter, focusing loupe, dark cloth and so on will also continue to serve you well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Large format is heavy.&lt;/strong&gt; While not lightweight, an LF system can very much be as heavy or light as you want. This depends on size, types and numbers of lenses and holders, tripod, etc. I have never accurately weighed my travel kit (wooden field camera, three lenses, 10 holders, boxes of sheet film, changing tent, light meter, focusing loupe, etc), but it comes in at around twenty five pounds, including the thinktank bag it all fits into.My full Hasselblad MF kit including three lenses, several backs, two bodies and accessories weighs about the same. In contrast, my digital wildlife kit is significantly heavier, at around thirty-five pounds (although I can shave a few pounds off by leaving the super tele at home). My &amp;ldquo;ultralight&amp;rdquo; LF kit consists of a wista field, 6 film holders, three lenses (75mm, 150mm, 210mm), a loupe, light meter and some bits and bobs. It fits in a think tank sling back and comes in between ten and twelve pounds! Granted, thereÕs a tripod that is carried separately, but there are plenty of lightweight alternatives with simple ballheads or level heads available.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Large format is too complicated.&lt;/strong&gt; Technical cameras, unlike the technical aspects of a space shuttle, are not very complicated at all. Yes, they do require some time and effort to learn, but there are always people there to help, like on this forum. In addition, there are great books such as &amp;ldquo;Using the view camera&amp;rdquo; that provide excellent information on how to use your camera and its movements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Film and supplies are hard to come by.&lt;/strong&gt; It is true that it is unlikely that your local photo shop stock sheet film and other supplies. However, there are many great sources online where you can order sheet film in many formats as well as pretty much anything else you could need or want.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;No access to a darkroom.&lt;/strong&gt; While needed for printing your photos, you do not need one to load and develop sheet film. Most of the people here probably do not have access to a full dark room. Instead, they work with changing tents or bags and daylight developing tanks. There work great and are widely available. Harrison tents are nice and pack very compact, but I have found loading my expert drums easier in a Calumet pop-up tent that sells for around 90 euros.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Developing film is prohibitively expensive or unavailable in my area.&lt;/strong&gt; This is the case for many photographers. There are probably professional laboratories in your country of residence that will receive and return film by mail for processing. This, however, can indeed be expensive (I am not sure about other countries, but the cheapest I have found in the Netherlands is 4.5 euros ex-vat and shipping for a 4x5 sheet). However, developing your own film is quite easy. Particularly if you choose to shoot black and white (My total costs for a drum with 6 sheets of B&amp;amp;W films is around 1,25 euros and includes developer, stop batch, fixer and a few drops of photo flow). Color (slide) film is somewhat more complicated but do-able. If developing seems too daunting, why not take a darkroom course. You will learn how to do it and have the confidence to experiment at home. And if you ask nicely, you may very well meet someone who is willing to show you how itÕs done for free.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;in-conclusion&#34;&gt;In conclusion&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Large format has much to offer and provides great creative possibilities when compared to small and medium format alternatives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If your photography lends itself to working with large format film, or if you desire to print large, there is little reason not to try.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is no mystique to LF and hurdles to a switch to LF are much lower in real life than they may seem when reading about them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Basic photographic principles apply, just like they do for any other format. If you are familiar with them, you will feel comfortable with an LF camera.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is no such thing as mutual exclusivity. I for one continue to shoot digital, MF and LF. Each of the systems has its merits. View them as complementary, rather than incompatible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And finally, yes, people will look at you when you shoot a LF camera. Most people will just look surprised, however, if you get any, reactions are almost always positive.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Large Format Primer</title>
      <link>http://lflf.surge.sh/why/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Apr 2001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lflf.surge.sh/why/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-is-a-large-format-camera&#34;&gt;What is a Large format camera ?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s grand-dad&amp;rsquo;s bellows box-like camera, where you had to disappear under a dark cloth. The principle remains the same, however nowadays they have evolved into precise and sophisticated instruments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With a few notable exceptions, these cameras share the following characteristics:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Large image size&lt;/strong&gt;: 4x5 inches (10x12cm), the most popular format by far, up to 20x24 inches (the Polaroid camera, which can be rented on-site for a reasonable fee). The film comes in separate sheets rather than rolls, but see below.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Flexible bellows connecting the front and back&lt;/strong&gt;: they allow the use of a range of focal lengths (with different lenses. there are no zooms in such formats) and focussing distances, as well as providing for lateral adjustments and angular adjustments between film plane and lens plane.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ground glass viewing&lt;/strong&gt;: makes it possible to assess the image with great accuracy once you get used to the dimness and inversion.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Interchangeable lenses&lt;/strong&gt;: you are not limited to a particular mount.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By contrast, Medium format cameras use roll-film which is 6cm wide so that the format available on those cameras are (all in cm) 4.5x6, 6x6, 6x7,6x9,6x12,6x17. Therefore they produce image whose size is less than that produced by large format cameras (hence the name). The vast majority of medium format cameras operate a bit like 35mm cameras (&amp;ldquo;small format&amp;rdquo;) and in particular don&amp;rsquo;t have features 2,3,4. However, a few medium format cameras share these features, and are also considered on this web site, since they actually operate like large format cameras. On the other hand, with almost all the large format cameras it is possible to use roll-film holders of various sizes and to therefore produce medium-format images.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-are-the-main-benefits-of-the-large-format-camera&#34;&gt;What are the main benefits of the large format camera ?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Larger image size.&lt;/strong&gt; Results are sharper, have a better tonality, and are grain-free. A 4x5 has 13 times the area of a 35mm frame. A 5x7 has 25 times that area. Contact printing gives an image whose delicacy cannot be matched by any enlargment, and allow a number of &amp;ldquo;alternative&amp;rdquo; processes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Camera movements.&lt;/strong&gt; You have more control on the final geometry of the photographed objects and of the perspective as well as on the areas of sharpness.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Individual sheets of film.&lt;/strong&gt; You can use as many types of film as you like easily, easily, including Polaroid, and process each sheet of film individually for optimum results. The latter point makes it possible to use Ansel Adams Zone System for black and white film.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contemplative approach.&lt;/strong&gt; You take your time for each image This is the flip-side of the drawbacks: you spend so much time on a single exposure, and invest so much effort in it that you&amp;rsquo;re compelled to think it through carefully and do it right.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-are-the-main-drawbacks-of-the-large-format-camera&#34;&gt;What are the main drawbacks of the large format camera ?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Everything is manual&lt;/strong&gt;. Most other cameras do some things automatically for us that we take for granted &amp;ndash; like preventing fogged film, double-exposures, non-exposures and so on. You need to remember to do things that were never an issue even with the most manual 35mm camera. As a result, &lt;a href=&#34;mistakes.html&#34;&gt;there are more ways to make mistakes than you could ever imagine.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Equipment and film:&lt;/strong&gt; the equipment is bulky, heavy (a good tripod is necessary) and relatively expensive. The cost per photograph is considerably higher than the same image in smaller format. Think of it as being proportional to the film area.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Larger magnification: longer focals are needed for the same angle of view:&lt;/strong&gt; The equivalent of a 24mm in 35mm is a &lt;sup&gt;75&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;90&lt;/sub&gt; lens in 4x5, a 120mm lens in 5x7. Depth of field is a serious problem. The cameras movements become &lt;em&gt;necessary&lt;/em&gt; to put everything in focus, and even though some subjects cannot be focussed entirely. Start thinking f32 where you thought f5.6 ! As a result you often get very long exposures, so wind shake (esp. with vegetation) and reciprocity failure begin to take their toll. Work which requires naturally a high degree of magnification, ie macro and tele-photo, is particularly impractical, the former because of the depth of field limitations, the second because lenses would have to be insanely long.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Everything takes a long time&lt;/strong&gt;:

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;loading/unloading your holders at home&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;moving around your heavy backpack or case and tripod&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;setting your camera&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;composing, esp. in low light with slow / wide-angle lenses (f8 max aperture is common)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;focussing: tricks are necessary to overcome the depth of field problem&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;exposing: long exposures are quite common.It is impractical to photograph quick action or candids, and even in landscape you&amp;rsquo;ll end up missing optimal conditions. Your productivity in terms of number of images (but not necessarily in terms of number of great images) will be very reduced. Think a dozen shots or less when you thought a few rolls. Even though your friends/spouse will complain about the waiting.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Besides, you&amp;rsquo;ll discover by yourself many quirks of Large format photography, like the fact that the dark cloth sometimes tend to fly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;A_little_too_windy_for_8x10.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;A_little_too_windy_for_8x10.small.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;font size=&#34;-1&#34;&gt;This is a photograph of my friend Charles attempting to use a darkcloth for focus and composition on a 8x10 . 40 mph winds were just a little to strong for the darkcloth. He ended up using the viewfinder and foot scale with this 300 mm setup. &lt;strong&gt;Mark Cieslikowski&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;pollack.html&#34;&gt;A vivid account by Michael Pollack&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;size&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-name-size-what-is-the-real-gain-compared-to-other-formats-a&#34;&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;size&#34;&gt;What is the real gain compared to other formats?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;size&#34;&gt;The consensus seems to be that as far as enlargements are concerned, the difference between 4x5 and 35mm is huge, but that the&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;quality.html&#34;&gt;difference between 4x5 and 6x7&lt;/a&gt; will show up only in big enlargements, 16x20 or larger. At 16x20 modern LF lenses have a slight edge due to reduced granularity and high contrast, above that, modern 4x5 wins due to granularity. However, you will see a bigger difference with format for B&amp;amp;W prints than with color prints. On the other hand, a &lt;a href=&#34;contact-print.html&#34;&gt;contact print&lt;/a&gt; has a special quality that some feel cannot be obtained by an enlargement. Contact printing is also the only way to work with some alternative process such as paladium/platinium, carbon, etc&amp;hellip;&lt;a name=&#34;price&#34;&gt;#### &lt;em&gt;Will I have to sell the house ?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Large format photography is actually not that expensive, especially&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;price-med.html&#34;&gt;compared to medium format photography&lt;/a&gt; (the prices for the 35mm market are influenced by the fact that it is quite consumer-oriented), and a good large format system can be built for no more than a good modern medium format system. There is also possibility to do large format on a budget. A fairly good 4x5 can be bought used for less than $500, and if you are willing to accept some limitations, you can get something which works for a couple hundred of dollars. The latest lenses are indeed very expensive, on the other hand there are a number of older lenses which are really inexpensive, a couple of hundred dollars or less. Most of the lenses will be totally appropriate for B&amp;amp;W work. They don&amp;rsquo;t have to be as sharp as lenses for smaller formats. Modern lenses, which will produce results virtually indistinguishable from the the latest designs, can be bought used for a rather reasonnable price. Since LF systems are usually not submitted to an heavy use like smaller formats, gear which is decades old will usually work fine. A great news is that as you have built a good set of lenses, when you upgrade to a better camera, you just keep them, and maybe change the lensboards. At one point I was hesitating between the Pentax 67 (one of the cheapest MF systems) and 4x5. One of the reasons which got me decided for the 4x5 was that the price of the 4x5 system was a little lower. Film looks expensive too, but you won&amp;rsquo;t shoot as many images as you used to. If you do color, you&amp;rsquo;ll probably have to have your film processed by a lab. The total cost of a 4x5 Velvia (film+processing) is less than $4, the cost of a 5x7 less than $8. On the other hand, B&amp;amp;W film home processed is quite cheap.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-to-find-more-information&#34;&gt;How to find more information ?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;books/&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Recommended books&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;: for instruction as well as inspiration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journals:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is only one journal devoted exclusively to large format: &lt;a&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://greenspun.com/ct/qtluong/photography/lf/why.html?send_to=http://www.viewcamera.com&#34;&gt;View Camera TM&lt;/a&gt;, published by Steve Simmons (&lt;a href=&#34;mailto:Largformat@aol.com&#34;&gt;Largformat@aol.com&lt;/a&gt;). The quality has been overall high compared to the mainstream magazines. Over the past few years, the magazine has concentrated on interviews and portfolios, in which the emphasis is on vision and photographs, rather than technique. Earlier in its history, the journal had more technical articles, but because it tries not to rehash topics which had been already published, the information really useful for LF beginners is limited in current issues. You could order back issues, but if you&amp;rsquo;re after technical basic material, you&amp;rsquo;d certainly be better served by &lt;a href=&#34;books/general.html&#34;&gt;books&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although not exclusively devoted to LF, &lt;a href=&#34;http://greenspun.com/ct/qtluong/photography/lf/why.html?send_to=http://www.phototechmag.com/&#34;&gt;Photo Techniques&lt;/a&gt; (USA) regulary runs more detailed reviews of LF equipment written by actual users, as well as excellent how-to articles on LF techniques.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Web Discussion forums:&lt;/strong&gt; The &lt;a href=&#34;http://lflf.surge.sh/lfforum&#34;&gt;LF Q&amp;amp;A forum&lt;/a&gt; associated on this site has proven to be the best place on the internet for discussion of LF related issues. It is very focussed, yet has the most active participation of any LF bulletin boards on the web. Other LF discussion forums on the web include: &lt;a href=&#34;http://greenspun.com/ct/qtluong/photography/lf/why.html?send_to=http://www.f32.net&#34;&gt;f32.net&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://greenspun.com/ct/qtluong/photography/lf/why.html?send_to=http://www.photo.net&#34;&gt;photo.net&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://greenspun.com/ct/qtluong/photography/lf/why.html?send_to=http://www.graflex.org/helpboard/&#34;&gt;graflex.org&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://greenspun.com/ct/qtluong/photography/lf/why.html?send_to=http://www.viewcamera.com/forum/&#34;&gt;view camera&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://greenspun.com/ct/qtluong/photography/lf/why.html?send_to=http://www.apug.org&#34;&gt;apug.org&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;PS. I started large format photography in 1993. There were a lot of things which were mysterious back then. After shooting thousands sheets of film, some of them are still mysterious, but I have beneficiated from advice of really knowlegeable persons on the net. I wrote this series in order to try and give back by answering the questions that I was myself asking a couple of years ago. It is written with location and field photography in mind. I have only very little knowledge about studio work.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Large Format Photography primer: equipment</title>
      <link>http://lflf.surge.sh/matos-begin.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 1999 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lflf.surge.sh/matos-begin.html</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;This article discusses what you need to start large format photography:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a camera&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;lens(es)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;film holders and film&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;tripod&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;accessories: darkcloth, focussing lupe, cable release, meter&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For an example of kit, see &lt;a href=&#34;camera-bag/&#34;&gt;inside my camera bag&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-camera&#34;&gt;The camera&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Think first about your intended application. 35mm cameras are universal, MF cameras and LF cameras are really more specialized. What kind of work are you going to do, and in which conditions ?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;which-format-to-use&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Which format to use ?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;roll-film&lt;/strong&gt; Shooting roll-film with a view camera is an interesting combination. There are cameras and backs which let you shoot 6x7, 6x9, 6x12, 6x17. Compared to 4x5, you don&amp;rsquo;t have to deal with sheet film, the cost is very low (lower than for 35mm actually, if the surface is considered), and there is a very wide choice of film. If you chose a 2x3 view camera, it can be actually cheaper than a lot of MF systems, and might not be heavier, especially if you buy lenses with small coverage. However, compared to convenentional MF systems, you gain &amp;ldquo;only&amp;rdquo; camera movements (their effect is not always very easy to judge on the small image area) and you loose a lot of ease of use (this might be a plus for folks willing to &amp;ldquo;slow down&amp;rdquo;). Another option that I find more interesting is to use a &lt;a href=&#34;#roll-film&#34;&gt;roll-film back&lt;/a&gt; with a 4x5 camera. There are 4x5 lightweight cameras wich are not much more heavy than 2x3 cameras. Then you can have the option of doing 4x5 if the opportunity looks very good. Speaking from my own experience and that of other folks, when you come home the 2x3 images will look a bit small if you have shot 4x5, and you will probably think that given the burden of carrying and operating a view camera, you&amp;rsquo;d rather have the big image. If you use a panoramic format like 6x12, this comparison might not apply.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4x5&lt;/strong&gt; This is in practice the smaller format where you can use sheet film (2x3 sheet film exists but is marginal). It is by far the most popular format, with lots of cameras, lenses (from 45mm to as long as the bellows will accomodate), film, different type of holders (including roll-film, polaroid, preloaded). For most people that&amp;rsquo;s the format of choice.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;5x7&lt;/strong&gt; The equipment is not really heavier than for 4x5: the lenses are most of the time the same, there are 6lbs cameras. It is mostly the holders which are bigger: they produce an image which is almost two times as large, but is more rectangular, in a format homothetic to 35mm and 6x9. It is large enough to produce decent contacts. but still small enough that it is relatively easy to enlarge. The only significant drawback comes from the scarcity of the film (as of summer 96, the only slide film available in the USA are Kodak EPP and EPR. Euro or Japaneese photographers have Fuji emulsions). One thing that I am really missing is the possibility to use Polaroid film, and quickloads. Processing and printing is more difficult to obtain with labs, and if you want a new color enlarger, you might have to buy a 8x10 enlarger. However, all these problems do not affect b&amp;amp;w photographers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;8x10 and larger&lt;/strong&gt; These formats gives you beautiful contact prints. Contact printing is required for some alternative process (like Platinium). The marginal quality over 4x5 or 5x7 obtained in enlargements is probably noticeable only for the extreme enlargements. The drawback is the size and weight of the equipment, as well as its cost. Older 8x10 cameras can be have for (relatively) cheap, and a Philips camera is not much heavier than some 4x5 cameras. However larger formats (sometimes called Ultra LF) require a considerable amount of work.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-features-to-look-for-in-a-camera&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;What features to look for in a camera ?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are a few things to consider. There are more discussions about the various trade-offs (wood vs metal, monorail vs flatbed, etc&amp;hellip;) elsewhere on the &lt;a href=&#34;./&#34;&gt;LF page&lt;/a&gt;. Remember that YOU have to find out what your priorities are first, and that not every camera, no matter how highly praised, is for everyone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Portable enough.&lt;/strong&gt; Whereas all the folding cameras are portable and have a reasonnable weight (3lbs - 7 lbs), some monorails are too heavy and bulky to be used in the field. There is a tradeoff here between portability and and versatility (possibility to use many focals and movements), and also rigidity. Usually, for the same features, a wooden camera will be lighter, but often less compact than an equivalent metal field camera.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Allow you to use your focals of choice&lt;/strong&gt; All the cameras do what they are designed for with a normal lens. However, with shorter and longer lenses difficulties might arise:

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Short focals&lt;/strong&gt;. Some flatbed cameras have very limited wide-angle abilities, due to:

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;large minimum extension,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;fixed bellows (the bellows compression will make movements impossible unless you have a wide-angle bellows which is shorter and more flexible)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;beds showing in the field of viewA recessed lensboard can make up for some problems by allowing a larger lens to film distance than the focal length of your lens. However, they are expensive ($150) and the controls of the lens become hard to reach. A monorail is usually more flexible, since all of them have a small minimum extension, wide-angle bellows. Depending on the nature of the tripod mount attachment, the rail showing in the field of view might or might not be a problem, but there are sometimes optional short rails.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Long focals&lt;/strong&gt;. A camera with bellows which are too short will not allow you to use long lenses, or to do close-ups. The cure for this problem are very limited. You can use on some cameras a combinations of front tilts, or get an extension board (opposite of a recessed board), but this will give you only a few additional centimeters. Here, again monorails are more flexible, since you can usually purchase a longer rail and extension bellows.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Enough movements for your type of photography.&lt;/strong&gt; The monorails have all the movements, whereas some type of flat bed cameras have almost none. Studio photography usually requires a great deal of image control, architecture requires shifts to maintain correct perspective. Landscape require the less movements, although to obtain adequate depth of field due to the fact that longer focals are needed for a given field of view, some tilts are often necessary.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rigidity and precision of alignment&lt;/strong&gt; This is all about sharpness. To shoot in windy conditions you need a camera which is rigid enough so that the standards won&amp;rsquo;t move (resulting in unsharp pictures). The locks have to be strong enough so that the standards don&amp;rsquo;t move when you insert the holder. Misalignements between standards or within the back standard to the film plane might cause misfocus in some areas of the image (although this is critical for reproduction work, I doubt that for real shooting it matters). Generally speaking, the metal cameras are more rigid and precisely aligned than the wooden cameras. The lighweight cameras are more likely to have problems here.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ease of operation.&lt;/strong&gt; Geared controls, positive and well placed locks, spirit levels, various scales, zero detents, smooth operation, rear focussing (very important for macro work), etc.., all help. If complicated adjustments are used, a &lt;a href=&#34;yaw.html&#34;&gt;yaw-free&lt;/a&gt; design might help. This feature is not relevant otherwise.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;which-is-best-wood-or-metal&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Which is best, wood, or metal ?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main advantage of wood (besides being cheaper to work) is that it is lighter. A consequence is that for the same weight you can make a bigger camera, which in turn will provide you more movements and more extension. A typical example are the Wisner and Canhams which are quite bulky (for 4x5 cameras) but offer more movements and bellows than any other field cameras. A metal camera using the same design would weight more than 11 lbs. Wood is also much better at dampening high-frequency vibration than any metal or metal alloy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Metal has technically many advantages. It is more rigid, which result in less flexing and low frequency vibrations. This is good for long extensions. It is more solid, resulting in a more durable camera. If your tripod is knocked over by the wind, a metal camera is quite likely to remain functional with a few scratches, whereas a wooden camera could be totally destroyed. My reversible wooden back broke at the edge, which would have been unlikely to happy with metal. The stability with respect to environmental conditions like humidity and temperature is also better (one day my Canham would focus quite smoothly, one day it would be quite sticky). Last, it is easier to implement small features on metal. Therefore metal cameras tend generally to be more compact, and to offer greater accessory systems like reflex hoods, etc&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;which-cameras-to-consider-to-get-started-on-a-budget&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Which cameras to consider to get started on a budget?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is best to buy used equipment. Shutterbug (dealers advertisements, classified, swap announces) and the net are good sources. Some recommended used stores with knowledgeable and honest people are Midwest Photo Exchange and Lens and Repro. There is not much which can go wrong on a large format camera which has not been seriously abused, since there are no delicate small high precision parts or electronics. Older cameras are well usable, but usually lack the convenience of more modern designs. Some of them are so beat-up that they lost their original rigidity. Another thing to watch for is pinholes in the bellows. A new bellows can always be installed, but the price might be a significant fraction of that of the cheaper cameras. Here are some suggestions (refer to the reviews for more details):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cheapest.&lt;/strong&gt; A Speed or Crown Graphic press camera (at the expense of movements, not a good choice if you are interested in perspective control or depth of field control. A basic monorail like Calumet CC-400, Omega, Graphic View II (at the expense of portability, at about 8 lbs., they are a little heavy and bulky for hiking), Bender (if you like woodworking). A Burke and James (good movements, more portable than a monorail, might be a bit ratty). $250.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cheap.&lt;/strong&gt; A new Calumet Cadet (a monorail camera). $400. Toyo 45cx. $450. A used lightweight wood-field (such as the Tachihara). $400-$500. A Technika III (metal, flatbed, adequate movements). $600.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Still reasonable.&lt;/strong&gt; A new lightweight wood-field (around $700), a used Wista, a used Zone VI. The new Arca-Swiss discovery (maybe too recent to find used) and the Sinar A1 (monorail cameras).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-lenses&#34;&gt;The lenses&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-to-look-for-in-a-lens&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;What to look for in a lens ?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Focal.&lt;/strong&gt; You are probably familiar with 35mm. Pick up your favorite focals and find the equivalent LF focals either using &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.mat.uc.pt/~rps/photos/angles.html&#34;&gt;Rui Salgueiro&amp;rsquo;s field-of-view calculator&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&#34;http://www-swiss.ai.mit.edu/philg/photo/lens-table.html&#34;&gt;Ed Scott&amp;rsquo; comparison tables&lt;/a&gt;. Note however that while 5x7 is homothetic to 35mm, 4x5 and 8x10 are both more squarish. More folks are happy with just one lens in the LF world than in 35mm. Personnally, I would tend to err on the wide side, since cropping is not too much of an issue.&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Coverage.&lt;/strong&gt; A lens projects an image circle which must be large enough to cover the film area without vignetting. The absolute minimun which is required is the diagonal of the format. If some movements are used, the diameter of the image circle has to be larger to cover the film area. The larger this circle is, the more movements you can do. In particular, it is easy to calculate how must shift you can get knowing the image circle and the format. The image circle is usually expressed in a millimeter diameter, at infinity, and at a specific aperture of f/16 or f/22. Stopping down might increase its diameter. Focussing to closer distances always does.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For general use, make sure to get enough to be able to do some movements, maybe around 180mm for 4x5 and around 230mm for 5x7. Applications like table top and architecture photography often require extensive movements and therefore larger image circles. Lenses with more coverage than you need will be heavy, big, and expensive.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Maximum aperture.&lt;/strong&gt; You won&amp;rsquo;t use a LF lens wide open, however a large maximum aperture ( f/4.5 or f/5.6) makes viewing and focussing easier, especially if you are indoors or like to photograph in low light. However, for a given focal length, the faster lens will be larger, heavier and more expensive.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Portability.&lt;/strong&gt; Be careful here. Lenses of same focal lengths vary &lt;em&gt;considerably&lt;/em&gt; in size and weight ! Make sure to see the lens before buying. Generally speaking focal length, coverage, and speed contribute to a big lens, all other factors being equal. That&amp;rsquo;s where modern lenses don&amp;rsquo;t necessarily shine. A significant portion of the weight and bulk can be due to the shutter. Longer focal lengths and/or faster lenses often come with a big #3.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Optical quality.&lt;/strong&gt; Basically all the modern lenses (current models from Fuji,Nikon, Rodenstock, Schneider) are good enough, and very difficult to distinguish from each other at the apertures used in practice. For color work, it is generally recommended to stick to those, or to relatively recent multicoated lenses, although a single coated lens properly shaded might work fine. This is less critical for B&amp;amp;W. For details, see &lt;a href=&#34;lenses-general.html&#34;&gt;a general discussion&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fit.&lt;/strong&gt; Some big lenses cannot be used with some field cameras or with some lensboards. Also, make sure you have enough belows. When using long focal lengths you may consider choosing a telephoto design lens (usually designated with a &amp;ldquo;T&amp;rdquo;) rather than a regular design lens of the same focal length. These lenses require approximatively &lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; of the bellows a regular lens would. However, they are usually more expensive, have less coverage, and behave a bit weird with respect to tilts. They are not necessarily more compact or lighter.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Working shutter.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a list of recommendations and tests, see &lt;a href=&#34;http://greenspun.com/ct/qtluong/photography/lf/lf.html?send_to=http://www.hevanet.com/cperez/testing.html&#34;&gt;http://www.hevanet.com/cperez/testing.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;film-and-holders&#34;&gt;Film and holders&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conventional-vs-preloaded-film-quickload-readyload-polaroid&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Conventional vs preloaded film (Quickload, Readyload, Polaroid)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can either use film that you load yourself in cut-film holders or preloaded film.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the first case, you need a dark and relatively clean place to load your film holders (might be a problem when travelling), and to unload them. Dust might be a problem, you have to clean your holders carefully. You cannot have too many holders. With a large number of holders, not only you&amp;rsquo;ll be sure not to run out of film ready to shoot, but you&amp;rsquo;ll have to reload less often, and you can keep exposed film in holders, which makes tracking easier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Readyloads are from Kodak, Quickloads from Fuji. The readyloads from Kodak hold two sheets of film, the Quickloads hold one. The film is in a paper packet that you put in a special holder (they are made by Kodak, Fuji, Polaroid). Polaroid film can be processed instantly or latter, inside the holder. The other films are processed normally in the lab. Here are the advantages of preloaded film:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No need to load and unload. Especially nice in the field.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Almost dust-free. Because they&amp;rsquo;re factory loaded in a clean room, the only dust you get on the film is the dust that lands on it after you pull the envelope/darkslide.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lighter/Less bulky. Preloaded film allows you to carry more ready-to-use film (although in the long run, if you are using lots of film, it will end up being heavier) since you don&amp;rsquo;t have the weight of individual film holders.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Easier to track after exposure. You can just write information on each packet.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main disadvantages are&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;more expensive (a sheet of conventional Velvia 4x5 costs $1.7 vs $2.6 for preloaded)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;only a limited number of emulsions are offered by Fuji (in particular no B&amp;amp;W film), Kodak, and Polaroid (the non-instant film is Fuji film).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Kodak system is known to suffer from light leaks&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Less sharp (maybe). In a Camera and Darkroom article, J.Englender writes that the preloaded system do not yield as sharp results as conventional holders due to film flatness problems (the best results are obtained with Graphmatics, then conventional holders, Fuji and Kodak holders, and Polaroid holders). Many people ignore that.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;if you have a lot of film to carry on a long trip, the enveloppes end up adding up.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The best results for the preloaded films seems to be obtained using the dedicated holder (Fuji and Kodak), although the Fuji Quickload work OK with the Polaroid holder. The new 545i holder is significantly lighter than the old 545 which was all metal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conventional-cut-film-holders&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Conventional cut-film holders&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you decide not to use the preloaded systems but instead buy your film in sheets and load it, you have the choice between regular film holders which hold one sheet on each side, and Grafmatics. Generally speaking, if you buy used holders, check them carefully for dust and light leaks problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wooden holders tend to slide better in wooden cameras, and are slightly lighter than plastic holders, but they cannot be found new. As far as new holders are concerned, most people use Fidelity or Lisco holders, which are the cheapest. Some brands make more expensive holders, but nobody has been able to prove that they yield sharper pictures in usual working conditions. The extremity of the dark slide is marked with two colors (black and white) and raised dots so that you can remember whether they contain blank film or exposed film. In addition, there is a tab which is supposed to keep the dark slide locked and prevent you from removing it accidentally, as well as help you identified loaded vs empty holders, but I have found that it tends to be quite unreliable. Riteway makes a holder with a button instead of the tab, which is an improvement, but it is not compatible with some cameras.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;holders.html#grafmatics&#34;&gt;Grafmatics&lt;/a&gt; are more light and compact, and allow you to shoot in a sequence, but the loading is more difficult, esp. if you want to unload after using a holder only partially. They can be bought only used.&lt;a name=&#34;roll-film&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-name-roll-film-roll-film-backs-a&#34;&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;roll-film&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Roll-film backs&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;roll-film&#34;&gt;Roll film backs are available for all roll-film sizes to 6x12 the most common being 6x7 and 6x9. There are two types of roll-film holders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Graflock-type holders&lt;/strong&gt;: Some 4x5 cameras have a back (Graflock, this standard was introduced on the Graflex cameras) where you remove the ground-glass assembly and replace it with a roll-film back. There are plenty of brands to chose from: Graflex, Singer, Linhof (super-rollex), Mamiya RB, Horseman, some of which can be found for quite cheap.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Slide-in type holders&lt;/strong&gt;: These holders are flat because the film spools are at one end. They can be inserted under the ground glass like a sheet film holder. Almost all the cameras accept them, but be sure to check for compatibility. The Calumet holders are quite cheap and are now produced in 6x7, 6x9, 6x12 (the latter is quite expensive actually). Sinar has a vario holder which allow you to switch format (from 6x4.5 to 6x12) at any time, for $2500 new.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Personnally I prefer the second type, because I find them faster to use and it is said that the film flatness is better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;polaroid-film&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Polaroid film&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Polaroid film is a great learning tool because you get instant feedback. Some people recommend that when you start 4x5 you expose Polaroids to begin. Another special application is proofing, to check composition, exposure (esp. with flash), and focus (by luping the negative). But Polaroid material has its own photographic merits, and can yield beautiful prints and negatives. It has been used as a medium by some masters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To use Polaroid film, all you need is a 4x5 camera, and a Polaroid holder. The sheet film holders are model 545 (older, metal construction) or 545i (current, plastic construction, lighter). They are reasonnably sized so they can also be used with Quickload (and maybe Readyloads, although the failure rate is catastrophic). There are two other Polaroid holders, for pack film, the 550 which accepts 4x5&amp;rdquo; pack film and the 405 which uses 3 1/4x 4 &lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;&amp;rdquo; pack film. Packs film are cheaper, but the film area is smaller than 4x5, so that makes them useful mostly for checking exposure. Personally I would just go for the 4x5 image given by the 545 (which is already a bit smaller than 4x5)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Polaroid also makes material for 8x10 cameras, but it is quite pricey and you also need a special processor, unlike in 4x5 where the holder serves as the processor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;roll-film&#34;&gt;For more information, call Polaroid to get a free guide to their film. I have personally found type 52 (gives a beautiful print), type 54 (gives a print not as beautiful, but which does not require coating), and type 55 (gives a print AND a negative), and type 56 (gives a beautiful sepia print) useful. Unfortunately with type 55, the negative is about 1.5 stops slower than the print, so you cannot get both well-exposed. The negative needs also a good cleaning to remain usable.&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;polaroid55.html&#34;&gt;More details on 55&lt;/a&gt;. All these materials are B&amp;amp;W. I don&amp;rsquo;t have too much experience with the color materials, but I heard they are quite sensitive to heat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-tripod&#34;&gt;The tripod&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-to-look-for-in-a-tripod&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;What to look for in a tripod ?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;portability&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;stability/rigidity&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;working height&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ease of use&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first and second points are contradicting, and therefore you have to compromise. A reasonnable choice would be something like a Gitzo series 300 or equivalent. A Gitzo series 400 would hold any view camera. A series 200 would be considered by many to be marginal, but I find it quite usable (see below). Quite a few people use wooden tripods. While it is said that they damp vibrations better than metal tripod, I find that their only real advantage is ruggedness (due actually to a simpler construction, rather than material), and warmer feel. On the other hand, with respect to the four previous points, for a given weight, the metal tripod is always better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;do-i-have-to-get-a-monster-tripod-for-this-large-format-camera&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Do I have to get a monster tripod for this large format camera ?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You don&amp;rsquo;t necessarily need a tripod bigger than the one you use for your small camera. I used to have a very heavy tripod (Zone VI, 16 lbs, ouch !) that i used next to the car, and a Gitzo 226 for hiking and traveling. Since then, i have sold my Zone VI, and use exclusively the Gitzo 1228 with a Linhof Profi II ball head. The combination weights 4lbs, and is quite usable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reasons why I think that a light tripod such that the 1228 is plenty adequate for my LF use are the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The real issue is the rigidity of the legs, NOT the weight of the tripod. With this respect, the Gitzos are pretty good. For the weight, I carry plenty enough. I have put a ring at the bottom of the center column, and attach by camera bag to it. The combo has a heavy weight that cannot be beat !&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Some medium format or even 35mm settups are in fact heavier than my LF, but I see NO reason why a heavier camera would require a heavier tripod (as long as it does not collapse, of course). Since regardless of the format, blur due to camera shake is mostly a function of focal length, I would tend to say that very stable tripods are needed mostly for very long lenses. Thus if the 1228 is sufficient to hold a 300mm lens for a 35mm camera (and it is), then it is also sufficient to hold a 300m for a 4x5 in still conditions. Most of my LF photography is done with 120 and 210 mm lenses.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;tripod-head-with-qr-system&#34;&gt;Tripod head with QR system&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A pan-tilt head is more convenient, because it is more easy to level the camera, and you can tilt the camera front to back without unwanted sideway tilt. If your camera does not have levels, it would be useful to have them on your head. A quick release system is very nice to have. Unfortunately the smallest PT head made by Manfrotto which meets all these requirements is the 3047, and although it is nice to use, it weights almost as much as my Gitzo 1228. I also have a smaller PT head, the 3029, but it does not have a built-in QR system, and i find it becomes quite bulky if I attach one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mostly because of the weight and bulk savings, many photographers use ball heads. An other benefit is that they work better for 35mm and MF if you use a second format. The Linhof Profi II is good enough for most lightweight LF cameras, however, the heavier and more expensive Arca-Swiss B1 is more rigid, smoother, and has an elliptic ball to prevent flip-over.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A Quick Release (QR) system is not absolutely necessary, but very nice to have, especially if you switch between different formats. You can buy a Manfrotto/Bogen adaptator to use the Bogen hex plates with several ball heads by replacing the stock platform. The spring-loaded Bogen QR system is inexpensive, quick and easy to operate, lock positively and well thanks to the hexagonal shape. If tightened enough, the plates won&amp;rsquo;t slip. However, if you are using at the same time smaller cameras, you might prefer the Arca Swiss system, where you slip the camera plate into a dovetail. With that system, camera plates can be custom made for each camera, which ensures a better fit, while the Bogen plates tend to stick out from small camera bodies. Don&amp;rsquo;t get the generic plates from Arca-Swiss. That would negate most of the advantages of the system ! Really Right Stuff is generally thought to make better fitting plates than Kirk Enterprises.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;accessories&#34;&gt;Accessories&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;darkcloth&#34;&gt;Darkcloth&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can use a jacket, but a dark cloth is preferable and does not cost much anyway compared to the price of the rest of the equipment. A cloth with a white exterior is nice on hot days or if photographing on a busy site. Personnally I don&amp;rsquo;t like those which have weight (ie Zone VI) because if it gets really windy they can fly around and break the ground glass, plus they tend to add weight. A Velcro on the side which is used arround the camera is nice to maintain it in place. For good viewing of the image with slow lenses, I have found that a second velcro is called. One part of the velcro is on the left side of the cloth, the other one on the right side, so that you can close totally the cloth (light coming from under the cloth is otherwise quite distracting). Darkroom Innovations have taken this idea seriously and makes a darkcloth with an elasticized collar that fits around the camera and a velcro-closed slit that you can close totally for excellent darkness. The choice of material makes it light and windproof. It&amp;rsquo;s better than any other darkcloth that I have seen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;focussing-aid&#34;&gt;Focussing aid&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Except maybe in 8x10, don&amp;rsquo;t trust the naked eye to focus critically. A lupe with a medium magnification, not too big, not too expensive, is the best here. This eliminates the lupes which are usually used for viewing slides on light tables. Unlike in that situation, to focus the view camera you don&amp;rsquo;t need a high quality lupe. On the other hand, there are a few practical requirements: its skirt does not prevent from viewing the corners, it is focussable so that you can make sure it is focussed on the ground glass, and it has attachement for a string so that you can dangle it around your neck. I like the Calumet lupe (7x) for its small size and good magnification. It works well with my very fine-grained Boss Screen but when I had the coarser Canham stock screen, I found it easier to focus with the Toyo (4x). Some people like cheap +4 dioptre glasses. Ron Wisner uses (and sells) a linen tester (an inexpensive folding magnifier that you put in your pocket, and which can be angled for good corner viewing). &amp;ldquo;Hastings Triplets&amp;rdquo; used by geologists are similar, but more powerful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;cable-release&#34;&gt;Cable release&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to avoid loosing them or spending time to screw/unscrew them, I have a cable release permanently attached to each of my lenses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;meter&#34;&gt;Meter&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Pentax digital spot meter seems to be popular with large format photographers. It is relatively small and light, reliable, and has easy controls and viewfinder readings. Recently the multi-purpose Sekonic Zoom-master has been succesfull, because it combines incident and flash with spot. However it is more complex and does not have viewfinder displays.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Personnally I use my 35mm camera. I like to have the small camera to be able to shoot quickly should something change suddently and produce many images for stock. I also use it as a viewfinder so I don&amp;rsquo;t have to move the tripod around. When I am in a hurry, I use the matrix metering, otherwise I use the a built-in spot meter with the &lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; stop analog scale in the viewfinder. I just set the same shutter speed and f-stop I intend to use on the LF camera, and then see where different part of the scene fall. Cameras with such a scale include the Nikon N8008s, F4, F5, F100 (N90 has only a f1 stop scale), and most canons, including the Rebel 2000 and the EOS 3. If I use the polarizer on the LF camera, I just put a polariser on my 35mm lens. The 24-120 or 24-85 lenses matches all the 4 focals that I commonly use on the LF camera.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;better-focussing-screen&#34;&gt;Better focussing screen&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can replace the focussing screen which comes with your camera, or supplement it with a fresnel lens to obtain a brighter and/or sharper image. After several screens, I have found the Boss screen to be by far the best.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>