<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Large Format Photography</title>
    <link>http://lflf.surge.sh/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content on Large Format Photography</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 01 Apr 2015 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://lflf.surge.sh/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Shooting LF is not difficult, from MF to LF</title>
      <link>http://lflf.surge.sh/from-mf-to-lf/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Apr 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lflf.surge.sh/from-mf-to-lf/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;With analog camera and lens prices down to levels no one could have dreamt of as little as twenty years ago, the introduction of digital cameras has opened the door to all kinds of exotic equipment for those who choose to shoot film. However, there seems to be a significant barrier to entry. It does not seem to dissuade easily people from getting into 35mm, but certainly holds them back when they consider buying into MF equipment. From there, even very seasoned photographers seem to view LF as a nigh impossible step. Are the barriers really that high and is the difference that large?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;the-choice-to-work-with-film&#34;&gt;The choice to work with film&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regardless of the size you choose to work with, there is a very conscious choice involved in shooting film. Quite to the contrary of the general availability and affordability of great photographic equipment, film, places that process it or stock chemicals to do it at home have become scarcer and more expensive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many photographers these days have very possibly never even owned or photographed with any analog camera, let alone system. With photographing, I mean consciously taking a picture, carefully evaluating variables such as film type and speed, lighting, aperture and shutter settings, etc. As such, this is not counting the classic 35mm point and shoot cameras offering only full auto mode. To them, LF may not be the way to go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For those who grew up with film or who shot it for artistic purposes, digital has often been a blessing or a necessary evil. Even though my first camera was a Pentax Spotmatic, followed by various Nikon 35mm film cameras, I too, at some stage abandoned film. As a wildlife photographer, the flexibility, cheap high volume workflow, and the possibility to share pretty much as soon as I shot, meant that digital was great, and film was as good as dead. Or so I thought.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As time passed and I, like many of you, kept upgrading to newer generations of digital cameras, I sometime glanced at analog gear. Remembering the luscious, saturated Velvia colors projected on the wall, I started buying and shooting analog again. First in 35mm (Nikon F6, Contax G2 kits, Leica M6), but soon I was shooting all sorts of MF equipment too (Mamiya 7 and 645 Pro TL, Hasselblad 501C, Fuji GW690II, GW690III, GA645Zi, Bronica ETRSi, GS-1, Pentax 645N and others). MF rapidly overtook 35mm for me as the creative and print possibilities it offers are much greater.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the years, I increasingly started to shoot black and white film in addition to Velvia. The satisfaction of projecting the large slides on the wall or watching them on a light table is so hard to describe. Then at some stage, you take identical or similar shots with your digital camera and on Velvia. Once processed and on the screen, there is a difference between night and day. What more reason do you need to shoot film? Motivations and purposes will differ, but we all have our reason to shoot film and I strongly feel film has a solid place in today&amp;rsquo;s world of photography.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;medium-format-or-large-format&#34;&gt;Medium format or large format&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The basic assumption for the purpose of this article is that your photography lends itself to both formats and that you currently probably shoot MF in addition to another system. Whether it is landscape, fashion, portrait or other, medium and large format have many specializations in which both could work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a nutshell, medium format gear is often comparatively portable. Add to this that quite a few cameras can be shot hand-held that eliminates the need for a tripod and offers flexibility. This makes for quite a compelling proposition. However, large format offers the big advantage of the larger negative or slide and in many cases the movements of the camera that open a whole new world of creative possibilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For those of us who are willing or routinely carry a tripod and a heavy pack of gear, large format seems to be a great choice. Still, many people do not take the leap. The hurdle appears to be high, which is a shame.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;the-large-format-hurdle&#34;&gt;The large format hurdle&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So your work could potentially benefit from the creative freedom of a large format system, or you are addicted to the big negatives and slides like many of us. You look at classifieds and eBay listings and see the greatest of gear, but just can not make up your mind to buy into it. My question is, why not? Assuming you have shot film before and are familiar with camera basics, the hurdle is much lower than you think. In random order:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Large format is expensive.&lt;/strong&gt; If you have read until here, you have probably also looked at classifieds. If you have, you will have noticed that a great LF set-up costs less than an enthusiast level digital camera (monorail cameras including a simple lens, a few film holders and some bits and bobs sell for as little as 300 euros on Ebay and locally! A full wooden LF field kit can be had for 750 euros if you are patient). The difference is that the LF equipment is not a direct write-off, but should sell for similar money in the future if looked after carefully.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Where to start?&lt;/strong&gt; There is so much gear on sale that finding a first camera can be confusing. This is true to an extend, however, if you carefully think about what you want to shoot and where, life becomes a lot simpler. If you want to shoot in a studio and want maximum movement, monorails are great and sell for ridiculously little money (cameras without accessories from anywhere as low as 200 euros). If you want portability, any of the wooden field cameras will be great (I just saw an &amp;ldquo;as new&amp;rdquo; Shen Hao field for 500 euros). And if you insist on hand held shooting, old press cameras are an option (anywhere from 150 euros and up depending on their condition), as are several modern developments. From there you can always migrate to bigger or better. Chances are that if you stick to the same format, all lenses (and probably lens boards too) and film holders will be directly compatible. Your light meter, focusing loupe, dark cloth and so on will also continue to serve you well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Large format is heavy.&lt;/strong&gt; While not lightweight, an LF system can very much be as heavy or light as you want. This depends on size, types and numbers of lenses and holders, tripod, etc. I have never accurately weighed my travel kit (wooden field camera, three lenses, 10 holders, boxes of sheet film, changing tent, light meter, focusing loupe, etc), but it comes in at around twenty five pounds, including the thinktank bag it all fits into.My full Hasselblad MF kit including three lenses, several backs, two bodies and accessories weighs about the same. In contrast, my digital wildlife kit is significantly heavier, at around thirty-five pounds (although I can shave a few pounds off by leaving the super tele at home). My &amp;ldquo;ultralight&amp;rdquo; LF kit consists of a wista field, 6 film holders, three lenses (75mm, 150mm, 210mm), a loupe, light meter and some bits and bobs. It fits in a think tank sling back and comes in between ten and twelve pounds! Granted, thereÕs a tripod that is carried separately, but there are plenty of lightweight alternatives with simple ballheads or level heads available.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Large format is too complicated.&lt;/strong&gt; Technical cameras, unlike the technical aspects of a space shuttle, are not very complicated at all. Yes, they do require some time and effort to learn, but there are always people there to help, like on this forum. In addition, there are great books such as &amp;ldquo;Using the view camera&amp;rdquo; that provide excellent information on how to use your camera and its movements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Film and supplies are hard to come by.&lt;/strong&gt; It is true that it is unlikely that your local photo shop stock sheet film and other supplies. However, there are many great sources online where you can order sheet film in many formats as well as pretty much anything else you could need or want.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;No access to a darkroom.&lt;/strong&gt; While needed for printing your photos, you do not need one to load and develop sheet film. Most of the people here probably do not have access to a full dark room. Instead, they work with changing tents or bags and daylight developing tanks. There work great and are widely available. Harrison tents are nice and pack very compact, but I have found loading my expert drums easier in a Calumet pop-up tent that sells for around 90 euros.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Developing film is prohibitively expensive or unavailable in my area.&lt;/strong&gt; This is the case for many photographers. There are probably professional laboratories in your country of residence that will receive and return film by mail for processing. This, however, can indeed be expensive (I am not sure about other countries, but the cheapest I have found in the Netherlands is 4.5 euros ex-vat and shipping for a 4x5 sheet). However, developing your own film is quite easy. Particularly if you choose to shoot black and white (My total costs for a drum with 6 sheets of B&amp;amp;W films is around 1,25 euros and includes developer, stop batch, fixer and a few drops of photo flow). Color (slide) film is somewhat more complicated but do-able. If developing seems too daunting, why not take a darkroom course. You will learn how to do it and have the confidence to experiment at home. And if you ask nicely, you may very well meet someone who is willing to show you how itÕs done for free.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;in-conclusion&#34;&gt;In conclusion&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Large format has much to offer and provides great creative possibilities when compared to small and medium format alternatives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If your photography lends itself to working with large format film, or if you desire to print large, there is little reason not to try.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is no mystique to LF and hurdles to a switch to LF are much lower in real life than they may seem when reading about them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Basic photographic principles apply, just like they do for any other format. If you are familiar with them, you will feel comfortable with an LF camera.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is no such thing as mutual exclusivity. I for one continue to shoot digital, MF and LF. Each of the systems has its merits. View them as complementary, rather than incompatible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And finally, yes, people will look at you when you shoot a LF camera. Most people will just look surprised, however, if you get any, reactions are almost always positive.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Large Format Primer</title>
      <link>http://lflf.surge.sh/why/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Apr 2001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lflf.surge.sh/why/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-is-a-large-format-camera&#34;&gt;What is a Large format camera ?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s grand-dad&amp;rsquo;s bellows box-like camera, where you had to disappear under a dark cloth. The principle remains the same, however nowadays they have evolved into precise and sophisticated instruments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With a few notable exceptions, these cameras share the following characteristics:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Large image size&lt;/strong&gt;: 4x5 inches (10x12cm), the most popular format by far, up to 20x24 inches (the Polaroid camera, which can be rented on-site for a reasonable fee). The film comes in separate sheets rather than rolls, but see below.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Flexible bellows connecting the front and back&lt;/strong&gt;: they allow the use of a range of focal lengths (with different lenses. there are no zooms in such formats) and focussing distances, as well as providing for lateral adjustments and angular adjustments between film plane and lens plane.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ground glass viewing&lt;/strong&gt;: makes it possible to assess the image with great accuracy once you get used to the dimness and inversion.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Interchangeable lenses&lt;/strong&gt;: you are not limited to a particular mount.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By contrast, Medium format cameras use roll-film which is 6cm wide so that the format available on those cameras are (all in cm) 4.5x6, 6x6, 6x7,6x9,6x12,6x17. Therefore they produce image whose size is less than that produced by large format cameras (hence the name). The vast majority of medium format cameras operate a bit like 35mm cameras (&amp;ldquo;small format&amp;rdquo;) and in particular don&amp;rsquo;t have features 2,3,4. However, a few medium format cameras share these features, and are also considered on this web site, since they actually operate like large format cameras. On the other hand, with almost all the large format cameras it is possible to use roll-film holders of various sizes and to therefore produce medium-format images.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-are-the-main-benefits-of-the-large-format-camera&#34;&gt;What are the main benefits of the large format camera ?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Larger image size.&lt;/strong&gt; Results are sharper, have a better tonality, and are grain-free. A 4x5 has 13 times the area of a 35mm frame. A 5x7 has 25 times that area. Contact printing gives an image whose delicacy cannot be matched by any enlargment, and allow a number of &amp;ldquo;alternative&amp;rdquo; processes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Camera movements.&lt;/strong&gt; You have more control on the final geometry of the photographed objects and of the perspective as well as on the areas of sharpness.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Individual sheets of film.&lt;/strong&gt; You can use as many types of film as you like easily, easily, including Polaroid, and process each sheet of film individually for optimum results. The latter point makes it possible to use Ansel Adams Zone System for black and white film.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contemplative approach.&lt;/strong&gt; You take your time for each image This is the flip-side of the drawbacks: you spend so much time on a single exposure, and invest so much effort in it that you&amp;rsquo;re compelled to think it through carefully and do it right.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-are-the-main-drawbacks-of-the-large-format-camera&#34;&gt;What are the main drawbacks of the large format camera ?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Everything is manual&lt;/strong&gt;. Most other cameras do some things automatically for us that we take for granted &amp;ndash; like preventing fogged film, double-exposures, non-exposures and so on. You need to remember to do things that were never an issue even with the most manual 35mm camera. As a result, &lt;a href=&#34;mistakes.html&#34;&gt;there are more ways to make mistakes than you could ever imagine.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Equipment and film:&lt;/strong&gt; the equipment is bulky, heavy (a good tripod is necessary) and relatively expensive. The cost per photograph is considerably higher than the same image in smaller format. Think of it as being proportional to the film area.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Larger magnification: longer focals are needed for the same angle of view:&lt;/strong&gt; The equivalent of a 24mm in 35mm is a &lt;sup&gt;75&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;90&lt;/sub&gt; lens in 4x5, a 120mm lens in 5x7. Depth of field is a serious problem. The cameras movements become &lt;em&gt;necessary&lt;/em&gt; to put everything in focus, and even though some subjects cannot be focussed entirely. Start thinking f32 where you thought f5.6 ! As a result you often get very long exposures, so wind shake (esp. with vegetation) and reciprocity failure begin to take their toll. Work which requires naturally a high degree of magnification, ie macro and tele-photo, is particularly impractical, the former because of the depth of field limitations, the second because lenses would have to be insanely long.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Everything takes a long time&lt;/strong&gt;:

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;loading/unloading your holders at home&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;moving around your heavy backpack or case and tripod&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;setting your camera&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;composing, esp. in low light with slow / wide-angle lenses (f8 max aperture is common)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;focussing: tricks are necessary to overcome the depth of field problem&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;exposing: long exposures are quite common.It is impractical to photograph quick action or candids, and even in landscape you&amp;rsquo;ll end up missing optimal conditions. Your productivity in terms of number of images (but not necessarily in terms of number of great images) will be very reduced. Think a dozen shots or less when you thought a few rolls. Even though your friends/spouse will complain about the waiting.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Besides, you&amp;rsquo;ll discover by yourself many quirks of Large format photography, like the fact that the dark cloth sometimes tend to fly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;A_little_too_windy_for_8x10.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;A_little_too_windy_for_8x10.small.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;font size=&#34;-1&#34;&gt;This is a photograph of my friend Charles attempting to use a darkcloth for focus and composition on a 8x10 . 40 mph winds were just a little to strong for the darkcloth. He ended up using the viewfinder and foot scale with this 300 mm setup. &lt;strong&gt;Mark Cieslikowski&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;pollack.html&#34;&gt;A vivid account by Michael Pollack&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;size&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-name-size-what-is-the-real-gain-compared-to-other-formats-a&#34;&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;size&#34;&gt;What is the real gain compared to other formats?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;size&#34;&gt;The consensus seems to be that as far as enlargements are concerned, the difference between 4x5 and 35mm is huge, but that the&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;quality.html&#34;&gt;difference between 4x5 and 6x7&lt;/a&gt; will show up only in big enlargements, 16x20 or larger. At 16x20 modern LF lenses have a slight edge due to reduced granularity and high contrast, above that, modern 4x5 wins due to granularity. However, you will see a bigger difference with format for B&amp;amp;W prints than with color prints. On the other hand, a &lt;a href=&#34;contact-print.html&#34;&gt;contact print&lt;/a&gt; has a special quality that some feel cannot be obtained by an enlargement. Contact printing is also the only way to work with some alternative process such as paladium/platinium, carbon, etc&amp;hellip;&lt;a name=&#34;price&#34;&gt;#### &lt;em&gt;Will I have to sell the house ?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Large format photography is actually not that expensive, especially&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;price-med.html&#34;&gt;compared to medium format photography&lt;/a&gt; (the prices for the 35mm market are influenced by the fact that it is quite consumer-oriented), and a good large format system can be built for no more than a good modern medium format system. There is also possibility to do large format on a budget. A fairly good 4x5 can be bought used for less than $500, and if you are willing to accept some limitations, you can get something which works for a couple hundred of dollars. The latest lenses are indeed very expensive, on the other hand there are a number of older lenses which are really inexpensive, a couple of hundred dollars or less. Most of the lenses will be totally appropriate for B&amp;amp;W work. They don&amp;rsquo;t have to be as sharp as lenses for smaller formats. Modern lenses, which will produce results virtually indistinguishable from the the latest designs, can be bought used for a rather reasonnable price. Since LF systems are usually not submitted to an heavy use like smaller formats, gear which is decades old will usually work fine. A great news is that as you have built a good set of lenses, when you upgrade to a better camera, you just keep them, and maybe change the lensboards. At one point I was hesitating between the Pentax 67 (one of the cheapest MF systems) and 4x5. One of the reasons which got me decided for the 4x5 was that the price of the 4x5 system was a little lower. Film looks expensive too, but you won&amp;rsquo;t shoot as many images as you used to. If you do color, you&amp;rsquo;ll probably have to have your film processed by a lab. The total cost of a 4x5 Velvia (film+processing) is less than $4, the cost of a 5x7 less than $8. On the other hand, B&amp;amp;W film home processed is quite cheap.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-to-find-more-information&#34;&gt;How to find more information ?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;books/&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Recommended books&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;: for instruction as well as inspiration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journals:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is only one journal devoted exclusively to large format: &lt;a&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://greenspun.com/ct/qtluong/photography/lf/why.html?send_to=http://www.viewcamera.com&#34;&gt;View Camera TM&lt;/a&gt;, published by Steve Simmons (&lt;a href=&#34;mailto:Largformat@aol.com&#34;&gt;Largformat@aol.com&lt;/a&gt;). The quality has been overall high compared to the mainstream magazines. Over the past few years, the magazine has concentrated on interviews and portfolios, in which the emphasis is on vision and photographs, rather than technique. Earlier in its history, the journal had more technical articles, but because it tries not to rehash topics which had been already published, the information really useful for LF beginners is limited in current issues. You could order back issues, but if you&amp;rsquo;re after technical basic material, you&amp;rsquo;d certainly be better served by &lt;a href=&#34;books/general.html&#34;&gt;books&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although not exclusively devoted to LF, &lt;a href=&#34;http://greenspun.com/ct/qtluong/photography/lf/why.html?send_to=http://www.phototechmag.com/&#34;&gt;Photo Techniques&lt;/a&gt; (USA) regulary runs more detailed reviews of LF equipment written by actual users, as well as excellent how-to articles on LF techniques.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Web Discussion forums:&lt;/strong&gt; The &lt;a href=&#34;http://lflf.surge.sh/lfforum&#34;&gt;LF Q&amp;amp;A forum&lt;/a&gt; associated on this site has proven to be the best place on the internet for discussion of LF related issues. It is very focussed, yet has the most active participation of any LF bulletin boards on the web. Other LF discussion forums on the web include: &lt;a href=&#34;http://greenspun.com/ct/qtluong/photography/lf/why.html?send_to=http://www.f32.net&#34;&gt;f32.net&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://greenspun.com/ct/qtluong/photography/lf/why.html?send_to=http://www.photo.net&#34;&gt;photo.net&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://greenspun.com/ct/qtluong/photography/lf/why.html?send_to=http://www.graflex.org/helpboard/&#34;&gt;graflex.org&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://greenspun.com/ct/qtluong/photography/lf/why.html?send_to=http://www.viewcamera.com/forum/&#34;&gt;view camera&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://greenspun.com/ct/qtluong/photography/lf/why.html?send_to=http://www.apug.org&#34;&gt;apug.org&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;PS. I started large format photography in 1993. There were a lot of things which were mysterious back then. After shooting thousands sheets of film, some of them are still mysterious, but I have beneficiated from advice of really knowlegeable persons on the net. I wrote this series in order to try and give back by answering the questions that I was myself asking a couple of years ago. It is written with location and field photography in mind. I have only very little knowledge about studio work.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>