<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Technicals on Large Format Photography</title>
    <link>http://lflf.surge.sh/technical/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Technicals on Large Format Photography</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://lflf.surge.sh/technical/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>http://lflf.surge.sh/technical/1800F-bw/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lflf.surge.sh/technical/1800F-bw/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h2 id=&#34;scanning-black-and-white-negative-film-with-the-microtek-artixscan-1800f&#34;&gt;Scanning black and white negative film with the Microtek Artixscan 1800F&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.srosenberg.com/&#34;&gt;Scott Rosenberg&lt;/a&gt; © 2005 for
&lt;a href=&#34;http://lflf.surge.sh/&#34;&gt;largeformatphotography.info&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Introduction:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;T&lt;/strong&gt;he digital workflow is pretty much ubiquitous in the world of fine
art color photography these days. The technology has gotten so good that
we are now able to produce prints with a vibrancy and clarity never
before possible. Modern scanning and printing technologies have gotten
so good, in fact, that for the first time since slide film has been
available, prints are actually starting to rival transparencies. While
reflected media will never look exactly like transmitted media, the
digital workflow of today is enabling photographers to produce prints
closer to their originals than ever before.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
After seeing what was possible with the new digital darkroom, I quickly
embraced the workflow for my color printing. Initially, however, I was
less enthusiastic about making black and white prints using these same
technologies. To my eye, I still preferred prints made in a traditional
darkroom. However, after recently seeing black and white prints from the
latest in digital printing, I feel like that gap has been bridged
considerably, and set out to determine how best to scan black and white
negatives using my Microtek Artixscan 1800F.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
To gather a list of best practices, I spoke to several photographers
whose work I admire and who are printing black and white images from
digital files made from film. While most are using the same scanner as
I, their individual methodologies shared little else. I therefore
decided to start from square one, consider every possibility I could
think of, and let the results speak for themselves. It should be noted
that there will always be sources of variation that can not be
controlled, and my findings are specific to the equipment, myself
included, in my personal workflow. In other words, your mileage may
vary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Experimental Design:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;H&lt;/strong&gt;aving not much else to go on, I decided to scan a sheet of black
and white film every way my scanner was capable of:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
                     1. As a Black and White Negative&lt;br /&gt;
                     2. As a Black and White Positive&lt;br /&gt;
                     3. As a Color Negative&lt;br /&gt;
                     4. As a Color Positive&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Since I set out to determine the scanning workflow that will lead to the
finest print, and not the amount of input required post scanning, I
worked with each file until I got that individual image to look just as
I would want it to before having it printed, taking care to get all the
files as closely matched as possible. Positive scans would have to be
inverted; color scans would have each of their three channels (Red,
Green, Blue) evaluated to determine which one yielded superior results.
I worked on each file as I would any other in preparation for printing,
and while no prints were made, these master files were then scrutinized
and a best practice was decided upon.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Since I was primarily interested in assessing my scanners capability
regarding tone and resolution of fine detail, I selected the image shown
below, as it contains a full range of tonal values, from the deep
shadows found under the porch to the bright whites of the dogwood
blooms, as well as some very fine elements in the detail of the
rough-cut timbers and the bark of the trees.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.srosenberg.com/Website7/images/dagorbarn1800f.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Farmhouse and Dogwood&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A Comparison of the Color Channels:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;T&lt;/strong&gt;he first thing I wanted to check was if there was a difference in
the red, green, and blue channels in the color scans. Since the final
print would be black and white, I could use any one of these three
channels independently of the other two, or use all three simply by
converting the RGB image to greyscale. Shown below are detail scans
illustrating each channel, as well as the RGB image once converted to
greyscale.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.srosenberg.com/Website7/images/ChannelsQT.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Red, Blue, Green, and RGB Channel Comparison&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The green channel, while a little grainier, clearly has retained the
most detail. Remember, these scans represent a very small area of the
overall image, and as such, the increased grain apparent in the green
channel is not really a concern, as it will be completely undetectable
in the final print.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Now that the sharpest channel of the color scans has been determined, we
can take a look at how the black and white scans compare to the green
channel of the color scans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Detail Scans and Conclusions:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;H&lt;/strong&gt;aving determined that the green channel from the color scans was in
fact the sharpest, I now set out to compare it to the black and white
scans. Shown below are detail scans illustrating how the black and white
scans compared to the green channel alone of the color scans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.srosenberg.com/Website7/images/dagorbarnbarkQT.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Detail Scans Comparing All Four Master Files&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These scans are slices from the tree to the right of the farmhouse. The
slices from the color scans clearly show more texture and detail than
those scanned as black and white. It is difficult to tell at this size,
but when enlarged further, the color positive scan shows the most
detail.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These scans are slices from knotty boards just above the window on the
farmhouse. Again, the slices from the color scans are sharper and
exhibit more detail than the black and white scans, with the color
positive scan showing the most detail when enlarged yet further than
what is shown here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.srosenberg.com/Website7/images/dagorbarnwoodQT.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Detail Scans Comparing All Four Master Files&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As can be seen in the detail images above, there was little difference
observed in the tonal range of the scans. There was, however, an
appreciable difference in the amount of detail captured, the master file
containing the most detail comes from the green channel when the film
was scanned as a color positive. This surprised me, as these are the
settings farthest from what was actually scanned - a black and white
negative. It was my initial belief that scanning the film as a black and
white negative would yield the best scans. So surprised was I by these
findings that I duplicated this experiment with an entirely different
black and white negative, this second experiment returning precisely the
same results.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
For my particular workflow, that is to say my scanner with me at the
wheel, the best scans of black and white negative film are obtained by
scanning the film as a color positive, inverting the file, and then
using only the green channel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;view-add-comments-http-largeformatphotography-info-lfforum-topic-504762-html&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://largeformatphotography.info/lfforum/topic/504762.html&#34;&gt;View/Add comments&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>http://lflf.surge.sh/technical/bellows-factor/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lflf.surge.sh/technical/bellows-factor/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Large Format Photography: Bellows extension exposure compensation&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;bellows-extension-exposure-compensation&#34;&gt;Bellows extension exposure compensation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Compiled by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.terragalleria.com/&#34;&gt;Q.-Tuan Luong&lt;/a&gt; for &lt;a href=&#34;.&#34;&gt;the
Large Format Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;formulas&#34;&gt;Formulas&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;mailto:bg174@FreeNet.Carleton.CA&#34;&gt;Michael Gudzinowicz:&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Multiply the marked f-stop by (1 + M), where M is the magnification on
the ground glass. Alternatively, mark &amp;amp; measure the position of the lens
at infinity focus, and then measure the ground glass to lens distance at
close focus. Divide the total extension at close focus by the former
number (near infinity, which should be close to the focal length for
most LF lenses), and the resultant f-stop factor will be the same (or
close enough).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;By &lt;a href=&#34;mailto:rkoser@worldnet.att.net&#34;&gt;Richard Koser&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the bellows is extended beyond infinity focus for close-up work, an
exposure FACTOR must be determined and applied. Two convenient ways of
finding the FACTOR are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;a) When the camera is focused at infinity, note a point on the camera
and another on the lens (e.g., diaphragm) such that the distance between
them is equal to the focal length (call it F). Then, when the bellows is
extended for close-up focus, the extension between those two points will
be greater than F (call it E). The exposure factor will be (E/F)
squared. For example, extending the bellows to twice-F to focus for an
object-to-image ratio of 1:1, the FACTOR will be 4.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;b) Measure the object width or height (call it O) and that of it&amp;rsquo;s image
on the ground-glass (call it o). The exposure factor will be (o/O+1)
squared. For example, focusing for an object-to-image ratio of 1:1, the
FACTOR will be (&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt; + 1) squared, or 4.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Applying the FACTOR:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If 4 times the exposure is required (per the examples above), open up
the lens 2 stops or increase the exposure time 4-fold.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two complications often arise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Firstly, it is hard, maybe even impossible, to measure bellows extension
when using swings, tilts, rise/fall and combinations thereof; thus the
object-to-image measurements are useful (indeed, Calumet offers a handy
plastic template, based on that principle, calibrated directly in
stops).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Secondly, FACTORs of 2, 4, 8, etc. obviously correspond to 1, 2, 3, etc.
stops; what about a FACTOR of 3?? To convert FACTORs to stops, use a
scientific calculator; (log FACTOR/log 2) or (ln FACTOR/ln 2) equals
stops. For a FACTOR of 3, (log 3/log 2) equals (.48/.3) equals 1.6
stops.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;By &lt;a href=&#34;mailto:roy@harrington.com&#34;&gt;Roy Harrington&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The formula (Extension/FocalLength) **2 is basically correct. The
focal length is basically the distance from the center of lens (where
the aperture is) to the film plane when the lens is focused at infinity.
So a 12inch lens will have 12 inches of bellows when focused at
infinity. You move the lens farther away from the film in order to focus
on something closer. The new distance of the lens from the film is the
&amp;ldquo;extension&amp;rdquo; (not the distance to what your focused on). For instance if
you move the lens to 24 inches from the film, objects another 24 inches
in front of the lens will be in focus. The image will be the same size
as the object i.e. 1:1 magnification and the bellows compensation will
be (&lt;sup&gt;24&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;12&lt;/sub&gt;)**2 = 4 or 2 stops more exposure needed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Personally, I like to do the calculation directly with the aperture and
thereby eliminate the square in the formula. For example the 12 inch
lens at 24 inch extension just doubles the effective aperture number so
f/16 is really f/32. Its very easy to use the aperture scale on the
front of the lens as a visual aid in this calculation. If you had an
8inch lens f/8 just becomes f/N when you have N inches of extension.
Many of the lenses have &lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; stop marks and if you can interpolate
between the full stop markings and use inchs, mm, cm etc you can fairly
easily figure out what compensation to make without a calculator or any
other fancy device.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some examples if my description is not clear. &lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; stop values approx:
f/8,9,10 f/11,12.5,14 f/16,18,20 f/22,25,28 f/32,36,40 f/45&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;Lens:        Extension:      Compens:
8in          12.5in           1 1/3 stops  -- f/8 to f/12.5
180mm        220mm            2/3 stops    -- f/18 to f/22
125mm        200mm            1 1/3 stops  -- f/12.5 to f/20
5in          7in              1 stop   (think f/10 to f/14)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The nice thing about this is the change can be made right on the lens
without even counting the &lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; stops.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;computing-tricks&#34;&gt;Computing tricks&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;using-the-relationships-between-f-stops&#34;&gt;Using the relationships between f/stops&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;By &lt;a href=&#34;mailto:nickdc@mail.erols.com&#34;&gt;Nicholas F. Hanks&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;re going to use the relationships between f/stops to determine the
additional exposure needed when extending the bellows. First, consider
the bellows at infinity as an f/stop type of number. That is, say your
120mm lens is &amp;ldquo;f/&amp;ldquo;120, but to bring things down to familiar f/&amp;rsquo;s, well
divide everything by 10, so call it &amp;ldquo;f/&amp;ldquo;12. We&amp;rsquo;re now dealing in
centimeters, but it doesn&amp;rsquo;t much matter. Let&amp;rsquo;s say you move your bellows
out to 160 mm. We&amp;rsquo;ll call that &amp;ldquo;f/&amp;ldquo;16. What this says is that we&amp;rsquo;ve gone
from &amp;ldquo;f/&amp;ldquo;12 to &amp;ldquo;f/&amp;ldquo;16 which is about one stop. So we&amp;rsquo;ve doubled our
exposure requirements. Either open up one stop or double your time.
Similarly, if we extend to 240mm it becomes &amp;ldquo;f/&amp;ldquo;24, which is two stops
more exposure or four times the time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This becomes a little confusing when working with odd numbers. A 90 mm
lens extended to 130mm is the difference between f/9 and f/13 which is
somewhere between familiar territory. Take a look down at the f/ scale
and make an estimate, and it&amp;rsquo;s probably good enough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s also hard to know where to measure to. It should be from the iris
to film plane, but sometimes the infinity setting doesn&amp;rsquo;t seem to
measure what I would expect it to based on the lens&amp;rsquo; focal length. It&amp;rsquo;s
best just to measure at infinity, then measure at the extension and make
the calculation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the method seems whimsical, it is based on sound engineering
principles. Remember that the f/stop is the ratio of the diameter of the
iris divided into the focal length. An f/8 with a 120mm lens would be
15mm in diameter. However, the amount of light is dependent on the area
(pi x r\^2). The area or a 15mm hole is 175.7 square mm. To double the
light you would double the area to 353.4 sq.mm. This gives us a 21.2mm
diameter hole which gives an f/ of 120mm/21.2mm which is f/5.6. If you
do the calculations for f/4 you&amp;rsquo;ll see that the hole is twice the
diameter (8 divided by 4) but four times the light area. Conversely,
f/16 is &lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; the hole diameter but &lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt; the light. Notice that there&amp;rsquo;s a
square relationship here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what?!!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As it turns, as you move the lens out from the film plane, the amount of
area on which light falls also increases in size and thus decreases in
density by a square relationship as well. Thus, as you move a 120mm lens
to 240mm, although twice the distance, the area on which light projects
is 4 times as much (2 squared) resulting in &lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt; the density.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, the f/ scale on the lens with which we are all familiar provides
us with a handy scale showing a square relationship which we can also
use as a key for our bellows extension.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;a-fast-method-to-calculate-bellows-extension-factor&#34;&gt;A Fast Method to Calculate Bellows Extension Factor&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;By &lt;a href=&#34;mailto:john12420@msn.com&#34;&gt;John A. Cook&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is an old saying that as photographers get older they don?t get
any better, but they do get faster. During my many years as a studio
product photographer, I never had the luxury of spending a lot of time
agonizing over technique. There was always a budget and a deadline
nipping at my heels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of necessity, I learned many shortcuts to get through the mountains of
products I was assigned to shoot. This is one of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This method for calculating bellows extension is predicated on the
relationship between the extension of the bellows (in inches) and common
f-stop numbers. It requires no fancy gadgets to purchase nor algebraic
formulae to memorize. You don?t even need batteries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Step One:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Make a permanent, durable list of the following F-numbers. (You can also
find them on your light meter.) Note that they are shown in &lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; stops.
Those with asterisks indicate &amp;ldquo;whole&amp;rdquo; stops:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;3.5
4 *
4.5
5
5.6 *
6.3
7.1
8 *
9
10
11 *
13
14
16 *
18
20
22 *
25
28
32 *
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Step Two:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Calculate the focal length of your lenses in inches, rather than
millimeters, by dividing by 25.4. Photography is not an exact science -
it?s okay to round off these numbers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;90mm = 3.5&amp;rdquo; 150mm = 6&amp;rdquo; 210mm = 8.26&amp;rdquo; 240mm = 9.4&amp;rdquo; 300mm = 11.8&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Step three:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you are ready to make the exposure, measure the view camera?s
extension from the ground glass to the lens board in inches. Measure
from the center of the lens board to the center of the ground glass so
as to not introduce errors from extreme swings and/or tilts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Compare this distance to the focal length (or flange distance) of the
lens and relate these two numbers to the above list of f-stops. Their
difference will indicate the number of stops you must increase the
exposure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example: a 210mm or 8&amp;rdquo; lens with 11&amp;rdquo; of bellows requires a one stop
exposure increase (the difference between f8 and f11).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A 240mm or 9.4&amp;rdquo; lens with 14&amp;rdquo; of bellows requires a one and one- third
stop increase (difference between f9 and f14).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A 90mm or 3.5&amp;rdquo; lens with 4.5&amp;rdquo; of bellows requires a two-thirds stop
exposure increase. And so on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This method is not accurate for telephoto lenses, whose optical center
is not near the lens board. To ensure always having a bellows measuring
device handy, I sewed a cloth tailor&amp;rsquo;s tape measure to the edge of my
focusing cloth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;devices&#34;&gt;Devices&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;a-tape&#34;&gt;A tape&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Making a &amp;ldquo;custom&amp;rdquo; tape measure means you can leave the calculator at
home. Stanley makes a very small (approx 1.5&amp;rdquo; x 1.5&amp;rdquo; x .3&amp;rdquo;) version of
their spring-retracting &amp;ldquo;carpenter&amp;rsquo;s&amp;rdquo; tape measure. Do the calculations,
(once) mark the back of the tape, and you can find exposure comp in a
few seconds. It is especially useful for telephoto lens designs that
don&amp;rsquo;t conform to the usual exposure comp formulas. I have one marked at
&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; stop increments using different colored marks for each lens. Works
great. &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;mailto:%0Aellinger@umich.edu&#34;&gt;Chris Ellinger&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;a-fixed-scale&#34;&gt;A fixed scale&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where I only have one lens, a 127mm (5 inch), I figured that a simple
scale on the bed next to the focusing rails calibrated in both stops and
time increase would do the job. Probably many people have already
thought of this where it is so simple but where this is all new to me,
ignorance is bliss. I used a paint program on the computer with the
measured values printed on heavy card stock which I cut to size. The
scale is held in place with the three screws that hold the bed together
so there is no modification of the camera and it is simple to change. If
I had two lenses a second scale could be put on the other side as well,
three lenses and I&amp;rsquo;m in trouble, but I probably couldn&amp;rsquo;t afford them
anyway. I&amp;rsquo;ve attached a JPEG picture to show the first revision I made
before I noticed where the screws would be so I&amp;rsquo;ve moved stuff slightly
so the screws don&amp;rsquo;t cover some of the printing on the scale. With
modification this could be used on any large format camera. &lt;strong&gt;Richard&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;bellows-scale.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;geoff-bowker-s-bellows-extension-charting-package&#34;&gt;Geoff Bowker&amp;rsquo;s bellows extension charting package&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is &lt;a href=&#34;Bell_Ext.xls&#34;&gt;a small excel spreadsheet&lt;/a&gt; that will calculate f
stop corrections for any lenses. just feed in the focal length and it
will produce a grid of f stop corrections and also a useful graph in &lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;
stop increments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;philipp-salzgeber-s-quickdisc&#34;&gt;Philipp Salzgeber&amp;rsquo;s QuickDisc&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.salzgeber.at/disc/index.html&#34;&gt;QuickDisc&lt;/a&gt; is a simple and
useful tool. The use of the QuickDisc involves no calculation, it is
lightweight, easy to replace and free for personal use. It consists of
two pieces of cardboard, the disc, and the measuring strip.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.greenspun.com/com/qtluong/photography/lf/bellows-factor.html&#34;&gt;View or add
comments&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>http://lflf.surge.sh/technical/camera-construction/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lflf.surge.sh/technical/camera-construction/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h2 id=&#34;reflexions-on-large-format-camera-construction&#34;&gt;Reflexions on Large Format Camera construction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;mailto:eahoo@earthlink.net&#34;&gt;Edward A. Hoover&lt;/a&gt; © 2002 for
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.largeformatphotography.info/&#34;&gt;largeformatphotography.info&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As my interest in photography and large format in particular has
evolved, I have become aware of several things about the hobby in
general that have led me down the path of simplified large format camera
design. My initial interest was aroused by the incredible detail that is
visible in the photographs taken by many of the pioneering photographers
from earlier eras. After a number of years of casual observation I
decided to see what design features these earlier cameras had in common
with there modern counterparts and began to collect available examples
of various types such as the folding view, tailboard, box and early
large roll cameras.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first thing that became apparent was the high price of collecting
usable samples and secondly the rather advanced stage of deterioration
that was common to the frames and bellows of these cameras. I then began
a quest for information on early fabrication and manufacturing
techniques. The information that I found consisted almost entirely of
repairing them and very little about design or building them so I began
to develop my own methods of construction based on readily available
materials and low tech tooling that most craftsman are likely to have
available to them or own personally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bellows being the most commonly dilapidated item I concentrated my
efforts in this direction first. All techniques for fabrication that I
could locate involved the rather imprecise method of adhering the ribs
or stiffeners directly to the pre-cut covering with little or no method
of precise control of intersecting dimensions or angles. After
dissecting various models, I developed the method of temporarily
adhering the stiffeners to a precise layout and then transferring them
to a precision matching form wrapped in the base or inside layer of the
covering. After application of the outside layer of the covering the
bellows is then slipped off of the form and the end rings are fixed in
place. With this simple method I was able to design and complete a
bellows with no error in very little time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I next focused my efforts on the camera back and immediately became
aware of the diversity of the existing designs and the differing
setbacks to the film plane of the various film and plate holders of
these early cameras. These designs seemed to consolidate to somewhat of
a standard in later years but when measuring them I observed noticeable
differences from the face of the film holder to the film plane that in
some cases would most likely be covered by the lens depth of field but
in others the difference such a divergence from the norm that I began to
wonder if it was intentional. After studying the setback of the ground
glass on various cameras I found it to be true that manufacturers of the
time did produce film holders and camera backs that were compatible only
with there own equipment and were not the least interchangeable as far
as focus but to the casual observer the mechanical fit was perfect. I
can&amp;rsquo;t help but wonder how many countless hours were spent by early
technicians in there darkrooms trying in vain to figure out where thy
went wrong!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The design feature that seemed to exist on all these backs was the
rather heavy spring pressures that resulted as the film or plate holder
was inserted after focusing was achieved and the difficulty encountered
when removing the film holder after the shot was taken. To say it is a
two handed operation is perhaps putting it to mildly in my opinion!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Keeping these observations in mind I decided to design a back that could
interchangeably accommodate various film or plate holders and
incorporate matching ground glass setbacks for whatever brand or type
the user would be inclined to experiment with. The solution I developed
to work around these problems was to create a focusing glass that is
removed before the film holder is inserted. If the side rails that
support the ground glass are fabricated to match the film or plate
holder focal plane setback and are machined to the same thickness as the
sides of the film holder that is utilized, an exact focal distance match
can be obtained and the film holder can be inserted and removed quite
easily without disturbing the position of the camera.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the frame of the camera I decided to utilize all friction stop
adjustment to remove the stumbling block, for the average experimenter,
of successfully fabricating a geared drive actuating mechanism while
still incorporating all movements required for focusing or offsets. The
method of fabrication I devised utilizes commonly available aluminum
channel and standard dimension hardwood that can be purchased from the
local home supply store and needs only to be cut to the proper length
before construction can begin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe that my design will allow the casual experimenter to enter the
world of large format photography at a time when its utilization is
becoming completely overshadowed by high priced products a rapid drift
toward digital media as the only low cost option with pleasing results.
The availability of low cost salvageable components such as lenses, film
holders and complete darkroom systems has never been higher and not
allowing these fine items to go waste when they can be easily obtained
and utilized in the extension of an extremely valuable and satisfying
art form is my reasoning for developing this low cost, simple, yet
precise method of camera chassis construction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;more-information&#34;&gt;More information&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More information and options for purchasing a complete construction
manual or a low cost chassis kit can be obtained by visiting my web site
at:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;http://home.earthlink.net/~eahoo/camera.html&#34;&gt;http://home.earthlink.net/~eahoo/camera.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Edward A. Hoover&lt;br /&gt;
5345 East Ohio Ave.&lt;br /&gt;
Sanford FL 32771&lt;br /&gt;
(407) 321.5128&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[](mailto:eahoo@earthlink.net)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;eahoo@earthlink.net&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>http://lflf.surge.sh/technical/darkroom-primer/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lflf.surge.sh/technical/darkroom-primer/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h2 id=&#34;b-w-darkroom-for-large-format-photography-a-primer&#34;&gt;B&amp;amp;W darkroom for large format photography: a primer&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;By &lt;a href=&#34;mailto:ndhanu@umich.edu&#34;&gt;N. Dhananjay&lt;/a&gt; for &lt;a href=&#34;.&#34;&gt;the Large Format
Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;**&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This document covers the basics to get started in
&lt;a href=&#34;#negative&#34;&gt;processing&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;#print&#34;&gt;printing&lt;/a&gt; B&amp;amp;W film. It is just a
primer and not meant to be comprehensive. For more details and
information, refer to the &lt;a href=&#34;#ref&#34;&gt;web and book references&lt;/a&gt; provided at
the end of the document.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[]{#negative}&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;film-processing&#34;&gt;Film Processing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;why-do-your-own-processing&#34;&gt;Why do your own processing?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1/ you learn a lot more about photographic controls since it forces you
to work a lot more closely. Knowing processing and printing, in a sense,
almost forces you to see through the camera and forces visualization&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2/ understanding what you can control in processing, and how, opens new
avenues and gives you greater creative freedom in how you take the
picture&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;half the point of using individual sheets of film is the individual
processing you can give each of them&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;4/ no more being at the mercy of automatic processing machines (you may
make mistakes but they are your mistakes and you learn from them)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;5/ cheaper in the long run&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;6/ reduces the number of variables (if a picture gets screwed up, you&amp;rsquo;r
e not wondering whether it was the processor or you, but you can get
down to figuring out where the problem is)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;processing-basics&#34;&gt;Processing Basics&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What exactly happens when you trip the shutter? A certain amount of
light strikes the film. Photographic film consists of silver compounds
(halides). The light strikes these particles and excites them and forms
a latent image. Processing is about developing the image and making it
permanent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Processing essentially consists of three steps - developing, stopping
development and fixing. You need some way by which you can unload the
film, expose it to the developing solution, which can develop the latent
image i.e., take the excited particles and get them to deposit metallic
silver. Once that is done to the requisite degree, you need to arrest
development or the developing solution can continue working on the
remaining halides. Once you have stopped development, you need to fix
the image, which is done by dissolving and washing away the undeveloped
silver halides from the emulsion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;what-equipment-do-you-need&#34;&gt;What equipment do you need?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1/ some containers to unload the film and run it through the chemistry&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2/ developer&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;3/ stop bath&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;4/ fixer&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;5/ wash aid&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;6/ wetting agent&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;7/ containers to hold the chemicals&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;8/ thermometer&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;9/ other stuff depending on which method you choose to use (trays, tanks
etc)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Processing containers: Your options (the ones I&amp;rsquo;m aware of) basically
are 1/ tray processing 2/ daylight safe tanks 3/ large tank 4/ tubes
(like the BTZS ones - see www.darkroom-innovations.com) 5/ other stuff
like the JOBO processors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tray processing is done by manually shuffling the film through trays
containing the chemicals. Not terribly expensive, all you need are
chemistry and trays. However everything needs to be done in the dark and
some people seem to hate this option (also painful if you&amp;rsquo;re sensitive
to chemicals). Daylight safe tanks (JOBO makes these and they come with
a contraption to facilitate the loading of the sheet film) are
convenient because once you&amp;rsquo;ve loaded your film into the daylight safe
tank in the dark, the rest of the work can be done in a lit room. Large
tanks involve loading the sheets into holders, which are dunked into the
chemistry. With tubes, you curl the emulsion and place it in a tube,
which is then rolled in the chemistry. I&amp;rsquo;ve only used 1 and 2 and will
explain below in more details the operating procedure for these methods.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each method appears to have its adherents and I guess it should be
possible to get a decent negative using any of these methods.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Developer: There are a variety of developers available. Typically, they
are available either as powders, which you will have to dissolve or as
concentrated liquids. Follow the manufacturer&amp;rsquo;s instructions. It is
probably wise to choose one developer and stick with it till you
understand it and are able to control it (as opposed to changing
developers in the search for the `perfect&amp;rsquo; developer, which only serves
to increase sources of variability).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The big question is whether you will use the developer one time or use
the replenishment system. In one time development, you develop a batch
of film and toss the developer down the drain. The advantage is
consistency but is quite wasteful of developer. The alternative is
replenishment wherein, for subsequent batches of film, you either add
small amounts of fresh developer or increase development time a little
to compensate for the slightly old, used developer. Replenished
developers are said to `ripen &amp;lsquo; with age as they collect silver salts
etc which are supposed to favorably alter the quality of subsequent
negatives, which has led to some people championing the cause of
replenishment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stop bath: This is typically acetic acid, which neutralizes the alkaline
solution required for development and thus halts development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fixer: Fixers dissolve the undeveloped silver salts, which can then be
removed by washing. If this step were not carried out, the unactivated
silver salts would become activated when exposed to light and cause
fogging of the image.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Washing aid: Once the film is developed and fixed, you need to remove
all the fixer/hypo from the film surface. This is achieved by washing
the negative. A washing aid can reduce washing time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wetting agent: At the end, you need to hang the wet negatives up to dry.
Sometimes, the water does not run off the negative but will form drops
on the surface of the negative and will dry, leaving marks on the
negative. A wetting agent changes the surface tension of the water,
allowing it to run off the surface of the film easily.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Agitation: If the film is placed in the developer and is left absolutely
still, one gets underdeveloped negatives. This is because as the
developer on the surface of the film acts on the film, it gets `tired&amp;rsquo;.
So you need to move the developer around to ensure that fresh developer
can reach the film surface. Agitation with a tank is achieved by
inverting the tank and turning it right side up. Agitation when
processing in trays is achieved by lifting up the film at the bottom of
a stack of sheets and moving it to the top of the stack and in this way,
shuffling through the entire stack repeatedly at a steady rate till the
development cycle is completed. Take care not to let the sharp edge of a
negative scratch the emulsion of another negative. It is important to
develop a good balance between agitation and rest since no agitation
causes underdevelopment and over agitation causes over development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Time and temperature: So how do you tell when development is complete if
you have to do everything in the dark? The film needs to be in the
developer at a particular temperature (usually 68F) for a certain amount
of time. You can vary these i.e., use a higher temperature for a shorter
time etc. The zone system can be used for expansion and contraction (if
the subject brightness range was too extreme or if your visualization
calls for a longer range) by increasing or reducing the developing time.
The manufacturer&amp;rsquo;s recommendations form excellent starting points. If
you consistently get underdeveloped or overdeveloped negatives, you can
then adjust development time accordingly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;using-trays&#34;&gt;Using Trays&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1/ Prepare the chemical solutions and place them in a logical order in
front of you (since you will be working completely in the dark). I
prepare four trays - water, developer, stop bath and fixer. The chemical
solutions should be at the correct temperature (this can be done by
placing the containers in a tray of water at the right temperature for a
little while before pouring them into the trays).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2/ Turn off the room lights. Unload your film holders. Make sure your
hands are absolutely dry. If you get the film sheets wet, they will
stick to each other and be impossible to pry apart without damage to at
least one of the emulsions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;3/ Arrange the sheets with all of them having the notches in the same
position. Now rotate one of these 180 degrees so that the notch is in
the opposite corner. This will serve as a marker in the dark.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;4/ Arrange the sheets in a fan shape (the way you would arrange the
cards you had been dealt in a card game) in your left hand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;5/ Take one of the sheets with your right hand and place it in the tray
containing the water. Now, even though your right hand is wet, since
your left hand is holding the sheets in a fan shape, your right hand can
pick them up one at a time to avoid getting two of them stuck together.
Transfer all the sheets to the water presoak.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;7/ Transfer the sheets one by one to the tray containing the developer.
Start agitation (by shuffling through them i.e., lifting the sheet at
the bottom to the top) and keep track of the marker sheet. Develop a
consistent rhythm. For about 6 sheets or so, the shuffling of one card
every 3-5 secs is said to produce a good agitation/rest interval. Take
care in setting the film down on the top of the stack and ensure the
sharp edge of the film does not scratch the emulsion of the film below.
At the end of the development cycle, finish shuffling till you move the
marker sheet to the top.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;8/ Transfer the sheets one at a time to the stop bath. Go through two
cycles of agitation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;9/ Transfer the sheets one at a time to the fixer. Agitate. You can turn
on the room lights about halfway through the fixing cycle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;10/ Transfer the sheets to a tray with water in it (I refill the initial
presoak tray). Run through one cycle of agitation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;11/ Refill the tray with water and agitate for 2 minutes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;12/ Transfer the sheets, one at a time to another tray with the washing
aid in it (I pour out the stop bath and rinse the tray and fill it with
washing aid). Agitate the film for 2 minutes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;13/ Transfer the sheets to a tray filled with a gentle stream of running
water. The emulsion is still extremely delicate and easily scratched.
Wash the negatives for about 5 minutes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;14/ In a tray, mix water with a wetting agent and place the sheets in it
for about a minute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;15/ Hang the sheets to dry in a dust free area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;16/ File the negatives carefully.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;using-a-daylight-safe-tank&#34;&gt;Using a daylight-safe tank&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1/ Mix your chemicals. Set the containers in a tray filled with water at
the required temperature and let the chemical solutions all reach the
required temperature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2/ Using either a completely dark room or in a changing bag, load sheets
of film into the tank.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;3/ Fill the tank with water. Tap it sharply to dislodge any air bubbles
on the surface of the film. Agitate for 30 secs. Let it soak for an
additional 30 secs. The purpose of the water presoak is to wet the film
completely so that it can `soak in&amp;rsquo; the developer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;4/ Pour out the water. Pour in the developer. Agitate continuously for
the first 30 secs and then for 5 secs out of every 30 secs for the rest
of the development cycle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;5/ Pour out the developer and pour in the stop bath. Agitate
continuously for 30 secs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;6/ Pour out the stop bath. Pour in the fixer. Agitate continuously for
the first 30 secs and then for 5 secs out of 30 secs for the rest of the
fixing cycle&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;7/ Pour out the fixer. Fill the tank with water and agitate continuously
for 30 secs. Pour out the water and repeat. You can take a look at the
film halfway through the fixing cycle but it is more convenient to just
finish the whole thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;8/ Fill the tank with a washing aid (which is used to clear the
fixer/hypo and reduce washing time).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;9/ Pour out the washing aid. The film now has to be washed. You can push
a thin hose into the tank and let water flow through the tank. I find it
more convenient to take the film out of the tank and take a look at it -
ah! The thrill of the unknown! I then place a tray under running water
(at the appropriate temperature) and place the film in this tray. Adjust
the flow of water to have at least a dozen changes of water in 5
minutes. Shuffle through the sheets very carefully a few times. The
emulsion is extremely sensitive and can be easily scratched - I don&amp;rsquo;t
care to remember how many perfectly good negatives I used to ruin when I
started doing my own processing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;10/ Add a few drops of wetting agent (which does something to the
surface tension of the water and lets it run off the film easily when it
is drying - else you can get marks from water droplets drying on the
film) to water. Let the film sit in this for a minute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;11/ Hang the film to dry in a dust free place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;12/ File them carefully after they are dry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[]{#print}&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;printing-the-negative&#34;&gt;Printing the negative&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In essence, printing is like photography in reverse. You take the
negative and project it out onto a sheet of paper (and so you get a
negative of the negative i.e., the positive) and develop the paper.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The prospect of setting up a darkroom can be intimidating at first and
look hideously expensive. You can get started on a budget, though.
Convert a bathroom into a darkroom (running water is available, many
bathrooms don&amp;rsquo;t have windows that need to be blacked out, the trays can
be set in sequence in the bathtub). Used equipment provides considerable
savings. Film processing equipment purchased new would probably cost in
the region of about \$100-150. Tray processing lowers the cost
considerably (to somewhere in the region of \$50-75). Printing equipment
is typically more expensive, especially enlargers and lenses but good
deals may be had on used equipment. Some used enlargers may be a little
ratty but you can easily fix these yourself. Mine had a light leak near
the negative carrier that fogged my papers (loss of crisp highlights). I
fixed it by first draping my darkcloth around it and then by placing a
rubber gasket around the area where the cold light head sat on the
negative carrier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;what-do-you-need&#34;&gt;What do you need?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1/ &lt;strong&gt;An enlarger&lt;/strong&gt; (I know this looks expensive at the beginning but
used enlargers can be had for quite reasonable amounts - typical brands
include Omega, Saunders, Durst, Beseler - I&amp;rsquo;m sure I&amp;rsquo;ve left some out).
The options are condenser or diffusion illumination (condensers are said
to provide added contrast at the expense of emphasizing dust and grain)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2/ &lt;strong&gt;An enlarging lens:&lt;/strong&gt; these are corrected for flat field and close
working - you&amp;rsquo;ll need a lens with a focal length approximately the
diagonal of the negative (else you&amp;rsquo;ll have light fall off at the edges),
typical lenses for 4X5 are 135mm or 150mm. Get the best one you can
afford. The optics are as important as your camera optics in getting a
good print&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;3/ &lt;strong&gt;A timer&lt;/strong&gt;: Not absolutely essential (I&amp;rsquo;ve managed to get by using
long exposures) but distinctly useful since many of them regulate the
voltage (preventing variations in intensity of light) and it also turns
the enlarger on and off.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;4/ &lt;strong&gt;A negative carrier&lt;/strong&gt; (two options - one, where the negative is
sandwiched between two glass plates which hold it absolutely flat but
provide four more surfaces for dust (and Newton rings), or glass-less
carriers which won&amp;rsquo;t stop negative sag i.e., hold the negative
absolutely flat resulting in attendant focus hassles&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;5/ &lt;strong&gt;Paper&lt;/strong&gt;: A huge variety is available (Kodak, Ilford, Oriental
Seagull, Forte and many others). The typical choices are fiber base or
resin coated. Fiber is the traditional stuff but takes a long time to
wash since the chemistry permeates the fiber. The first resin coated
papers were not as long lasting as fiber based papers but the new
generations of papers are quite an advancement and are said to last as
long as fiber based stuff (time will tell!). Paper is available in
various contrast grades to facilitate printing negatives with weak or
strong contrast. Grade 2 is considered normal contrast, with anything
below (0 and 1) being low contrast, and anything above (3 and 4) being
high contrast (see below for understanding contrast grades).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Multigrade papers are a convenient option. These consist of strong
contrast as well as weak contrast emulsions in the same paper, but these
are sensitive to different wavelengths. By choosing the appropriate
filter, it is possible to achieve various contrast grades with the same
paper (which spares you the trouble of stocking papers of various
contrast grades).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;6/ &lt;strong&gt;An easel&lt;/strong&gt; to hold the paper: four bordered easels let you set a
border on all four margins. Border-less easels let you print right to
the edge of the paper. Single size easels let you slip papers of a
particular size into them easily for fast operation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;7/ &lt;strong&gt;Chemistry&lt;/strong&gt; (paper developer, stop bath, fixer)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;8/ &lt;strong&gt;Bamboo tongs&lt;/strong&gt; to move the paper from one bath to another&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;9/ A darkroom&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;10/ A grain focusser&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;11/ A &lt;strong&gt;safelight&lt;/strong&gt; - printing papers are quite slow and orthochromatic,
i.e., insensitive to red light at a distance. Keep the safelight at
least four feet distant from the paper to reduce risks of fogging.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;basic-techniques&#34;&gt;Basic Techniques&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;the-basic-idea&#34;&gt;The Basic Idea&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Typically, images are cued to the tonalities of white and black and so
these form convenient starting points in determining exposure and
contrast grade. So, the first problem facing you is to find an exposure,
which will give you a `correct&amp;rsquo; white or black. Find an area that you
want reproduced as a white and find the exposure at which you just lose
the white i.e., it goes light grey and that is the right exposure.
Alternatively, find an area you want reproduced as a black and find the
exposure at which it just hits black, i.e., beyond this, it remains
black and you risk your barely textured darks also becoming black and
without texture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now print the whole image at this exposure and study the image. Let&amp;rsquo;s
consider an example where you key the print to the blacks. You may find
that in obtaining the correct black, you are losing the other end of the
scale i.e., the whites are not being reproduced as you visualize it.
There are two ways this can happen. You get a correct black but your
whites are either grey or the areas which should be light grey are still
white. This means the contrast on the negative is not matched to the
contrast of the paper for the expression of the picture you have in
mind. You will then need to switch to a higher or lower contrast paper
to put in all the values as you visualize them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alternatively, you decide on an exposure to obtain the lightest textured
area and you can control the darks through appropriate contrast grade
selection. In other words, if in obtaining the right amount of texture
in your highlights, your shadows (the parts which you want dark but with
some texture) go black and lose all definition, switch to a lower
contrast grade paper (or filter if you are using multigrade papers). If
the shadows are muddy and not deep enough, switch to a higher contrast
grade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that these are simplifications based on a general way of working.
Let the image dictate what you need. An image might well need to be
keyed to the midtones. The essence is to key the printing to some area,
find the exposure which gives you that area the way you want it and try
to control the rest of the image with paper contrast changes so that all
areas are reproduced the way you want them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;understanding-contrast-grades&#34;&gt;Understanding Contrast Grades&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To begin with, contrast is very much a function of medium. Even as
facile a mechanism as the human eye has its limits. Extremely bright
(blinding light in the eye) will be perceived without detail even if
there are actually variations of tone. Similarly, extremely dark
situations will be rendered uniformly dark, regardless of whether there
actually is variation in tone or not (as demonstrated by someone with
poor night vision in a dimly lit room). There are further interactions
resulting from the physiology and psychology of seeing which give rise
to effects such as higher contrast images appearing to be sharper and so
on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For our purposes, we are interested in the contrast grades of film and
paper and in trying to match the contrast of the negative to that of the
paper such that a straight print yields us an image of normal contrast.
Refer to the two accompanying figures as you read this. Fig 1 is the
characteristic curve (log exposure against density) for a hard contrast
paper. Fig 2 refers to a soft contrast paper. As can be seen, the slope
of figure 1 is considerably steeper than that of figure 2. So a unit
change in exposure will make a much bigger change in density for the
figure 1 paper than for the figure 2 paper. This means that the paper
corresponding to figure 2 will demonstrate a much more even range of
greys than the paper corresponding to figure 1.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;lfdoc_contrast1.gif&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;lfdoc_contrast2.gif&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s consider an example. Let us say that the dense areas of a negative
allows 1 photon of light to pass through every second while the thin
areas (the shadows) allow 10 photons of light to pass through every
second. Also let&amp;rsquo;s say that we have two mid-tone areas which allow 3 and
7 photons through respectively. Now, you start exposing the image on a
very hard contrast paper like that corresponding to Fig. 1. Let us say,
for e.g., that with this paper, it takes 50 photons of light to achieve
maximum black and about 30 photons to achieve the first hint of texture
i.e., above paper white. So in about 5 seconds, the shadow areas of the
negative would have allowed 50 photons to strike the paper and achieve
maximum black. However the highlight portions would have only allowed 5
photons of light through. The mid-tones would have allowed 15 and 35
photons to strike the paper. So in effect, the highlights and some of
the midtones are not really being separated in tonality from one another
(since both 5 and 15 units are below the level needed to get the first
hint of texture). So, in spite of the fact that you would like these two
values separated tonally, they will not be. Now, if the same negative
was used on a paper no. 2, which needs 300 photons of light for maximum
black and 30 photons for the first hit of texture. The shadow areas
would put 300 photons on the paper in about 30 seconds. In the same 30
seconds, the highlight areas would put 30 photons of light on the paper
and the midtones would put 90 and 210 photons of light on the paper.
This would translate into a full range of tones from white through a
range of greys to black from this negative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So a very contrasty negative would need the use a soft contrast paper
for this purpose and vice versa. In other words, if the negative has a
very smooth gradation of tones but your visualization calls for
something starker, you would print it on a higher contrast paper.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;exposure&#34;&gt;Exposure&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So how do you determine the correct exposure ? Test strips are a useful
way of doing this. Place a strip of paper on the easel. Raise the
enlarger head to the height you will be using it at (depending on final
print size). I find it convenient to work with exposures in the 20 to 40
sec range since that provides time for any manipulations that are
required. Give the paper 5 secs of exposure and then cover 20% of it
with a card and give it another 5 secs and so on. When you develop this
strip, you will have successive bands of increasing exposure. Pick the
one that best corresponds to your visualization. If the best strip
appears to be towards one end of the exposure sequence (5 secs or 30
secs), run another test strip. By ensuring that you have lighter and
darker renditions to each side, you confirm that the exposure you choose
really is the best one. Otherwise there is no way of knowing whether a
shorter (or longer) exposure may not have been better. Remember that
intensity of light falls off with distance. So the higher the enlarger
head is (for a larger print), the longer the exposure needed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;developing-the-print&#34;&gt;Developing the print&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This proceeds in exactly the same fashion as film, except that since
paper is orthochromatic, you can work under the safelights and watch the
image come up in the developing solution (this part is truly magical -
you&amp;rsquo;ll never lose your fascination for watching this happen).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Place the paper in the developer. Generally, it needs 1 to 2 minutes
(see manufacturer instructions). Do not pull the paper before its time
just because it looks too dark or light. Run another print if that is
the case. Once the time is over, use the tongs and drop the paper into
the stop bath (do not let the tongs touch the stop since it will then
contaminate the developer when you put it back there). Let the print sit
in the stop bath for about 15-30 secs depending on the paper (fiber
based papers need longer). Then transfer it with a separate pair of
tongs to the fixer. Time in the fixer depends on whether you are using a
rapid fixer or not. Once the print is fixed, it needs to be washed.
Print washing (especially of fiber based papers can take a long time -
print washers can help do this efficiently as can a washing aid).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;steps-to-a-fine-print&#34;&gt;Steps to a fine print&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;examining-the-negative&#34;&gt;Examining the Negative&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Look at the negative. A well exposed negative viewed by transmitted
light will always reveal more detail than a print viewed by reflected
light but you are looking for a creative expression of the picture in
your head. Study the negative as the source of information from which
you choose what you want to express. Begin by studying the low
densities, then the midtones and finally the high densities (the
highlights of the image).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;the-contact-print&#34;&gt;The Contact Print&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With large format (4X5 and larger), these are large enough to provide a
good deal of information useful for later printing. A contact printing
frame is useful for this although it is perfectly feasible to get by
with a plate of glass. Almost anything can be used for illumination (I
started making contact prints by using a desk lamp with a low wattage
bulb in it), but an enlarger is undeniably easier to work with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Raise the enlarger head till it throws a circle, which covers the area
well. Place a blank negative in the carrier (unexposed, developed film).
Make a test strip as explained above. Once you&amp;rsquo;ve developed and dried
this test print, study it to see how much exposure just gives you a
maximum black. This will be the time you will use for making your proof
sheet. The logic is that this exposure keys towards the black i.e., it
is the exposure that will &lt;em&gt;just&lt;/em&gt; give you maximum black from a blank
area (shadow) in your actual negative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now you have the information to make a contact print. Place the printing
paper, emulsion side up (the side that looks shiny under the safelight),
and place the negative to be contact printed, emulsion side down on the
paper. Place the glass down on this to hold the paper and negative well
in contact with one another. Turn on the enlarger and expose for the
required amount of time. Develop the print. Study the print for any
manipulations that seem necessary, contrast grade etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Making an enlargement&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Determining exposure: Decide on the size of the print that you want to
make. Raise the enlarger to the necessary height. Place the negative in
the negative carrier after dusting it and making sure it is clean
(remember any dust on the negative or lens means long hours spent
retouching the print). Place an old print face down on the easel to
focus on (this will ensure that the plane of focus is exactly where you
will eventually place the printing paper). Use a grain magnifier to
critically focus on the grain of the negative. Replace the old print you
used for focussing with unexposed paper. Make test strips as explained
earlier to determine the optimum exposure time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Work Print: Once you have determined the optimum exposure time, make
a straight print with no manipulations. Develop this print and study it
critically. See if the paper contrast grade is appropriate to your
visualization or whether you need to change it. If needed, make another
work print on the appropriate paper grade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dodging and burning: You now have a negative that is matched to the
appropriate paper grade to render your visualization. However, your work
print may still not match your visualization. You may have wanted some
parts of the image lighter or darker. This is where dodging and burning
come in. These allow you to control the tones of local areas. The basic
idea is very simple - you add exposure to those areas that you want
darker (burning in) and hide light from the areas you want lighter
(dodging). An assortment of cards/matboards works well. Your hands work
even better. For dodging areas in the middle of the print, you can make
dodging tools by fixing various shaped cardboard pieces to wire. For
burning in the middle, you can use you hands or use holes cut in card.
By bending cards, you can get curved shapes. By tilting a circular dodge
tool, you can get ovals. Keep the stuff moving all the time to prevent
hard edges and unreal effects. Another useful control is afforded by how
close to the lens (i.e., far away from the paper) you hold the tool.
Closer to the lens gives you a more diffuse penumbra, which yields a
more gradual effect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Print touching: If you have dust on the negative, you will end up with
whitish specks on the print. If your negative had a tiny pinhole, this
will give you a black dot on the print. Spotting can be used for dealing
with white spots from dust. The pinholes are more difficult to deal
with. I&amp;rsquo;ve heard that it is possible to carefully spot the negative,
which then gives you a white spot on the print, which can now be spotted
as usual. Or you could try using a sharp knife to gently reduce the
amount of silver deposit in this area, something I do not trust my
unsteady hands to do. The other option is to use a bleaching agent like
Farmer&amp;rsquo;s reducer (this contains ferricyanide, so handle with care). Dab
a bud or brush in this and apply it to the area you want to bleach. Keep
fixer handy since you will need to apply fixer to stop the action of the
bleach. This can also be used to bleach a print that has gone dark
overall by filling a tray with bleach and putting the print in it.
Farmer&amp;rsquo;s reducer can also be used to tone down an overly dense negative
as intensification can be used for thin negatives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you have the print you want, you can tone it. Toning affords
protection to the print and can change the color bias of the print.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;other-related-issues&#34;&gt;Other Related Issues&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1/ Checking for safelight fog: Place a few coins on a piece of paper and
turn on your safelights for about 3-5 minutes. Develop this paper and
see if the area surrounding the coins, are light grey compared to the
area below the coins (which should be absolutely unexposed and white).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2/ The dry down effect: Never check prints when they are wet. This is
because wet prints glisten with a slightly higher contrast but as they
dry, they lose that sparkling white intensity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;3/ Paper colors: Papers come in a variety of colors from pale cream to
cold tones. These colors can be further changed through toning -
something to keep in mind when deciding a paper for a particular
picture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[]{#ref}&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;more-information&#34;&gt;More information&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some useful web addresses (not comprehensive)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1/ &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.kodak.com/&#34;&gt;www.kodak.com&lt;/a&gt; for information on films,
papers, chemistry, processing times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2/ &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ilford.com/&#34;&gt;www.ilford.com&lt;/a&gt; for information on films,
papers, chemistry, processing times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;3/ &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.digitaltruth.com/&#34;&gt;www.digitaltruth.com&lt;/a&gt; for a huge data
sheet on processing times, crossing films and developers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;4/ &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.saundersphoto.com/&#34;&gt;www.saundersphoto.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;5/ &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.jobo-usa.com/&#34;&gt;www.jobo-usa.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;6/ &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.darkroom-innovations.com/&#34;&gt;www.darkroom-innovations.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;7/ &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.omega.satter.com/&#34;&gt;www.omega.satter.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Books&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1/ The Kodak Darkroom Dataguide (make sure you have this one)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2/ `The Negative&amp;rsquo; by Ansel Adams&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;3/ `The Print&amp;rsquo; by Ansel Adams&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;4/ &amp;ldquo;Basic Techniques of Photography&amp;rsquo; by John Schaefer from the Ansel
Adams Publishing Co.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;5/ `Black and White Printing&amp;rsquo; by George Schaub&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;6/ I&amp;rsquo;m not sure about the title and the authors but I think it is ` Th
e Darkroom Handbook&amp;rsquo; and at least one of the authors was Langford.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;7/ The Elements of Black and White Printing by Carson Graves&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;view-or-add-comments-http-www-greenspun-com-com-qtluong-photography-lf-darkroom-primer-html&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.greenspun.com/com/qtluong/photography/lf/darkroom-primer.html&#34;&gt;View or add comments&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>http://lflf.surge.sh/technical/digital-printing/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lflf.surge.sh/technical/digital-printing/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h2 id=&#34;an-overview-of-large-format-color-digital-printing&#34;&gt;An overview of large format color digital printing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;by &lt;a href=&#34;%20http://www.terragalleria.com&#34;&gt;Q.-Tuan Luong&lt;/a&gt; for the &lt;a href=&#34;%20.&#34;&gt;Large
Format Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Summary: an overview of the digital printers able of high-quality color
output in large format, including continuous-tone printers and inkjet
printers, as of July 2005.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While in B&amp;amp;W, there is still a place for the traditional darkroom
despite recent advances in digital printing, most of fine art printing
in color is nowadays done digitally. The tools in the B&amp;amp;W darkroom
always gave its practioners a tremendous amount of control. With the
exception of the dye-transfer process, it wasn&amp;rsquo;t until the advent of
digital workflows that color photographers gained access to equally
powerful controls. However, dye transfer is extremely time-consuming,
expensive, and difficult. Availability of materials is problematic,
since the few remaining experts rely on stockpiles of discontinued
supplies. The tactile and visual qualities of the medium have always
played a large role in B&amp;amp;W photography, and there is a considerable
range of possibilities. In color photography, the practical output
choices are limited between type-C prints and Ilfochrome/Cibachrome.
Digital printing not only includes those options, but adds quite a few
of its own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;continuous-tone-digital-printers-lightjet-chromira-lambda&#34;&gt;Continuous tone digital printers: Lightjet, Chromira, Lambda&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Continuous tone printers use photographic (silver-based) paper. The
image is created by exposing the paper pixel by pixel with RGB light
sources, either lasers or LEDs. Each pixel has a continuous 24 (8x3) bit
RGB value. Processing is done automatically in the printer with
traditional chemistry. The resulting prints look exactly like
traditionally made color photographs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By far, the most commonly used papers are type-C (for printing from
negatives) processed in RA-4 chemistry. Of all the type-C papers, the
preferred medium is Fuji Crystal Archive, that has the best longevity
rating of any color photographic paper. Crystal Archive has an estimated
longevity rating of 60 years, whereas the best previous photographic
paper, Cibachrome/Ilfochrome, had a longevity rating of 35 years. The
sharpness and color is excellent, with very deep blacks. Crystal Archive
comes in three varieties, Semi-Gloss, Glossy, and Super Glossy. The
glossy papers look more deep and &amp;ldquo;three-dimensional&amp;rdquo;, however they are
also more fragile. The surface is less tolerant to scratches and
fingerprints than the semi-glossy paper. Super Glossy is a
polyester-based surface like Ilfochrome/Cibachrome which has a metallic,
mirror-like finish. It is also possible to print on
Ilfochrome/Cibachrome, but this is rarely done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Printers include the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cymbolic.com/products/lightjet5000.html&#34;&gt;Cymbolic Sciences
Lightjet&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.digital-photo-lab.com/Lambda.html&#34;&gt;Durst
Lambda&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.zbe.com/products/chromira/chromira30.html&#34;&gt;ZBE
Chromira&lt;/a&gt;. Since
its introduction, in 1996, the Lightjet has emerged as the printer of
choice for fine-art printing. The Lambda is more often used for
commercial printing. I was told by a tech at a Custom Color Lab in Palo
Alto (incidently, the rise of digital forced that lab out of business in
2002) that the reason why the Lightjet is used for fine art printing is
that it is such a &amp;ldquo;bear&amp;rdquo; that it would be too inefficient for commercial
printing. We did a series of tests with one of my images that I had
printed on the Lightjet by another lab. With the settings that he used,
his Lambda prints were noticeably softer. Both of those printers use
lasers, and cost about \$200,000. The more recent Chromira uses LEDs,
and costs &amp;ldquo;only&amp;rdquo; around \$60,000. This made it possible for fine-art
labs such as West Coast Imaging or LaserLight to acquire one, whereas
before they would send out for Lightjets. The LEDs are low-power, unlike
lasers, which makes maintainance and calibration easier. The Chromira is
said to produce prints at least as good as the Lightjet. Because of
those high costs, those printers are exclusively operated by labs. There
are probably less than a thousand Lightjets installed worldwide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The maximum printing size of the most commonly installed Lightjet
printers is 48x96 inches (Reed Photo Imaging of Denver can print up to
48x120 inches). The less common Lightjet 500XL (in the US: Laumont,
ColorEdge, Duggal, Ferrari Color, in Germany: Grieger) is currently the
largest continuous tone printer. It prints up to 72x120 inches. Lambda&amp;rsquo;s
are limited to 50 inch wide. Earlier Chromiras were limited to 30 inch
wide. The newest generation can print up to 50 inch wide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because those printers have very high-quality interpolation algorithms,
and because of the nature of photographic paper, where there is a bit of
diffusion, excellent results can be obtained with 200DPI files, although
the native resolution is 300DPI.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is necessary that the lab provides you with the ICC profiles of their
printer on each type of medium they use, since this is the only way
you&amp;rsquo;d get a precisely matched color. A good lab also linearizes their
printer daily in order to provide consistent results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The costs of materials for those printers is the lowest of any, at
around \$0.30 per square foot. However, labs have to recoup the price of
the initial investment for the printer. Competitive good labs charge
around \$12 per square foot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;inkjet-printers-iris-epson-hp&#34;&gt;Inkjet printers: Iris, Epson, HP&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Inkjet printers lay very fine droplets of ink on paper. High-end Inkjet
printers are a world apart from cheap office printers, and can produce
prints of remarkable quality. However, the technology is still maturing.
Colors are formed by the juxtaposition of droplets of a number of
primary colors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A large variety of papers can be used. Some of those papers try to mimic
the apparency of traditional photographic papers, with RC surfaces,
semi-glossy and glossy finish, while others have a matte finish which is
unique to the inkjet process. Interesting heavy and thick fine-art matte
paper of refined appearance, as well as watercolor and canvas can be
used with the inkjets. With such papers, the print will look very
different from a traditional photograph. This look can be a bit &amp;ldquo;flat&amp;rdquo;
for an unframed print. Longevity rating is excellent, exceeding those of
photographic paper based on accelerated fading tests. It must be noted
that those tests failed to predict rapid fading of some ink/paper
combinations in the past.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;iris-printers&#34;&gt;Iris printers&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first inkjet printers to produce high-quality output were the Iris
printers. The Iris is a large drum based inkjet printer of high
mechanical complexity. It squirts a million droplets of ink from each of
its four nozzles (Cyan, Magenta, Yellow and Black) every second towards
a drum rotating at a speed of 150 inches per second. These droplets are
given an electric charge on their way to the drum either positive or
neutral to allow the printer to determine which should actually hit the
drum, and which should be deflected away to the waste system. Papers are
typically fine watercolor papers or canvas. The term Giclee (a French
word meaning &amp;ldquo;to spray&amp;rdquo;, although in slang the verb &amp;ldquo;gicler&amp;rdquo; has a
different meaning) was coined in the English-speaking world to refer to
Iris prints. It is nowadays often used to refer to any inkjet print on
fine art papers. There are two main limitations of Iris printers. The
first one is the cost, due to the high complexity of the printer,
limiting their use to labs. The second one is that the print has a size
limited by the size of the drum. Iris prints are often reproduction of
art pieces other than photography. For photographic art, the Iris
printers have largely been displaced by the Epson large format printers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;epson-ultrachrome&#34;&gt;Epson Ultrachrome&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Epson has dominated the market of fine-art printing since the
introduction of the Ultrachrome-based 7600/9600/10600 printers in 2002.
The 9600 costs \$5000 and prints to 44 inches wide. The 7600 costs
\$3000 and prints to 24 inches wide. Because the price difference is not
that large, and because the paper for the 9600 is more economical, I
would think that the 9600 would be a better choice, since you never know
how large you&amp;rsquo;d like to print. The 10600 is a more efficient version of
the 9600 meant for production environments. Subsequently Epson released
the 4000, which prints up to 17 inches wide and was designed to be used
with cut sheets (while the other printers primarily use paper in roll).
The small brother of the family, the 2200 (13 inch wide) does not have
the self-calibration feature (see below), and is more prone to clogging
and other problems than the larger, professionally-oriented printers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those printers were the first large format inkjet printers yielding a
combination of quality color, metamerism problems well controlled, and
longevity (at least as good as the Crystal Archive papers), thanks to
their &amp;ldquo;Ultrachrome&amp;rdquo; pigmented inks. Before that, you had the choice
between dye-based inks that yielded excellent color and dense blacks,
but were not archival (some of the prints began to fade just after a few
years), and pigment-based inks that were archival, but had a reduced
color gamut (range of colors that can be reproduced), in particular in
the reds colors, and serious metamerism. Metamerism refers to the fact
that colors would shift when viewed under different light conditions. So
you could produce a print that was perfect looking in your studio under
5000K lighting, but if the print was viewed under more common tungsten
or halogen lights, it would take an ugly magenta cast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The gamut (range of colors that can be reproduced accurately) is
slightly wider than the gamut of the Lightjet, in particular in the
blues and oranges. However, the blacks are not as deep as those obtained
on the Lightjet, which makes for prints that look more &amp;ldquo;flat&amp;rdquo;. The Epson
papers are not as nice to the touch as photographic papers. They are
also more easily damaged, for instance a water drop could damage a
print. However, once the print is framed, most of the advantages of the
Lightjet are reduced.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many people avoid printing on glossy paper (such as Epson Premium Glossy
Photo Paper) with the Epson Ultrachrome inks, because of a problem known
as &amp;ldquo;bronzing&amp;rdquo;, or &amp;ldquo;gloss differential&amp;rdquo;. Gloss differential is what
happens when light is directly reflected towards the viewer from off of
the print. The result is darkened, or &amp;ldquo;bronzed,&amp;rdquo; reflections where ink
has been laid, and full reflection (blown-out highlights) where little
to no ink has been laid. Because different colors can have different
&amp;ldquo;gloss&amp;rdquo;, under certain viewing conditions (generally at an angle), the
print will not look uniform, but rather will have a patchy appearance.
In general, bronzing is not a real issue once the print is framed.
Semi-glossy papers (such as Epson Premium Luster Photo Paper) can
exhibit this problem to a lesser degree. Matte papers do not suffer from
bronzing. Bronzing can be mitigated by applying a coating to the print
with such products as Lyson Print Guard, and Premier Art Print Shield,
that make the reflection more uniform.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another potential problem is &amp;ldquo;out-gassing&amp;rdquo; with glossy and semi-glossy
papers. In order to avoid nozzle clogging, some humectant chemicals that
are very slowly evaporating are added to the inks. When printing on
photographic-like papers (glossy and semi-glossy coated surfaces), those
chemicals are not absorbed by the paper. They&amp;rsquo;ll still be on the print
long after the water has gone and the print &amp;ldquo;feels&amp;rdquo; dry. As they
evaporate over time, they can cause fogging in the inside of the glass
when the print is framed. With uncoated paper, this is not a problem,
since the humectants can be absorbed by the paper. In order to prevent
outgassing, one must cure all the prints for a few days before framing.
The best way to do it is, after letting the print dry for about a hour,
is to lay absorbent paper (Chris Jordan uses news print paper that comes
in huge rolls of a thousand feet long for \$50, while Joseph Holmes uses
Light Impressions Renaissance non-buffered archival paper) totally flat
against the print with no air in-between for at least 24 hours,
preferably with pressure. Prints can be stacked and interleaved with
absorbent paper in order to achieve that. The paper acts like a sponge
and draws out the gases from the inks much faster than they would escape
if just exposed to air. The paper will go wavy as the solvent
evaporates. You keep interleaving until the paper is no longer wavy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Setting up the 7600/9600/10600 can be tricky. In order to get the widest
color gamut from the 7600/9600/10600, it is necessary to use the &amp;ldquo;no
color adjustment setting&amp;rdquo;, and profile the printer. Creating a good
profile can be very difficult, since the grey-scale raw output in that
setting is highly non-linear and suffers from complex color casts.
Fortunately, the 7600/9600/10600 incorporates an automatic closed-loop
calibration technology which is so good that any two printers provide
basically the exact same output. It is therefore possible to use a
profile created by someone else for their printer on your printer. Bill
Atkinson created excellent profiles for his own use, and makes them
available for free.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The native resolution of the Epson printers is 360DPI. When using a file
with not enough pixels, it is in general better to interpolate the file
in photoshop. Feeding the Epson with less than 240DPI results in
inferior prints on photographic paper. However, I have once produced a
large print on canvas at 175DPI and have been pleasantly surprised at
the results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;hewlett-packard&#34;&gt;Hewlett-Packard&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hewlett Packard large-format printers have a wide installed base in
engineering and design studios. Recently HP began to target the fine-art
market.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2004, HP released a new set of inks and matching paper, which is a
&amp;ldquo;swellable medium&amp;rdquo; that expends to receive the inks, and then contracts
to protect them. They are available in the affordable (\$1300) Designjet
130 printer, that can print up to 24 inch. This made it possible for
them to use dye-based inks while achieving a longevity rating comparable
to Epson pigmented inks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The appearance of the Designjet 130 prints compares very favorably with
the Epson prints. In particular, Charles Cramer (View Camera Magazine,
March/April 2005) observed that the blacks obtained by the 130 were the
blackest that he has ever seen in his career, better than the highly
regarded color Dye Transfers, or even Selenium-toned Ilford FB B&amp;amp;W
silver gelatin papers. He rates the density of the blacks in the
following order, starting from the best blacks: HP Designjet 130, FB B&amp;amp;W
silver gelatin, Dye transfer, Lightjet, Ilfochrome, Epson 9600. This
observation has been corroborated by several reviewers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;epson-ultrachrome-k3&#34;&gt;Epson Ultrachrome K3&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In May 2005, Epson a announced new line of printers with new inks,
called Ultrachrome K3. The line consists of the 2400 (replaces the
2200), 4800 (replaces the 4000), 7800 (replaces 7600), and 9800
(replaces 9600). The 2400 and 4800 shipped in the spring of 2005, while
the others are scheduled for fall 2005.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to Joseph Holmes &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.josephholmes.com/news.html&#34;&gt;beta-testing
report&lt;/a&gt;, this printer represents
a significant advance. The differential gloss problem (&amp;ldquo;bronzing&amp;rdquo;) is
much reduced, the output much more neutral and linear, and the blacks
considerably improved, in particular on glossy papers. They would fall
in between Dye transfer and Lightjet. The Ultrachrome K3 inks have a
slightly larger gammut, and an even better longevity rating than the
Ultrachrome inks. They are also said to produce outstanding black and
white prints.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Continuous tone printers produce prints that are traditional photographs
(silver-based). If you like the brilliance of a glossy print, they are
currently unsurpassed, especially with polyester-based surfaces. The
main drawback is the necessity to use a lab, at a cost of more than
\$12/square foot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Inkjet printers have dramatically improved. In many metrics, they have
surpassed continuous tone printers. They can create prints that have a
similar look as traditional photographs as well as prints that have a
unique look on matte, fine art, and canvas surfaces. However, the prints
still look more like ink on paper (because it is what they are) than
traditional photographs, where the color is embodied in the paper,
giving it a more three-dimensional and glowing appearance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The printing costs (ink and paper) vary between \$1 and \$2 per square
foot. See the tables for &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.inkjetart.com/pro/7600_9600/cost_page.html&#34;&gt;Epson Ultrachrome
printers&lt;/a&gt; (the
cost and printing costs for the next-generation Epson printers &lt;sup&gt;9800&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;7800&lt;/sub&gt;
are expected to be the same) and &lt;a href=&#34;http://h41186.www4.hp.com/Data/costperprint/&#34;&gt;HP
printers&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This, combined with the relatively affordable costs of the printers, is
the main advantage of inkjet printers. They allow the photographer to
own his printer. Having in-house printing capabilities, besides
improving efficiency, let you have instant and low cost feedback, and
fine-tune prints in a way that would not be practical when you have to
order prints from a lab. The cost of consumables is much less than the
cost of ordering a print from a lab, which in the long run makes the
printer pay for itself if you print enough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;view-add-comments-http-largeformatphotography-info-lfforum-topic-502683-html&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://largeformatphotography.info/lfforum/topic/502683.html&#34;&gt;View/Add comments&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>http://lflf.surge.sh/technical/dust-spotting/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lflf.surge.sh/technical/dust-spotting/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Large Format Photography:dust and spotting&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;dust-and-spotting&#34;&gt;dust and spotting&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Compiled by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.terragalleria.com/&#34;&gt;Q.-Tuan Luong&lt;/a&gt; for &lt;a href=&#34;.&#34;&gt;the
Large Format Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;By &lt;a href=&#34;mailto:bjs@oes.amdahl.com&#34;&gt;Barry Sherman&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;John Herberg  wrote:

&amp;gt;I don&#39;t have a darkroom, so I&#39;m forced to load and unload 4x5 holders in
&amp;gt;black bags.  I have two:  standard black cloth, dome-type.
&amp;gt;
&amp;gt;I vacuum the holders, blow them out.  I periodically vacuum the bags.
&amp;gt;After loading film, I blow off the negatives with canned  air.  Still, dust
&amp;gt;gets in.  I haven&#39;t tried vacuuming the film once it&#39;s in the holder, but
&amp;gt;I suspect that might stir up dust.
&amp;gt;
&amp;gt;Any tips that might help?

I&amp;quot;ve done all of the above.  I&#39;ve even built a mini-clean room
(small vinyl covered framework with air cleaner maintaining
a positive air pressure with clean air) for loading film.  Still
the clear spots on film from dust on it.

I gave up completely a few years ago.  For years now, if the film
doesn&#39;t come in a Readyload or a Quickload then I don&#39;t use it.
Period.  Once in a long, long time there&#39;ll be a dust mark on 
a Ready/Quickload film, but they&#39;re damn rare.


&amp;gt;And...print spotting.  Suggestions.  I presume that a matte or semi-matte
&amp;gt;surface is the best to work on 

Not really.  If you&#39;re using fiber base, the standard glossy will
be just fine.

&amp;gt; (RC, I gather, is pretty  difficult if not
&amp;gt; impossible.  Should the spotting solutions be *slightly*  wet, or wet?

The usual technique is to get the dye on the brush, wipe the brush
on scrap paper until it&#39;s quite dry and then apply the dye with a 
&amp;quot;stippling&amp;quot; motion.  Rather than paint it on you make a bunch of small
dots.  After a while, with practice, you&#39;ll probably find yourself both
using a wetter brush and at times using a painting motion, but the
dry brush and stippling are easiest at first.

I prefer to make up a series of dilutions.  Something like put down two 
drops of dye, move one drop an inch away (I just use a saucer and put
the drops in a ring around the edge), dilute it with a drop or two of
water, move a drop of *that* an inch away and dilute it, ...  That way
you have a range of dilutions to choose from and you can start with
a weak dilution and work your way up until you get the the strength
that you need for any given spot.

&amp;gt;Products for same?

Spotone is the standard product for spotting white specks from dust
on the negative at printing time.  Dust on the negative at exposure
time results in clear dust marks which print as black specks.  These
are much more difficult to deal with and the  most common technique is
to use a very sharp blade (Xacto at the least, preferably a scalpel)
to gently scrape away emulsion until the mark goes away.  Often you
get a few specks of emulsion torn away entirely and you then have to
spot them back with Spotone.

&amp;gt;What works best for you, if you do spotting of BW?  I haven&#39;t even
&amp;gt;contemplated spotting color, although, for some reason, color doesn&#39;t
&amp;gt;seem to show dust as badly.

Color spots just fine.  Ilfochrome makes dyes which look like a child&#39;s
watercolor set and which work just fine on all types of color paper.

Dust marks on direct positive materials are black rather than white
and are pretty well impossible to remove.  The only cure is prevention,
making sure that the transparency is absolutely perfectly clean at
printing time.  Good luck!  I&#39;ve spent literally hours cleaning
4x5 transparencies which had large expanses of sky.

Spotting super-glossy Polyester base papers such as Ilfochrome requires a 
little more effort.  Because dust marks show up as dark specks and are 
unfixable, spotting Ilfochrome is, for me, usually for the purpose of
removing defects such as people in landscape scenes, &amp;quot;hot spots&amp;quot; from
specular highlights, etc.  The problem is that with the super-glossy surface 
you can see a crust of dye after it&#39;d dried.  The secret is to do it while 
the print is moist.  I wash the print, lay it on a sheet of acrylic plastic, 
gently sponge it off with a clean photographic sponge to remove surface water 
and then spot away.  When I&#39;m through, the print gets a quick rinse in the 
wash water to remove any dye from the surface and then dry as usual.  There&#39;s 
a problem with spotting 
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My dust problem has diminished since I started using a vacuum cleaner on
my film holders and the insides of my cameras. Some of your dust could
be attracted to the film from the camera bellows, especially if the film
holder is highly charged with static. I bought a small Black &amp;amp; Decker
vacuum with attachments, and I don&amp;rsquo;t use it for anything but cameras and
darkroom stuff. It has been better than compressed air for me. Howard
Bond cuts cardboard to surround his film holders, then puts the
cardboard in plastic bags. That keeps the plastic away from the surfaces
of the film holders and minimizes the static, I suppose. &lt;strong&gt;Edward
Spence&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And now for another sucess story. I use the air compressor to clean the
holders before I take them inside to load film. I have been using those
anti-static bags that motherboards and other general electronics boards
come in to protect them from static. It really helps to keep the dusts
and stuff out. &lt;strong&gt;Lee Carmichael&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have an Electrolux tank-type vacuum cleaner. The day before I load
film, I vacuum the entire loading area. The day I load film, I take the
vacuum cleaner to another room and vacuum out all the holders and
slides. The reason for this procedure is so that the action of the
vacuum cleaner does not stir-up all the dust that probably exists in the
darkroom. Blowing the dust is a poor idea: it just gets it annoyed and
it moves to the part of your negatives where the uniform mid-tones are
so as to cause maximum annoyance. Sort of like teaching a pig to sing:
it only frustrates you and annoys the pig. I have had some success with
just brushing the dust off using the Zone VI high-voltage electrozapper
prush, but its present price is so high that I doubt most people will
wish to buy one. Once loaded, I just put the holders back in the boxen
(which are wearing out and I will need to find an alternate solution
when that time comes). I load with the film face up. I have not found it
necessary to do it face down. I would probably forget and put the sheets
in the holders upside down. &lt;strong&gt;Jean-David Beyer&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.greenspun.com/com/qtluong/photography/lf/dust-spotting.html&#34;&gt;View or add
comments&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>http://lflf.surge.sh/technical/e6-cheap/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lflf.surge.sh/technical/e6-cheap/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;E6 sheet film processing on a budget&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;e6-sheet-film-processing-on-a-budget&#34;&gt;E6 sheet film processing on a budget&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;By &lt;a href=&#34;mailto:oconnell@siam.org&#34;&gt;John O&amp;rsquo;Connell&lt;/a&gt; for &lt;a href=&#34;.&#34;&gt;the Large Format
Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;LF really set me back financially, even though I did it on a budget. Old
rail, decent lens, old (square-leg!) tripod, t-shirt for darkcloth, my
old folding dyer&amp;rsquo;s loupe to focus. After I had shot some film, I needed
to get it developed and printed&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I settled on contact printing 4x5 for black and white, because I
couldn&amp;rsquo;t afford an enlarger worth owning. It&amp;rsquo;s not really satisfying.
But it got me thinking &amp;ndash; why not try slides?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I went out and bought some out-of-date Velvia and shot it. Then I
found out it would cost me \$2-3+ dollars per sheet to get it developed!
Money was an issue for my photography: not the immediate \$30, but the
continual drain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I looked into developing E-6 myself. It didn&amp;rsquo;t look too tough. I could
keep a bath at about 100F(+/- 1 degree) with water from my tap. Kodak&amp;rsquo;s
1 gallon kit was \$50. I figured it would do at least 40 sheets. \$1.25
or better!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tanks were another story. JOBO starter tanks were \$120+. Trays didn&amp;rsquo;t
look like they&amp;rsquo;d work. I didn&amp;rsquo;t know about the old Unicolor print drums.
So, I succumbed to the \$30 Yankee Agitank&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I provide the following information for the amusement of those who don&amp;rsquo;t
have to do this and to convince those who think they must do this, to do
something else. It is not for the faint of heart. So:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do not trust an Agitank out of the box. It was designed to fit a whole
gamut of formats you can&amp;rsquo;t even find film for nowadays. The rack for the
sheets is collapsible, and only small notches in the central post keep
it up. HINT: the post falls and springs your film out when you agitate,
either from tapping the tank to remove bubbles or from sloshing the
liquid. Of course, this will only happen after you take your first
perfectly exposed flash portraits of some excited children, resulting in
long explanations to their parents and 35mm replacement shots which must
themselves be shot, developed, and printed&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take a stainless steel screw and fix the collapsible rack at the 4x5
position WITHOUT PIERCING THE CENTRAL BLACK POST! (If you do, it&amp;rsquo;s not
necessarily light-tight anymore. If you don&amp;rsquo;t use the set screw, it will
collapse on you and spring your shots out against the side of the tank,
to be found all pressed together in a multicolored stack after fixing.
Aaaagghhhh! And I wouldn&amp;rsquo;t use glue: E-6 first dev, color dev, or bleach
might take it out or react with it.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And now you must load your Agitank. It&amp;rsquo;s about as easy as loading film
holders. There&amp;rsquo;s a sliding doo-hickey you run along one edge of the rack
that you drop the sheets through into separate slots. You&amp;rsquo;ll look at it,
wonder if it scratches film, use it, and discover that yes, sometimes it
does. (Aaaagghhhh!) You can carefully load without it, provided you
practice and trust yourself not to double load any slots. Loading a full
12 and checking at the end to see if you&amp;rsquo;re in the last slot helps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(By the way, my Agitank has proven to be light-tight under ordinary
circumstances (i.e., not daylight), but if one absent-mindedly lifts the
lid to pour in the first developer, one ruins the film. Current losses
due to this: 10 sheets, E100S.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Agitank also requires 55 oz. of solution to process anything in 4x5.
Yep. And it only holds 12 sheets. So, you need to re-use the slightly
exhausted developer, and to do that in E-6 it means 6 available
containers and 6 funnels, because pouring out of the Agitank before you
can expose the film to the light is MESSY. So is pouring 55 oz. after
you can take the lid off. And you should be testing pH levels to assure
effectiveness the second time round (I don&amp;rsquo;t, even though I should know
better).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The INTERESTING bit about E-6 on a budget is that you can&amp;rsquo;t afford any
fun temperature regulation equipment. You need to keep all of your baths
at about 100F, some more precisely than others. I keep telling myself
I&amp;rsquo;ll go to an aquarium supply store and get some of their stuff, and I
keep saying that I&amp;rsquo;ll build an air box heater for bringing the chemicals
up to temp, but for now I use a little faucet flow to keep an 11x14
developing tray at 100F. It works. You need another 11x14 tray to hold
the chemicals you&amp;rsquo;ll need later, also, so I keep that one at temp by &amp;ndash;
get this &amp;ndash; using a coffeepot full of hot water to bring it up
occasionally. Transfer chemicals out of that bath to the good bath,
where the Agitank sits, BEFORE you need them, to assure proper
temperature control.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Use the instructions for small tank processing, and follow the
directions on top of the Agitank about agitation direction. Failure to
do so may cause problems. Wear rubber gloves when using E-6 chemicals,
by the way. Agitation causes a little to come up around the edges.
Warning: many people have different recommendations for E-6 development
with Kodak vs. Fuji films. I develop my Fuji Velvia for 6&amp;rsquo;30&amp;rdquo; in 35mm,
but 6&amp;rsquo; for the 4x5 sheet stuff works fine (EI 50 for the 4x5).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only good thing about the Agitank for E-6 is that you can expose the
film to light after the reversal bath, so you can fill and drain without
the lid fairly quickly (for the &lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; gallon quantities you&amp;rsquo;ll need).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After you finish, you can let the film dry in the Agitank&amp;rsquo;s racks. It
may have a blue look to it, as if you screwed up. You didn&amp;rsquo;t; it&amp;rsquo;ll dry
fine. Everybody repeat Philip Greenspun&amp;rsquo;s words after me: &amp;ldquo;You&amp;rsquo;ll feel
like a hero.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, your Agitank&amp;rsquo;s rack may look pretty warped by the &amp;ldquo;high&amp;rdquo;
temperature (or the bleach &amp;ndash; who knows?). Don&amp;rsquo;t worry. It&amp;rsquo;s still
usable, and as a plus, it makes that scratch-o-matic loading device
nigh-unusable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If your Agitank IS unusable afterward, consider it a blessing. You&amp;rsquo;ll
never be tempted to fill it with the outrageously expensive 4x5 Tech
Pan&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;view-or-add-comments-http-www-greenspun-com-com-qtluong-photography-lf-e6-cheap-html&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.greenspun.com/com/qtluong/photography/lf/e6-cheap.html&#34;&gt;View or add comments&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>http://lflf.surge.sh/technical/fstop/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lflf.surge.sh/technical/fstop/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Large format photography: how to select the f-stop&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-to-select-the-f-stop&#34;&gt;How to select the f-stop&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;part-3-of-setting-up-the-view-camera&#34;&gt;Part 3 of Setting up the view camera&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.terragalleria.com/&#34;&gt;Q.-Tuan Luong&lt;/a&gt; for the &lt;a href=&#34;.&#34;&gt;Large
Format Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Summary: a systematic method to find the f-stop which as a function of
the displacement of the standards between the far and near points,
measured on the camera with a scale (the focus spread). Two optical
effects are taken into account: &lt;a href=&#34;#defocus&#34;&gt;defocus&lt;/a&gt; and
&lt;a href=&#34;#diffraction&#34;&gt;diffraction&lt;/a&gt;. This page also contains for
&lt;a href=&#34;#ref&#34;&gt;reference&lt;/a&gt; the excellent original articles of Stephen Peterson
and Paul Hansma. In practice: First try to use the &lt;a href=&#34;#result2&#34;&gt;optimal
f-stop&lt;/a&gt; (yields the sharpest possible image at the depth of
field limits) and see what shutter speed you get. If it&amp;rsquo;s too slow, then
try to use the &lt;a href=&#34;#result1&#34;&gt;admissible f-stop&lt;/a&gt; (based on choice of a
circle of confusion).&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;operational-summary&#34;&gt;Operational summary&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using movements and focussing, you have already placed the plane of
focus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you managed to get everything in focus, then the f-stop you could
use would be the smallest one (ie largest aperture) for which you
have no vignetting. However, because you don&amp;rsquo;t want to worry about
misalignments and optical aberrations, you would probably choose a
couple of f-stops from wide open. Most LF lenses just aren&amp;rsquo;t
corrected well for wide apertures, since it was assumed they wouln&amp;rsquo;t
be used that way. Film flatness is more problematic with LF than
with other formats. The film tends to buckle and curve away from the
film plane, so a little extra depth of focus helps.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Otherwise, you need to extend your depth of field by stopping down
the lens. This article will show you how much. You will see it is a
lot.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, I looked at the technical data for the 49 photographs in
John Sexton&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;Listen to the trees&lt;/em&gt;, done with a 4x5. The breakdown was
as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;f16   f22   f32   f45   f64 
 5%   30%   50%   20%    5%
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Would the project have been &lt;em&gt;Smell the tidepools&lt;/em&gt;, the breakdown would
have been probably quite different, but this still gives you an idea of
what f-stops are commonly used.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you don&amp;rsquo;t want to read the explanations and wade in the math which
follows, here are the important points explaned in more details in this
article:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you stop down a lot diffraction will degrade resolution.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;However, if the subject is very &amp;ldquo;three-dimensional&amp;rdquo; you might have
to stopping down a lot to have enough depth of field. In this case,
do not worry about point 1, since the effect of not having enough
depth of field will be more detracting than the loss of resolution
due to diffraction, which is not that significant with large format.&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;There is a very simple and practical way to find which f-stop you
need to use, taking both point 1 and 2 into account. It is due to
Paul Hansma. Make your movements first. Then focus on far, focus on
near, read the distance &amp;ldquo;D&amp;rdquo; in millimiters between the two positions
on your rail, refocus so as to split the distance on the rail, and
use the following table that I recommend you carry with you all the
time. &amp;ldquo;F&amp;rdquo; is given in decimal f-stops, as on a hand-held meter, for
example 16.6 is 16 and 0.6 (aka between &lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; and &lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;) of a f-stop.
See &lt;a href=&#34;#result2&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; for details.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;D(mm) F        
 1   16.6      
 2   22.6      
 3   32.2      
 4   32.6      
 5   32.9       
 6   45.2       
 7   45.4       
 8   45.6       
 9   45.8       
10   64         
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now time to get technical&amp;hellip; []{#defocus}&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-defocus-circle-of-confusion&#34;&gt;The defocus circle of confusion&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let consider a bright point in space surrounded by a dark background, or
equivalently a point light source. It is converged by the lens into a
cone. The image of the point is the intersection of the film plane with
the cone. If the point in space lies in the plane of focus, the tip of
the cone coincides with the film plane, so that the image is a point. If
the point in space lies outside the plane of focus, the cone is not
intercepted by the film plane at the right place, therefore the image is
a circle, called the circle of confusion. The more the point is out of
focus, the larger is the circle. If tilts are used, the image is
actually an ellipse, however for reasonable amounts of tilts, the circle
is a good approximation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the circle of confusion is large, the image will look fuzzy. If the
circle of confusion is small, then it will be indistinguishable to the
eye from a point, and the image will look sharp. There is not a
universal boundary between fuzzy and sharp. The blurring of an out of
focus point occurs gradually. The calculations done in this document
should be taken just as general guidelines. When you use a depth of
field scale, you rely on the manufacturer&amp;rsquo;s choice of a value for the
acceptable circle of confusion. This value might not be the best for
your use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The brightness within the circle of confusion is constant. If we use the
criterion that two points are resolved when their circle of confusion do
not overlap (if the circles overlap, the two points are imaged in a
continuous bright spot) then the resolution R is related to the diameter
of the circle of confusion c by R = 1/c. This is the number of
non-overlapping circles of confusion that can be fit in a unit length.
If c is expressed in millimeters, then R represents the number of lines
pairs per millimiters (lp/mm). One precision is necessary here. We have
considered two bright points, separated by a dark space. This is the
same situation as two bright lines separated by a dark line. Each
element consists of a dark line and and bright line. The separation
between each element is c. A source of confusion is that some authors
consider a line pair (a dark line and a white line) to be two lines, so
they would use R = 2/c. This corresponds to the number of pixels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;what-is-an-acceptable-circle-of-confusion&#34;&gt;What is an acceptable circle of confusion ?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The diameter of the largest circle of confusion which is perceived by
the eye as a point is called the acceptable (or permissible) circle of
confusion. The acceptable circle of confusion c on the negative depends
on:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;resolvable distance by the eye c0 at mimimum viewing distance d0&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;viewing distance d&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;enlargement factor m (size of final print / size of negative)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The equation is c = c0/m * d/d0 .&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The smallest resolvable distance c0 is such that two dark lines
separated by more than this distance (by a white line) are seen as two
lines, while two dark lines separated by less than this distance would
be seen as one line. It is generally agreed that at normal minimal
viewing distance d0 (reading distance, around 25cm), the eye can resolve
elements spaced at 0.2mm. A good choice for the diameter of the
acceptable circle of confusion c on a print viewed at that distance is
therefore 0.2mm. The resolution is R0 = 1/c0 = 5 lp/mm Some people feel
that the eye can sense finer details.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The resolving power of the eye is approximatively inversely proportional
to the viewing distance d. A common practice is that a print should be
viewed from a distance approximately equal to the diagonal measurement
of the print. The rationale is that the eye would then be at the center
of projection if the image was taken with a normal lens (whose focal is
equal to the diagonal measurement of the negative), resulting in a
correct perspective. Personally I am not fond of this rule. After
viewing the image as a whole, I always like to come closer to see the
details. It is in order to preserve those details, even in extreme
enlargements, that you use a large format camera in the first place !&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The enlargement factor is the ratio of the linear dimension of a feature
on the print by its corresponding feature on the negative. If the print
and the negative don&amp;rsquo;t have the same aspect ratio, it is not the ratio
of the dimensions of the print and the negative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lets illustrate the formula c = c0/m * d/d0 by a few examples. We
assume c0 = 0.2 (average eye resolution), and d/d0 = 1 (print viewed at
the minimal distance). The formula becomes c = 0.2/m&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To make a full-format 6x8 (150mm x 200mm) from a 35mm negative (24mm x
36mm), you match the two smaller dimensions, so the magnification is m =
&lt;sup&gt;150&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;24&lt;/sub&gt; = 6.25, and the acceptable circle of confusion on the negative is
c= 0.2 * &lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;6&lt;/sub&gt;.25 = 0.032mm. This value appears to be used by most of the
35mm lens manufacturers on their depth of field scale. The diagonal of a
150mm x 200mm (6x8inch) print is 250mm (10inch), which corresponds to a
normal minimal viewing distance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To make a full-frame 8x10 (200mm x 250mm) from a 35mm negative (24mm x
36mm), you match the two larger dimensions, so the magnification is m =
&lt;sup&gt;250&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;36&lt;/sub&gt; = 7, and the acceptable circle of confusion on the negative is c
= 0.2 * &lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;7&lt;/sub&gt; = 0.028mm. This indicates the limitation of the depth of
field scales commonly used: even a 8x10 looked closely won&amp;rsquo;t appear
critically sharp. To make the same print from a 4x5 (100mm x 125mm)
negative, the magnification is &lt;sup&gt;250&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;125&lt;/sub&gt; = 2, and the acceptable circle of
confusion on the negative is 0.2 * &lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; = 0.1mm. This value is often
used for LF depth of field tables, but personally I don&amp;rsquo;t find it
adequate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In summary, the acceptable circle of confusion on the negative depends
on a number of factors, and it is better to determine the one which is
best for you, rather than rely on the manufacturer&amp;rsquo;s which is often not
critical enough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-relation-between-focus-spread-and-the-circle-of-confusion&#34;&gt;The relation between focus spread and the circle of confusion&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have followed the &lt;a href=&#34;how-to-focus.html#focus&#34;&gt;method II.3&lt;/a&gt;, you
have chosen a point of nearest focus and a point of furthest focus,
measured the distance D (called here the &lt;em&gt;focus spread&lt;/em&gt; between the two
focussing rail positions. If the distance D was zero, then everything is
exactly in focus because your subject is planar or at infinity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Calculations (&lt;a href=&#34;#ref&#34;&gt;see references&lt;/a&gt;) show that for small
magnifications, the relation between the focus spread D and the diameter
of the circle of confusion c is extremely simple, and gives you the
&lt;em&gt;admissible f-number&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;N = D/(2c)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;where N is the f-stop number, regardless of the focal length or format
used. Once you have determined what is an acceptable circle of confusion
for you, this formula gives you the f-stop, proportional to the focus
spread. As an example, here are the tabulated values that I would use,
based on c=0.1 for 5x7. This gives a critically sharp 11x14 at minimum
viewing distance, and has the advantage of being easy to remember. I&amp;rsquo;ve
also included in the table the equivalent for 4x5 based on c=0.066, and
8x10 based on c=0.133 Distances are in mm. []{#result1}&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;table-of-admissible-fstops&#34;&gt;Table of admissible fstops&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This shows you the fstop to which you should stop down at a minimum if
you want to achieve a circle of confusion c=0.066 on 4x5 (resp. c=0.1 on
5x7, and c=0.133 on 8x10).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;focus spread    admissible
4x5  5x7  8x10   fstop
  D (mm)           N
1.4   2.2   2.8    11
2.1   3.2   4.2    16
3.0   4.5   6.0    22
4.2   6.4   8.4    32
6.0   9.0  12.0    45
8.5  12.8  17.0    64
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The focus spread is sometimes refered to as &lt;em&gt;depth of focus&lt;/em&gt;, the
acceptable distance between imaging planes for a given circle of
confusion and f-stop D = 2cN.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the previous formula N is the effective f-number. For close-ups, you
would replace the f-stop by the effective f-stop, and use instead the
relation:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;N = f/v * D/(2c) = 1/(1+M) * D/(2c)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;where f is the focal and v your total belows extension. M is the
magnification. Since the ratio f/v is always smaller than 1, by using
the previous formula, you always end up stopping down more than
necessary. Note that at infinity, the ratio is exactly 1.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think this approach is most useful for judging whether within the
constraints dictated by the shutter speeds that you can use, you can get
your subjects sufficiently in focus. For instance, you are trying to get
a field of flowers in focus at the same time as a tree behind. You
measure a focus spread of 10mm between the closest flower and the tree.
In 5x7, you&amp;rsquo;d need to stop down at 45. Is the resulting shutter speed
acceptable, given the small breeze ? If yes, you just go ahead and take
the picture. If no, you might want to change the composition so that the
closest flower would be a bit further.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a general approach (ie independently from the constraints), the
drawback of this approach is that it relies on the choice of an
acceptable circle of confusion, which in turn depends on a number of
factors, including the dimensions and display of the final print. Since
you don&amp;rsquo;t necessarily know what you&amp;rsquo;d like to do with your negative in
the future, why don&amp;rsquo;t you just use a very tight acceptable circle of
confusion and stop down more ? The next two sections answer this from an
optical point of view. []{#diffraction}&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;diffraction&#34;&gt;Diffraction&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A beam of light passing through a circular aperture spreads out a
little, a phenomenon known as diffraction. Diffraction is a physical
phenomena which is unescapable. The smaller the aperture, the more the
spreading. For photographic lenses, diffraction depends only on the
f-number N.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Strictly speaking, diffraction is a function of aperture size or the
physical size of the hole and that is how it would be defined in a
physics textbook. Which means that the larger area aperture in a 300mm
lens at f/16 (as compared to a 50mm lens at f/16) should provide lower
diffraction. However, diffraction patterns are angular patterns and as
such are dependent on how far from the aperture you place the screen
used to view it also. In photography, the aperture is at the optical
center of the lens and the screen is (for infinity focus) one focal
length away. The physical size of the diffraction blur is then the focal
length divided by the apparent size of the aperture i.e., the definition
of the f stop. Thus, in photography, diffraction is only a function of f
stop and not a function of the focal length. In simpler terms, the
larger aperture of the 300mm lens does offer lesser diffraction at the
diaphragm (i.e., less bending around the diaphragm) but since the light
now has a longer distance to travel (as compared to the 50mm lens), the
smaller bending still results in a fair bit of blur at the viewing
screen. &lt;strong&gt;N Dhananjay&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The image of a point light source (such as a star) after diffraction
appears not as a point, but as a central circular spot surrounded by a
series of dark and bright rings. See &lt;a href=&#34;#ref-diff&#34;&gt;references&lt;/a&gt; for details
and formulas. Because a point source is imaged as a disk rather than a
point, it will appear blured, and this limits the maximum resolution of
the lens. The formula R = 1500/N explaned below, gives the maximum
resolution of the lens as a function of the f-number N.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The central spot size due to diffraction, called the Airy disk, has a
diameter of d = 2.44 x lambda x N. Note that this formula depends on the
f-stop and not on the physical aperture of the lens. For a wavelength
near the middle of the visible, lambda = 550 x 10 exp(-9) meters , d =
1.34 x 10 exp(-6) x N meters, or d = N / 750 if d is in mm. No lens can
make a spot smaller than that value. 86% of the power is in the Airy
disk, so it can be viewed as the image of the point. However unlike in
the case of defocus, the brightness within the central diffraction spot
is not constant, but it decreases from the center to its border, where
it reaches 0, resulting in a dark ring. If we use the Rayleigh&amp;rsquo;s
criterion that two points are resolved when the dark ring of one
coincides with the center of the Airy disk of the other, the
corresponding resolution is R = 2/d.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;fstop     resolution limit
  N     R (lp/mm)    d (mm)    
  11     136         .014
  16      93         .021
  22      68         .029
  32      46         .042
  45      33         .059
  64      23         .085
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These values correspond to the &amp;ldquo;diffraction limit&amp;rdquo; of resolution, the
maximum resolution which could be achieved on perfect film by a perfect
lens. Don&amp;rsquo;t expect a real lens to deliver 136 lp/mm at f11.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As it can be seen from these values, stopping down the lens beyond a
certain point degrades considerably the resolution. However, this is
more of a concern to small camera users than to large format users who
don&amp;rsquo;t need a large enlargement ratio. At f22, the diffraction spot
equals the acceptable circle of confusion for 35mm. At f64, it barely
equals the acceptable circle of confusion for 4x5. There is still plenty
of sharpness left, and these values indicate that you shouldn&amp;rsquo;t be too
worried about stopping down a lot if necessary. Some folks on the East
Coast thought that that Ansel Adams f64 Group was lame and started a
f180 Group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An aggravation to note is that the fstop N is the effective aperture.
Therefore, if you are working at 1:1, your f-number would be doubled
(two f-stops), and the resulting resolution would be divided by two. Add
to that the fact that you need to stop down a lot a close distances to
get enough depth of field, and you see why there are not many folks
doing macro work with LF&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;finding-the-optimal-f-stop-to-balance-defocus-and-diffraction&#34;&gt;Finding the optimal f-stop to balance defocus and diffraction&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Defocus, resulting in the circle of confusion of diameter c=D/(2N),
is more important for large apertures (small N)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Diffraction , resulting in the spot of diameter d=N/750, is more
important for small apertures (large N)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The more you stop down, the more you gain sharpness for the out of focus
points at the depth of field limit, but at one point, diffraction
effects outweight whatever gain is obtained. Intuitively, the optimal
point is when the two effects are equal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although the more rigorous way to combine both effects is the use the
MTF (&lt;a href=&#34;#ref&#34;&gt;see references&lt;/a&gt;), a good approximation is to use the root
mean square error of the two diameters. The total circle of confusion
is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;ct = sqrt( (D/(2N))^2 + (N/750)^2 )
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This quantity is mimimal when N = sqrt(375 D). For such a f-number, the
diameter of the defocus circle of confusion is exactly equal to the
diameter of the diffraction spot: D/(2N) = N/750.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This choice of f-stop is optimal, in the sense that it will yield the
sharpess possible image at the depth of field limits. However, the
larger your focus spread, the less sharp it will be. Sometimes you want
to know whether it results in enough resolution for the enlargements you
want to make. The resulting total circle of confusion has a diameter:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;ct = sqrt(2)/750 N =  N/530  = .0365 sqrt(D)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have predetermined a value for the acceptable circle of confusion
ct, this formula gives you the maximum focus spread and f-stop that you
can use:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;D = 750 ct^2     N = 530 ct
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let suppose that you are assuming average eye resolution and minimal
viewing distance, then ct = 2 * 0.2/m, where m is the enlargement
factor. This gives you the following values:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;m      D(mm)     N
2     30        106
3     13        70
4     7.5       53
5     4.8       42
6     3.3       35
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The defocus and the diffraction result in two different light patterns,
which in turn lead to two different definitions of resolution. Remember
that in the defocus case, brightness in the circle is uniform, and two
points are considered resolved when their circle of confusion do not
overlap, resulting in a resolution R = 1/c, while in the diffraction
case, brightness is more concentrated at the center. If one accepts the
technical definition that two points are resolved using the Rayleigh&amp;rsquo;s
criterion, this would result in the resolution R = 2/d. For this reason,
Bob Wheeler advocated combining the circle of confusion with the central
half of the diffraction spot, ie using N/1500 instead of N/750,
resulting in the optimum f-number: N = sqrt(750 D). In practice, this
would mean using the next f-stop in the table below (ie for D=1.3mm,
you&amp;rsquo;d use f32 instead of f22), which would imply stopping down even
more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, Paul Hansma suggests that from a photographic point of view,
the Rayleigh criterion is not really enough. The brightness between the
two &amp;ldquo;resolved&amp;rdquo; objects is very close to the peak brightness, so we would
not call them resolved if that is what we saw in a photo. To have a
level of resolution comparable to that obtained with the circle of
confusion, where there is no overlap, would call for having no overlap
of the two diffraction spots. This would explain why N/750 fits his
experimental results very well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[To summarize, if D is the focus spread expressed in millimeters, then
the &lt;em&gt;optimal f-stop&lt;/em&gt; which yields the sharpest possible image at the
depth of field limits is N = sqrt(375 D). This works regardless of focal
lengths, formats, and movements. The resulting resolution at the limits
of depth of field (ie for your far and near points) cannot be improved
in anyway and determine the maximum possible enlargment. Here are some
tabulated values by whole fstops:]{#result2}&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;table-of-optimal-fstops-1&#34;&gt;Table of optimal fstops (1)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;focus   optimal   resolution        resolution      maximum enlargment
spread   fstop    at DOF limits    for in-focus     based on DOF limits
D (mm)    N      ct(mm) R(lp/mm)   d (mm) R(lp/mm)         m
.3        11     .021   95         .014    136             19
.7        16     .030   65         .021     93             13
1.3       22     .042   47         .029     68              9
2.7       32     .061   32         .042     46              6.4
5.4       45     .085   23         .059     33              4.6
11.0      64     .122   16         .085     23              3.2
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are tabulated values by whole millimeters focus spread. I give the
f-stop is given in decimal values (&amp;ldquo;F&amp;rdquo;), followed by actual f-number
(&amp;ldquo;N&amp;rdquo;). Now what does &amp;ldquo;decimal value&amp;rdquo; mean ? It is what you would read on
a meter graduated in 1/10th of fstops, like many hand-held meters. For
instance, &amp;ldquo;decimal&amp;rdquo; 22.33 means 22 and one third of a stop (0.33),
&amp;ldquo;decimal&amp;rdquo; 22.5 means 22 and a half stop (0.5), whereas in f-numbers this
would be respectively 25.4 and 26.9 which certainly speaks less to me.
On my camera, I have stuck only the decimal values.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;table-of-optimal-fstops-2&#34;&gt;Table of optimal fstops (2)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This shows you the best value of the f-stop to use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;D(mm) F          N
 1   16.6       19.4
 2   22.6       27.4
 3   32.2       33.5
 4   32.6       38.7
 5   32.9       43.3
 6   45.2       47.4
 7   45.4       51.2
 8   45.6       54.8
 9   45.8       58.1
10   64         61.2
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fstop given on these tables is optimal in the sense that it is the
choice which yields the sharpest results at the DOF limits among all the
other possible f-stops. Remark that this table implies that you have to
stop down a lot ! This assumes that other considerations (wind,
reciprocity&amp;hellip;) do not prevent you from doing so, in which case you&amp;rsquo;d
have to compromise. By compromising, I mean you would use an f-stop
other than the optimal value. Then by applying the &lt;a href=&#34;#result1&#34;&gt;admissible
f-stop&lt;/a&gt; above, you would see if that non optimal f-stop gives
you a result which is acceptable, although you know now that it would
not be the best possible. In general, calculations show that results
pretty close to the optimal one are obtained within 1 fstop of the
optimal value.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The previous calculations were done at zero magnification. As before, or
close-ups, you would replace the f-stop by the effective f-stop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;satisfying-sharpness-requirements-for-the-horizon&#34;&gt;Satisfying sharpness requirements for the horizon&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you focus on the point which is &lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; from the near, &lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; from the far,
as suggested in the &lt;a href=&#34;how-to-focus.html#focus&#34;&gt;focussing method II.3&lt;/a&gt;,
and the focus spread between near and far was D then the actual focus
spread is &lt;sup&gt;4&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; * D. This is because you have &amp;ldquo;wasted&amp;rdquo; &lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; behind the far
point to ensure that the horizon is critically sharp.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When using the relation N = D/(2c), you need to multiply your f-stop
by 1.33, which is quite close to just adding one more f-stop.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When using the relation N = sqrt(375 D), you need to multiply your
f-stop by 1.15, which is quite close to adding one half-stop.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;what-about-real-system-resolution&#34;&gt;What about real system resolution ?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The optics that I outlined so far give you the aerial resolution
r_lens, assuming a perfect lens (resolution limited only by
diffraction), and ignoring the film. This is a valid approach in LF for
the two reasons discussed next.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because of various optical aberrations, lenses are not perfect. However,
stopping down enough corrects those aberrations pretty well in modern
lenses, well enough that they can be considered diffraction limited at
f22 and smaller apertures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The final resolution r_final that you get on film depends not only on
the aerial resolution of the lens r_lens but also on the resolution of
the film r_film. However, when r_lens becomes critical, the effect of
r_film becomes quite neglectible. In LF, since you have to stop down so
much, this is almost always the case.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Several sources use the formula 1/r_final = 1/r_lens + 1/r_film to
compute the final resolution. This formula is an approximation to the
exact calculation consisting of the convolution of the response of the
film and the response of the lens. This approximation is most valid when
both the film and lens are being used near their resolution limits
(spatial frequencies with very low contrast). This corresponds roughly
to f-stops up to f16. Thus the formula is pretty good for 35mm and MF
work. However, when the frequencies involved are nowhere near the film
limits, the formula is a poor approximation which predits a worse
1/r_final than what you actual get. For f-stops of f32 and higher, what
you get on film is in fact practically equal to the aerial resolution,
and the formula shouldn&amp;rsquo;t be used in that case.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;alternative-methods&#34;&gt;Alternative methods&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The method recommended in this document used measurements on the camera,
ie in image space. I don&amp;rsquo;t think using depth of field calculations in
object space is a good idea with the view camera. First, unlike on
helicoidal-mounted lenses used on rigid cameras, you don&amp;rsquo;t have a
focussing scale indicating at what distance your lens is focussed,
neither do you have a depth of fields scale. I guess you could use a
laser range finder and a bunch of depth of field tables. Even though,
and this is the second point, tables can be used only when the standards
are maintained parallel. Third, why use a method based on guessing, when
you can fairly easily use an exact method ?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some people think that instead of using all that math, you should just
rely on inspecting the ground glass. You would watch it through a lupe
as you stop down, and see when the out of focus areas become sharp
enough. For several years I have relied on this approach. I eventually
found, when I switched to a higher power lupe for evaluating the
transparency on the light box, that this yielded results less sharp than
I wanted. The problem is that it is not that easy to make a good
judgement of sharpness on the ground glass. The image is grainy, and
when you stop down, it gets pretty dim, especially through a lupe in the
corners of a wide-angle view.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;references&#34;&gt;References&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[The idea to relate the focus spread to depth of field was first
implemented by Sinar in their cameras. As their patent ran out, other
manufacturers, including Arca-Swiss came up with a similar device.
Masayoshi Hayashi wrote a]{#ref}&lt;a href=&#34;dofknob/&#34;&gt;document&lt;/a&gt; detailing how to
make one for your own camera. It discusses the magnification factors,
which were ignored by Sinar. In the 35mm world, Canon incorporated it in
their EOS bodies as the &amp;ldquo;Depth&amp;rdquo; mode. Here are some articles which
detail this idea:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Image sharpness and focussing the view camera&lt;/em&gt;: &lt;a href=&#34;articles/peterson-dof.1.gif&#34;&gt;page
1&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;articles/peterson-dof.2.gif&#34;&gt;page
2&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;articles/peterson-dof.3.gif&#34;&gt;page
3&lt;/a&gt; (gif files, reproduced with the
author&amp;rsquo;s permission) by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.summitek.com/&#34;&gt;Stephen
Peterson&lt;/a&gt;, in Phototechniques March/April

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Derives the relation, discusses the circle of confusion and
explains how to take diffraction into account in the calculations.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.micronet.fr/~deriencg/DOFforLF.pdf&#34;&gt;Depth of field and the view
camera&lt;/a&gt;, a draft by
Guy de Riencourt. Derives the relation and explain how to modify it
when sharpness at infinity is required.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.englander-workshops.com/documents/depth.pdf&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Apparent Depth of Field: Practical Use in Landscape
Photography&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;,
by Joe Englander. Discusses the circle of confusion and sharpness at
infinity.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[Material on diffraction includes]{#ref-diff}&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.mellesgriot.com/pdf/001.20-1.22.pdf&#34;&gt;the Melles Griot
catalog&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.photo.net/photo/optics/lensTutorial&#34;&gt;David
Jacobson&amp;rsquo;s lens
tutorial&lt;/a&gt;. In the latter
reference, defocus and diffraction are combined using the MTF. The
resulting &lt;a href=&#34;http://bobatkinsdev.furfly.net/photography/technical/dofdiff.html&#34;&gt;on-film resolution
values&lt;/a&gt;
were calculated by Bob Atkins. Using the formulas in this article, for
c=0.035, at f32, D= 2 * 0.035 * 32 = 2.24, ct = .0365 * sqrt(2.24) =
.054, which gives the resolution R = 2/.054 = 37 lp/mm, which is in the
ballpark of Bob Atkins calculation of 43.5 lp/mm. Note that his data at
f32 supports the observation that at high f-numbers, on-film resolution
is pretty close to aerial resolution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The idea of combining the effects of diffraction and defocus to find the
optimal f-stop was introduced in the article &lt;em&gt;View camera focussing in
practice&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;articles/hansma-dof.1.gif&#34;&gt;page 1&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;articles/hansma-dof.2.gif&#34;&gt;page
2&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;articles/hansma-dof.3.gif&#34;&gt;page 3&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&#34;articles/hansma-dof.4.gif&#34;&gt;page 4&lt;/a&gt; (gif files, reproduced with the
author&amp;rsquo;s permission) by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.physics.ucsb.edu/~prasant/&#34;&gt;Paul
Hansma&lt;/a&gt; in Phototechniques
March/April 96. Most of the ideas developed in this page are from this
article. Later, Bob Wheeler, in his &lt;a href=&#34;%0Ahttp://www.bobwheeler.com/photo/ViewCam.pdf&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Notes on view camera
geometry&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, section 9.3,
advocated combining the radius of the diffraction spot N/1500 with the
circle of confusion, rather than the diameter N/750. His own data
support this argument, which is theoretically sound. However Paul
Hansma&amp;rsquo;s experiments seem to have been conducted more carefully.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Struan Gray suggests this &lt;a href=&#34;http://groups.google.com/groups?hl=en&amp;amp;lr=&amp;amp;safe=off&amp;amp;th=783e23810f8662c2&amp;amp;start=0&amp;amp;ic=1&#34;&gt;r.p.e.l-f usenet
thread&lt;/a&gt;
for a discussion of system resolution (ie combining lens resolution and
film resolution).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.greenspun.com/com/qtluong/photography/lf/fstop.html&#34;&gt;View or add
comments&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>http://lflf.surge.sh/technical/how-to-focus/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lflf.surge.sh/technical/how-to-focus/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Large format photography: how to focus the view camera&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-to-focus-the-view-camera&#34;&gt;How to focus the view camera&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;part-2-of-setting-up-the-view-camera&#34;&gt;Part 2 of Setting up the view camera&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.terragalleria.com/&#34;&gt;Q.-Tuan Luong&lt;/a&gt; for the &lt;a href=&#34;.&#34;&gt;Large
Format Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Summary: two visual, iterative methods to focus the view camera on a
chosen plane of arbitrary location, assuming that you want to maximize
sharpness, as in landscape photography.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The procedure I is 100% visual. All assessments are done by looking
at the ground glass. It can be used with any view camera and does
not require any accessory. It involves a bit of guesswork (the
estimation of the best plane) and a few simple and fast iterations
(the actual adjusting of the tilt/swing). Variants of this procedure
are used by many photographers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The procedure II requires that you have a metric scale, ideally
attached to your camera rail or bed. Measurements on the scale are
used to make assessments. This procedure finds the best plane
instead of having you guess it, however each iteration is more
complex.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are probably as many visual techniques for focusing when employing
a Scheimpflug relationship as there are photographers doing so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In practice, what I personally use is procedure I (focus on far, tilt on
near) when photographing mostly flat/planar subjects. When the subject
is tall, most of the time I use procedure II, going directly to step 2
(spread focus between far and near). If this results in a very small
aperture (f45 or worse), I might try the full procedure II (minimize
focus spread with tilt) to get a larger aperture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I recommend using a metric scale. It is also necessary for the optimal
determination of the f-stop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;principles&#34;&gt;Principles&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Scheimpflug rule (named after an Austrian Army officer who patented
it in 1904), states that the film plane, the subject plane (plane of
sharp focus), and lens plane (the plane through the optical center and
perpendicular to the lens axis) must converge along a single line. See
&lt;a href=&#34;#ref&#34;&gt;references&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We all know that when a rigid camera is focused, all the objects which
are at a same perpendicular distance from the film plane can be brought
in focus at a time. For a rigid camera, the film plane and the lens
plane are parallel (or equivalently intersect at infinity). So the
subject plane must also be parallel to these two planes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a view camera, the geometric relationship between the film plane (the
back standard) and the lens plane (the front standard) can be adjusted.
This makes it possible to focus on virtually any plane, be it receding
or slanted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To use the Scheimpflug rule, here are a few points to keep in mind:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Scheimpflug rule can be used to help you figure out the camera
movement you need. For example, if your camera back is vertical, and
you want to focus on the ground plane, it tells you that you need to
tilt the lens forward. Moreover, by picturing the intersection of
those two planes, you get an approximate idea of the amount of tilt
needed. For example, the lower your camera, the more tilt you need.
The longer your focal length, the more tilt you need.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When you rack the standards back and forth, the subject plane
rotates along the &amp;ldquo;Hinge line&amp;rdquo;. The Hinge line is the intersection
of the plane through the center of the lens and parallel to the film
with the plane perpendicular to the lens axis and one focal length
in front of the lens. Harold Merklinger (see &lt;a href=&#34;#ref&#34;&gt;references&lt;/a&gt;)
elaborates a lot on this.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In camera advertisements they often show off the camera with a 45
degree tilt, however often, except for macro work, a small amount of
tilt (5 to 10 degrees) will be sufficient.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The depth of field area is a volume around the subject plane. When
tilts and/or swings are applied, this volume is not constant as it
depends also of the distance from the camera. The closer you are to
the camera, the smaller this volume is. You can picture it as a sort
of conical volume. When you focus on the ground plane, the top of
the flowers which are next to the camera might be out of focus,
while the top of the distant mountain will be in focus.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;which-controls-to-use&#34;&gt;Which controls to use ?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Which standard to tilt ?&lt;/strong&gt; Most cameras have tilts (and swings) on
both standards. &lt;em&gt;Esthetic considerations&lt;/em&gt; determine whether you use
front tilt, back tilt, or a combination of both. However, if you use
long lenses, you might find that front movements require
monkey-sized arms to operate.

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Front tilt preserve linear structure, in particular keeps the
verticals parallel.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Back tilt causes the foreground to &amp;ldquo;loom&amp;rdquo; and look larger,
making the near-far relationship more dramatic.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Front tilt requires more lens coverage than back tilt.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Base or axis tilt ?&lt;/strong&gt; Usually field cameras have base tilt and
monorails have axis tilt. If your camera has both, its probably
better to stick with one of the methods. It is a matter of personal
preference, and doesn&amp;rsquo;t affect the final image.

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;With base tilt, it seems clearer to me which areas are out of
focus. I also find axis tilt confusing if the far point is not
close to the axis of the tilt.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;With base tilt and shorter lenses, you might find that you
cannot get the two standards close together enough.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Axis tilt requires less refocussing and recomposing than base
tilt.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Which standard to rack ?&lt;/strong&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For close-ups, focussing with the rear standards will preserve
the magnification unlike focussing with the front, and is
therefore preferred if your camera has both.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For landscapes, this is equivalent, and I prefer to focus with
the front because the dark cloth doesn&amp;rsquo;t move.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A note about TS lenses&lt;/strong&gt;. Tilt and Shift lenses available in 35mm
for Canon and Nikon systems don&amp;rsquo;t let you use a tilt and a swing
like view cameras. Instead you pivot the lens to determine the axis
of the tilt. Place it on horizontal, and you get what is refered to
in LF terminology as a tilt. Place it on vertical, and you get what
is refered to in LF terminology as a swing. More generally, once you
have determined your plane of focus in space, the direction of the
tilt axis is given by the intersection of this plane with the image
plane. It&amp;rsquo;s pretty difficult to make fine focus judgement on a 35mm
viewfinder, so usually one or two iterations of the procedure I will
be enough. For specific information about using TS lenses, see &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.photosafaris.com/TiltLenses.asp&#34;&gt;this
article by John Shaw&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;procedure-i&#34;&gt;Procedure I&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Estimate the best plane of focus.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
This is the tricky part, and requires judgement. Once this is done, the
rest of the procedure is mechanical.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When your subject is essentially planar, such as a tide pool, a flat
landscape with a distant mountain, or the facade of a building, the
plane of focus is clearly the subject, and a fairly large aperture
can be used.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The difficulty comes when your subject is somewhat
three-dimensional, and several planes seem to make sense. For
example, imagine a scene in which you have a 1 meter high rock in
the foreground and a 1000 meter high mountain in the background. On
which part of the rock and which part of the mountain do you focus ?
In this case, there is an answer: when you establish a Scheimpflug
relationship, the subject plane (plane of focus) is one where depth
of field behind that plane remains double the distance of depth of
field in front. This is just as when the subject plane is parallel
to the film. If your camera is above the rock, you would have the
subject plane defined by two points (assuming that no swings are
used), the first point about two thirds of the way up the rock, the
second point two thirds the way up the mountain. However, if in
addition, you have a tree in between the two, then there is no easy
answer. You will have to stop down quite a bit, but less than if you
hadn&amp;rsquo;t used movements.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If no good plane can be found, because the subject is inherently
three-dimensional (for instance a landscape with a tall tree filling
the frame in the foreground), do not use tilts/swings. They result
in a smaller DOF area. The only way to get enough DOF is to stop
down, like with a small camera. You might have to stop down a lot.
Some compositions can just not be focussed sharp entirely with the
view camera. You will learn to recognize them and try to find
another composition. Go directly to the step 3 (adjusting the
focussing point).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Adjust the tilt and/or swing and focus&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If the plane is not slanted, most common situation in landscape
photography where you want foreground and background sharp, you need
only to use tilt.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If the plane is vertical, you need only to use swing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Otherwise, you need to tilt and swing. Do not adjust them
simultaneously, but proceed sequentially. If a swing is to be
applied after a tilt had already be applied, the left and right
points need to be chosen on the same horizontal line. Reciprocally,
if a tilt is to be applied after a swing had already be applied, the
top and bottom points need to be chosen on the same vertical line.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To adjust the tilt, use the following. To adjust the swing, replace
&amp;ldquo;top/bottom&amp;rdquo; by &amp;ldquo;left/right&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Choose a near point (top of ground glass) and a far point
(middle/bottom of ground glass)&lt;/strong&gt; both in the plane of focus and
with good contrast to focus on. In the rock/mountain example, this
would be a point on the rock approximatively two thirds of the
height of the rock and a point on the mountain approximatively two
thirds of the height of the mountain. I place tiny flashlights
(Maglite solitaire with reflector unscrewed) as focussing points on
the ground when it is too dark. If you are going to use axis tilt,
the far point should be close to the middle of the ground glass.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;[FF] &lt;strong&gt;Focus on the far point using the focussing knob.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;[TN] &lt;strong&gt;Make the near point sharp using the tilt.&lt;/strong&gt; You will
&lt;em&gt;augment&lt;/em&gt; the tilt. Image location is affected (unless the pivot
point of the tilt coincides with the rear nodal point of the lens):
as you tilt, you may need to use a little rise to regain your
composition).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;[EF] &lt;strong&gt;Evaluate&lt;/strong&gt; now whether the far point needs refocussing. If
so, you will have to refocus &lt;em&gt;further&lt;/em&gt;, go back to [FF]. Otherwise
you are done. Usually a couple of iterations will be sufficient.
This procedure continuously increases tilt. The more tilt you need
the more iterations you will have.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Variations of this technique:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Some people prefer to focus on the near with the knob and on the far
with the tilt. This might work better with axis tilts, while the
technique I described might be better with base tilts. Experiment
for yourself and see what seems more efficient to you.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Howard Bond&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;articles/bond-checklist.html#fc&#34;&gt;Focus-Check
procedure&lt;/a&gt;. Instead of [TN] and
[EF], you turn the focussing knob only in one direction and check
the effect on the near point [CN]. Then depending on the effect
(got sharper or blurrier), you add or remove tilt. He recommends
coming out of the dark cloth and looking at your camera.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Some cameras (Sinar, Ebony) have asymmetrical tilts, where the axis
of tilt is below the center of the GG. You focus on a far point &lt;em&gt;on
this axis&lt;/em&gt; [FF]. After [TN], the far point remains in perfect
focus, because it was along the axis of tilt, and thus did not
change its distance from the lens, so you are done in one iteration
!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;(Re-)adjust the focussing point&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Visually, you adjust this point so that the most blurry close point and
the most blurry far point would be equally blurry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If your estimate of the best plane of focus was good, you should
have ended at such a point while adjusting the tilt/swing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Since this is difficult to judge accurately, I recommend using step
2 of procedure II which follows, if:

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;you had maintained the standards parallel because the scene had
tall objects.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;you are unsure that your choice of plane of focus was optimal.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;procedure-ii&#34;&gt;Procedure II&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This method requires that you have a millimeter scale so that you can
measure the difference, in millimeters, between the near and the far
focus points. By the way, metric units makes calculations much easier.
Most monorail cameras come with such a scale, and on several flat-bed
cameras (including the Tachihara, Technika, and Canham KBC), it is easy
to attach one. You just have to make sure that it doesn&amp;rsquo;t slip during
focussing, and that you have a reference point on your focussing rail
from which to take measurements. Having a pointer (like on the Technika)
helps in making precise measurements. If it is not possible to attach a
scale, you can always take measurements with a ruler.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The procedure is described for tilt adjustment only. Same considerations
as before apply for swing. The idea is simple: by successive trial and
error, you will determine the tilt which is such that the focus spread
is minimized (step 1). Then you determine the optimal focus point (step
2).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The idea behind step 1 can be used without applying the full procedure.
For instance, you have a distant landscape with some tall trees in the
foreground. Since this is not planar, you&amp;rsquo;ll have to stop down. If you
shoot without movements, focussing somewhere behind the trees, the trees
and the horizon will be out of focus and require stopping down. If you
tilt the lens, focussing somewhere on &lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; the height of the trees, the
bottom and top of the trees will be out of focus and require stopping
down. Which of the two alternatives is the best ? The answer is given by
measuring the focus spread for each of them, and seeing which one is the
smallest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ajust the tilt&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Read the initial total focus spread.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Focus on the nearest point. Note the position A of focussing
rail which corresponds to the maximum extension for any point in
the image.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Focus on the furthest point. Note the position B of focussing
rail which corresponds to the minimum extension for any point in
the image.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Read the difference D between (A,B).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Make a guess about the amount of tilt needed, and apply it.&lt;/strong&gt; One
possibility, now that your camera is focussed on the far, is to tilt
until the near is sharp.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;[F]&lt;strong&gt;Read the new total focus spread.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Focus on the closest point (highest point above the plane of
focus). Note the position A of focussing rail which corresponds
to the maximum extension for any point in the image (you might
have to try several points and note the maximum value).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Focus on the furthest point (lowest point below the plane of
focus). Note the position B of focussing rail which corresponds
to the minimum extension for any point of in the image (you
might have to try several points and note the minimum value). In
the rock/mountain example, this is now the base of the mountain.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Read the new difference D between (A,B).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;[T] &lt;strong&gt;Adjust the tilt by a small amount.&lt;/strong&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If the difference D has decreased, add tilt, repeat [F]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If the difference D has increased, remove tilt, repeat [F]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If the difference D remains the same, you are done. Note that if
the subject is planar, D will be zero.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[]{#focus}&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Adjust the focussing point&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Focus on the closest point (highest above plane of focus), which you
want to make sharp. In the rock/mountain example previously used,
this would be the top of the rock. Note the position A of focussing
rail.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Focus on the furthest point (lowest below plane of focus) which you
want to make sharp. In the rock/mountain example previously used,
this would be the base of the mountain. Note the position B of
focussing rail.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Focussing at the median of (A,B) will make the closest point and the
furthest point equally sharp.&lt;br /&gt;
Note that this works regardless of camera movements (tilts/swings,
translations), focal lengths, and formats. To be exact, the general
result (referenced in Paul Hansma&amp;rsquo;s article, and detailed by Leonard
Evens, see references) is that you focus on the point C such as the
ratio of distances d(C,A)/d(C,B) is (1+MB)/(1+MA), where MA and MB
are the magnifications associated with the close and far object.
This point is always closer to A than to B. However, the only case
when the median rule is not a good approximation is when the two
magnifications are significantly different and at least one of them
is comparable to 1 which is only the case for close-ups with very
wide lenses, so in practice one needs not worry about this
technicality.

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Making he closest point and the furthest point equally sharp is
optimal &lt;em&gt;if the far point is not at the horizon&lt;/em&gt;. If you had
applied movements, this would always be the case.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;If you have maintained the standards parallel and the far point
is the horizon&lt;/em&gt;, you should instead focus closer to infinity
than to the near point (the two thirds of (A,B) is practical for
determining the f-stop to use). This is because perceptually, a
higher resolution is required for the horizon to appear
acceptably sharp than for the foreground. Note however that
Ansel Adams recommends, if sharpness has to be compromised that
the nearest point be sharper.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;alternatives-methods-and-references&#34;&gt;Alternatives methods and references&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The two methods that I have described are visual and iterative. There
are other approaches which try to nail down the correct tilt directly.
All of them require a way to measure tilt angles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One class of methods are based on measurements on the camera and
computations. They require a calculator such as the Rodenstock tool or
Bob Wheeler&amp;rsquo;s Vade Mecum which runs on palm devices. Both are detailed
in Bob Wheeler&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bobwheeler.com/photo/Surveys/Survey.pdf&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Photographer&amp;rsquo;s Aids: A
survey&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. In
particular, Bob Wheeler gives a in &lt;a href=&#34;%0Ahttp://www.bobwheeler.com/photo/ViewCam.pdf&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Notes on view camera
geometry&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; a practical
rule for use in the field. &lt;em&gt;Wheeler&amp;rsquo;s rule&lt;/em&gt; states that the angle of
tilt is 60*delta_focus/delta_GG, where:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;delta_focus is the focus spread, the distance on the focussing rail
from A to B&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;delta_GG is the perpendicular distance between the images of the
near point and the far point used to define the plane of focus,
imaged on GG before applying tilt to the camera.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is also a method developed by Harold Merklinger in his book
&amp;ldquo;Focusing the View Camera&amp;rdquo;, and well summarized on &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.trenholm.org/hmmerk/&#34;&gt;his web
site&lt;/a&gt;. This site in particular has a
few brilliant animations which are very helpful in visualizing the
Scheimpflug. Merklinger points out to a rule complementary to the
Scheimpflug, called the &amp;ldquo;hinge rule&amp;rdquo;. His method calls for the
measurement of the distance J from the lens to the required plane of
sharp focus, measured parallel to the film, and the use of a table to
get the tilt value. Personally I think this a great geometric analysis,
but that in practice it is not easy to apply because J is not that easy
to estimate. For a discussion on the practical feasibility of this
approach, see &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.greenspun.com/bboard/q-and-a-fetch-msg.tcl?msg_id=000du2&#34;&gt;this QA forum
thread&lt;/a&gt;
and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.greenspun.com/bboard/q-and-a-fetch-msg.tcl?msg_id=0008GT&#34;&gt;this
one&lt;/a&gt;.
If you want to try to use this approach, this &lt;a href=&#34;merklinger-spreadsheet.html&#34;&gt;Excel
file&lt;/a&gt; might help.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[For the historically inclined, Harold Merklinger&amp;rsquo;s page has the
51-page]{#ref}&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.trenholm.org/hmmerk/TSBP.pdf&#34;&gt;Theodor Scheimpflug&amp;rsquo;s 1904 British
Patent&lt;/a&gt;. For the geometrically
inclined, I sketched an elegant (I think) &lt;a href=&#34;scheimpflug.jpeg&#34;&gt;geometric proof of the
Scheimpflug&amp;rsquo;s principle using Desargues theorem&lt;/a&gt;. An
essentially identical derivation is given in Bob Wheeler&amp;rsquo;s excellent
&lt;a href=&#34;%0Ahttp://www.bobwheeler.com/photo/ViewCam.pdf&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Notes on view camera
geometry&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Generally
speaking, these notes are some of the best exposition of the math behind
view camera operation that I have seen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Subsequently, Emmanuel Bigler sent me a new derivation (&lt;a href=&#34;scheimpflug-bigler-english.pdf&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Scheimpflug&amp;rsquo;s
rule: a simple ray-tracing for high school
?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;) which requires only high-school
level (well, French high school from the 60s) geometry. He then goes on
to show geometrically, using an absolute minimum of algebra how to
derive the position of the slanted planes defining the DOF area (&lt;a href=&#34;scheimpflug-DOF-bigler-english.pdf&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Depth
of field and Scheimpflug&amp;rsquo;s rule: a minimalist geometrical
approach&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A number of great technical/mathematical notes can also be found on
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.math.northwestern.edu/~len/photos/&#34;&gt;this page by professional mathematician and photographer Leonard
Evens&lt;/a&gt;. Of particular
interest is the thorough &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.math.northwestern.edu/~len/photos/pages/vc.pdf&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;View Camera
Geometry&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.
Originally intended as a relatively short article for the American Math
Monthly, it soon got too large for that, approaching book length at 105
pages (in the spirit of Wheeler&amp;rsquo;s notes). It does address a whole lot of
issues that arise in the use of a view camera from an analytic,
mathematical point of view. That page has also the more focused, but
formula-free (and therefore more accessible to those familiar with
geometry) &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.math.northwestern.edu/~len/photos/pages/tilt_dof.pdf&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Depth of Field for the Tilted
Lens&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Howard Bond describes with plenty of details his well-proven method in
his article, &lt;a href=&#34;articles/bond-checklist.html&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Setting Up the View
Camera&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (reproduced on this site). The
idea of biasing the focus towards infinity in landscape photography is
discussed by Harold Merklinger&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.trenholm.org/hmmerk/DOFR.html&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The INs and OUTs of
FOCUS&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, and in the article by
Joe Englander, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.englander-workshops.com/documents/depth.pdf&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Apparent Depth of Field: Practical Use in Landscape
Photography&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.greenspun.com/com/qtluong/photography/lf/how-to-focus.html&#34;&gt;View or add
comments&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>http://lflf.surge.sh/technical/how-to-manage-film/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lflf.surge.sh/technical/how-to-manage-film/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Large format photography: how to manage your film&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-to-manage-your-film&#34;&gt;How to manage your film&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.terragalleria.com/&#34;&gt;Q.-Tuan Luong&lt;/a&gt; for the &lt;a href=&#34;.&#34;&gt;Large
Format Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Summary: this article explains how to load and unload film holders,
store sheets after exposure, and file them so that if you shoot backup
sheets so you can adjust development. It emphasizes methods that I use
for a long trip in the field when I expose a hundred or more sheets
before returning to the lab.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You won&amp;rsquo;t have to do anything described here if you shoot
quickloads/readyloads, which tells you how useful they are ! One
unloading/reloading cycle as described below with 20 holders takes me
about two hours that I&amp;rsquo;d rather use for sleep or rest. However this is
not always an option, if you are shooting larger formats than 4x5, or
the emulsion you prefer is not available in quickloads/readyloads. Also
Kerry told me that despite (or maybe because ?) shooting 35mm-like
quantities of Velvia, David Muench doesn&amp;rsquo;t use quickloads.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you shoot less film than the number of film holders you have, you
could leave all the film into the holders and give them directly to the
lab, marking with tape or post-it notes which ones you want processed.
However, some labs will charge you an extra fee if you don&amp;rsquo;t give them
the film in boxes. If you are just beginning, and don&amp;rsquo;t have yet an
empty film box, try to ask your lab for one. Despite the apparent
fragility, those boxes are light-tight when handled properly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;taking-notes&#34;&gt;Taking notes&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For each exposure, I write the following information in my notebook&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Number of the film holder being used (each face of my holders is
numbered, between 1 and 40). This is useful in the short term for
knowing which image is in which holder, and in the long term to identify
leaking holders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Number of the sheet of film used in the trip. Useful for overall
reference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the sheet of film is a backup (identical image), number of the
back-up sheet of film used in the trip, otherwise this field is blank.
This is useful once you get home for retrieving backup sheets so you can
adjust development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Description of the image&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Technical info (lense, fstop/speed, filters, special processing&amp;hellip;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It really helps if for each exposure, you make exactly one backup. Then
you know mechanically that each odd-numbered sheet is processed
directly, while each corresponding even-numbered sheet is a backup.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;finding-a-dark-place&#34;&gt;Finding a dark place&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;re staying in a motel, the bathroom usually works fine provided
it has no windows. Examine it before renting the room. You can block the
light beneath the door with a towel. The light from a small window can
be blocked by hanging a dark cloth with duct tape.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Otherwise, besides a few creative options that I tried in the past, such
as blocking all the light from the sky in your car with tarps, or
working in a sleeping bag, your best option is to use a changing tent. A
changing tent has a semi-rigid (collapsible structure) and is a
considerable improvement over a simple changing bag.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;changing-tents&#34;&gt;Changing tents&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Harrison tent seems to be the more popular. It sets up like a
free-standing dome tent, with two diagonal poles which go outside, and
provides a large flat working surface inside. Once collapsed, it takes
little room, which is why I favor it while traveling other than by car.
I have the smallest model, and although it is advertised for 4x5 use, I
find it works fine with 5x7. The Shadow Box has a very similar design.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the Photoflex/Calumet changing tent is also worth considering.
The new model sets up instantly, unlike the Harrison. Even though I have
the older model, I can still set it up in 15 seconds. For a smaller
footprint than the Harrison, it has a taller volume, which I find
convenient. The arms openings are more spread-out (sort of working with
a Microsoft natural keyboard as opposed to a normal keyboard) which I
find personally more comfortable. The drawbacks are that it collapses to
a flat but big package, and the metallic rings inside can get in the
way. There are also rumors that it is less light-tight than the
Harrison, and therefore wouldn&amp;rsquo;t allow you to work in direct sunlight,
which I avoid anyways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;unloading-film-for-processing&#34;&gt;Unloading film for processing&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I separate holders is three piles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Those for which one side is to be processed immediately, while the
other is a backup. the side to be processed is put on top.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Those for which the two sides are to be processed immediately&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Those for which the two sides are backups.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I first unload all the film that I want immediately processed (ie all
the sheets not marked as backups) into one separate &amp;ldquo;process&amp;rdquo; film box.
I put the pile 1 into on side of the changing tent with the &amp;ldquo;process&amp;rdquo;
box on the other side, close the tent, open the box, unload the top side
of every holder, close the box, and then unload pile 2. At the end of
the trip, I will just send directly the &amp;ldquo;process&amp;rdquo; box(es) to the lab.
All the backups will be unloaded into a different box, so I am sure that
I never process at the same time two sheets which have identical images,
but rather always have in a different place the two versions, should a
problem arise (for instance, last summer an otherwise good lab opened in
daylight a &amp;ldquo;process&amp;rdquo; box).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;unloading-and-filing-film-for-backups&#34;&gt;Unloading and filing film for backups&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Inside the &amp;ldquo;backup&amp;rdquo; box, I have four dividers, which are just the pieces
of cardboard in which the film was originally sandwiched. Kodak gives
you two separate pieces, whereas Fuji gives you on hinged piece, which I
prefer to use for dividing film. I have notched the four dividers with:
no notch, one notch, two notches, three notches, to indicate the tens.
As dividers, you could also use sheets of papers, or the mylar wrappers
in which your film came. The idea is that I am going to use the number
of the back-up sheet to be able to retrieve it later by counting the
order of the sheet in the &amp;ldquo;backup&amp;rdquo; box. However, it is pretty difficult
to count reliably more than 10 sheets at a time, so that&amp;rsquo;s why I have
the dividers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then I pile up the holders who contain either one or two backup sheets,
exactly in the order of numbered backup sheets, introduce them into the
changing tent with the &amp;ldquo;backup&amp;rdquo; box, and unload them into their
dividers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once I have finished using a box for the unloading section, I
immediately tape it to prevent accidental opening. Each of the boxes is
clearly marked, either &amp;ldquo;Film&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;Process&amp;rdquo;, or &amp;ldquo;Backup&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;a-variant-of-the-system-for-shorter-lighter-trips&#34;&gt;A variant of the system for shorter/lighter trips&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On backpacking outings, I take less film holders (therefore reload
often) and might shoot less film total. Often I will take only one empty
box and divide it in two. One part contains the film to be processed,
the other part contains the backups. I do the unloading sequentially by
film holder, while looking at the note book, introducing the holders in
the changing bag sorted by their numbers. This method allows for faster
unloading and saves carrying one film box.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;cleaning-holders&#34;&gt;Cleaning holders&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now all the holders are empty. It is time to get rid of the dust.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I use a paintbrush. I first clean the outside of the holders with the
black side of the dark slides closed. Then I remove one dark slide,
clean the top, reinsert only slightly the dark slide with the white side
up, clean up the dark slide, tap the holder in my hands while holding it
vertically, clean up the inside and the film rails, flip out the bottom,
clean it, slide down the dark slide to a point where one centimeter of
the film rail is still visible, and repeat the same operation with the
other side. If at home, I&amp;rsquo;ll also from time to time use canned air.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I then shake the dust out the changing tent, and I am ready to reload.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;reloading-holders&#34;&gt;Reloading holders&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For now see &lt;a href=&#34;loading.html&#34;&gt;this article&lt;/a&gt;. Just two additional
precisions: (a) you don&amp;rsquo;t have to worry about leaving finger marks on
the film, because unless your hands are very dirty or sweaty, they will
be washed out by the developer. (b) the main error in loading is not to
have the film under the two rails. I recommend you feel the extremities
of the rails with your fingers to make sure the film is under.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The way I tend to work with a changing tent is to pile up all the empty
holders on one side, the film box on the other side. As holders gets
reloaded, I pile them under the film box.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;storing-film-boxes-and-holders&#34;&gt;Storing film boxes and holders&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To protect film from heat, I store all the film boxes and holders not
currently in use in an ice-chest. I do not put ice in it due to the risk
of leakage and film damage, however, I cover it with a pillow or
sleeping bag to protect it from direct sunlight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;processing-the-backup-film&#34;&gt;Processing the backup film&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please keep in mind while reading the following that I use almost
exclusively transparency film.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is better to process exposed film promptly for optimal results. For
instance, after a few months, Velvia tends to have a (very subtle
magenta shift) and to loose a bit of speed. In the while, refrigerating
the film will keep the degradation minimal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You end up by knowing how much you alter the processing of the second
sheet by experience. What I suggest is that you ask the lab technician
for his advice to begin. After you&amp;rsquo;ve seen the results a couple dozens
of times, you&amp;rsquo;ll be able to guess with good accuracy. A few tips:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;stick with either &lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; or &lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; of stops.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To determine the amount of push, look at the highlight areas, and
compare them with the average tone to see how much push they can
take without washing out. Since you don&amp;rsquo;t want to puch beyond +1.5
stops (results in excessive contrast and murky shadows with all the
films I have tried, although in some cases +2 can give usable
results), all you have is to decide between a few values.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Be careful with pulling. Film is more sensitive to pulling than to
pushing. The contrast is seriously reduced, and for optimal results,
you will try to avoid pulling beyond -&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; or even -&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; stops (in
some cases -1 will give usable results). Think about that when you
are exposing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If not processing yourself, you must always use the same lab, and
they must run a carefully calibrated processing system. You must
also always use the same light box.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You need different clearly marked film boxes, one for each type of
processing (eg -&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;,-&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;,0,+&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;,+&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;,+1) What I do is introduce in the
changing tent all the back-up boxes and only one processing box at a
time, begining with the most populated box (hopefully the &amp;ldquo;0&amp;rdquo; box !).
The notebook is open and I look at it while retrieving all the relevant
sheets with my hands in the tent. When this is done, I upgrade the
numbers on the notebook, taking into account the sheets which are no
longer there, and reiterate with the next most populated box.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You never have enough of a good thing. If your image was great and the
exposure correct, process the backup. You&amp;rsquo;ll be happy to have it if your
first original gets lost or damaged. You can carry it around and show it
off, and not worry. You could file it with a stock agency. In case this
additional \$1.5 to process your 4x5 backup sounds expensive, remember
that a 4x5 duplicate costs \$30. If you didn&amp;rsquo;t like your image, don&amp;rsquo;t
process the backup.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.greenspun.com/com/qtluong/photography/lf/how-to-manage-film.html&#34;&gt;View or add
comments&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>http://lflf.surge.sh/technical/leaks/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lflf.surge.sh/technical/leaks/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Large format photography: Light leaks&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;light-leaks&#34;&gt;Light leaks&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Compiled by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.terragalleria.com/&#34;&gt;Q.-Tuan Luong&lt;/a&gt; for &lt;a href=&#34;.&#34;&gt;the
Large Format Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some photographers (like me) are plagued by these problems, which are
among the worse frustrations of LF. Some have never experienced them.
There are zillions of different sources of light leaks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;a-summary&#34;&gt;A summary&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Holder: Leaks at light trap for dark slide. Leaks because its
warped. Leaks from defective dark slide or dark slide doesn&amp;rsquo;t fit.
Leak at loading flap.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Camera back: Leaks because its warped. Because the light trap keeps
the holder from seating properly. Leaks because something else keeps
the holder from seating.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Camera body: Leaks from cracks or bad joints. Possible around screws
or rivets holding parts on. Leaks from ill fitting lens boards.
Leaks from holes in lens board.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bellows: Pin holes at corners or elswhere. Doesn&amp;rsquo;t fit at ends where
its fastened to camera body and front.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Leaks from shutters sticking open, perhaps only a pin hole opening.
Can also be caused by defective shutter leaves. Check both cocked
and after tripping. Some shutters have hard rubber leaves and can
have pin holes in them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reflective something inside camera. Light outside of the image area
being reflected onto the film.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Film is getting fogged somewhare other than in the camera.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Richard Knoppow&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;a-few-diagnosis-remarks&#34;&gt;A few diagnosis remarks&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the fogging extends past the borders from the rails in the holder it
has to be coming from elsewhere than from the camera. If many negatives
have identical an identical or nearly identical fog pattern it may come
from a leak in the film box. &lt;strong&gt;Richard Knoppow&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pinhole leaks would be more likely to look like superimposed images than
oblong blobs. &lt;strong&gt;Paul Butzi&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the &amp;ldquo;light leaks&amp;rdquo; do not have sharp edges but they do have edges, i.
e. there is not a bright area which gradually fades out, this must be
not too far from the film. If the leak were in the bellows or in the
front board then I would expect the bright areas to have foggy edges.
&lt;strong&gt;Eberhard Funke&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;leaking-film-holders&#34;&gt;Leaking film holders&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;common-problems&#34;&gt;Common problems&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check the condition of the hinges on the loading flap. If they are worn
that could be your leak. Is the slide seating all the way down into the
holder? Maybe you have a small hairline crack at the seam of the flap
possibly?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One place they leak is the place where you pull out the dark slide. Ever
take a holder apart? A friend and I did when we where building a vacumn
4x5 film holder for our astrogrpah (that&amp;rsquo;s another story). Inside the
&amp;ldquo;top&amp;rdquo; of the holder, behind the metal part, is a peice of light brass -
it looks like a curved comb. over top of this metal is a peice of black
felt. What happens over tiem is the felt wears down, &amp;ldquo;teeth&amp;rdquo; on the comb
loose thier spring and fail to hold up the felt in place, or break all
together. Normally when you pull back a darkslide, the curved part of
the &amp;ldquo;comb&amp;rdquo; springs back up into place, blocking off light. Older
holders, the felt may have holes in it, allowing small light leaks to
escape through. Also, the felt may be very dirty, so no matter how clean
the rest of the holder is, you continually get scratches and dust marks
on your flim, carried in off the felt onto the emulsion of your film
from the darkslide being pushed in. &lt;strong&gt;Joseph O&amp;rsquo;Neil&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can check these with a flash light by folding down the loading flap
so you can look straight into the holder and shining the light right
into the slot for the slide. &lt;strong&gt;Richard Knoppow&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;marking-holders-for-identification&#34;&gt;Marking holders for identification&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If large format users would use a notch-encoding scheme to number their
holders, it would be MUCH easier to exactly pinpoint a leaky holder. I
(and several other large format people I&amp;rsquo;m friends with) take miniature
files and notch the flap with the files. For me I use a v-notch for 1-4,
square-notch for 5, and a half-round- notch for 10. Thus, the holder
that I&amp;rsquo;ve designated to hold sheets 9 and 10 has a square-notch and 4
v-notches on the 9-side, and a half-round-notch on the 10 side. Should
either side of that holder ever leak, it&amp;rsquo;ll be really obvious as to
which holder (and side) is the culprit. NOTE: the notch goes into the
side that contacts the film, since light hits the ends of the holder at
an angle, there is no need to notch both sides of the flap. Be sure to
clean off the residue with an X-acto knife and clean the plastic dust
out of the holder when you&amp;rsquo;re done. &lt;strong&gt;Dean Barto&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;to-identify-leaking-holders-among-a-large-set&#34;&gt;To identify leaking holders among a large set&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The best that we came up with was to load them with the cheapest paper
that you can get (pre cut to 4x5 will save time) and take them out into
the sun and twist each one so that all surfaces face the sun (remember
paper is a lot slower than film therefore keep them in the sunlight
about 5 times longer than usual) Advnatage: you can load them under a
safelight. If you are really cheap and can spend the time, you can use
the same sheet of paper for more than one holder to narrow in on faulty
ones. [Algorithm to determine the minimum number of light sensitive
sheets to identify all leaky holders left as an exercise for the
reader] Don&amp;rsquo;t forget to number all holders (and matching sheets of
paper before you start). &lt;strong&gt;Sandor&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;leaking-camera&#34;&gt;Leaking camera&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;how-to-find-a-leak&#34;&gt;How to find a leak&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would take the camera into a darkened room and remove the lens board.
I would shine a light into the camera body to see if there is a light
leak in the bellows or the back. If no light can be seen, put the lens
board back on and take the back off and shine the light in from that end
and inspect for leaks in that direction. More than likely, you will find
the leak and patch it with black tape and be back on the road in no
time. &lt;strong&gt;Lee Carmichael&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just to suggest another, more definitive, way of finding those pesky
pinhole leaks: if you are in a university and have access to a
photomultiplier tube (try a physics lab), I would give that a try using
an ordinary flash inside the bellows. This way you can look at a meter
rather than trust your eyes to find even the smallest pinhole light
leak.&lt;strong&gt;JohnK&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;flare-problem-due-to-excessive-coverage&#34;&gt;Flare problem due to excessive coverage&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another cause of this sort of problem is flare due to the sun or another
bright light source out of the composed frame, bouncing light off the
bellows and dumping the non-image light on part of the film. Since the
lens reverses the image position on film, the upper right of your photo
would be lower left on the ground glass - the sun, outside the frame to
the upper right could be reflected by the bellows to the lower left area
of the GG/film causing fogging. The solution is to use a lens hood,
compendium bellows, or a card to prevent sources outside the composed
frame from illuminating the lens and reflecting off the interior of the
bellows. &lt;strong&gt;Michael Gudzinowicz&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, as a reward for those who slogged thru all of that, I have one
last note - this I discovered today. A friend had an image spoiled by
what looked like a light leak - the fogging appeared as a splash of
light from the top of the frame. We examined the negative, and it seemed
that, perhaps, it was caused by the image of the sun, which was just
barely out of the frame. It looked rather as if the image of the sun
fell on the beveled edge of the readyload film holder - around the
frame, the bevel slopes *in* toward the film. And it looked to me like
the image of the sun fell on this bevel, and reflected off and was
splashed across the film. Ick. I think the moral of the story is that if
the sun is just outside the frame, use a lens hood and adjust it very
carefully. &lt;strong&gt;Paul Butzi&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;holder-not-sitting-light-tight-against-camera&#34;&gt;Holder not sitting light-tight against camera&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I suggest this: once you insert the holder, try wrapping the darkcloth
around it and the back, leaving just enough to pull the slide. Or maybe
wrap the entire back and holder, clip it shut with clothespins, and pull
the slide inside there. It sounds like the holder is not seating
light-tight against the camera. I think it&amp;rsquo;s occasional possibly due to
moisture changes in the atmosphere causing the wood to warp slightly.
&lt;strong&gt;David Meiland&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Would it be possible to put some black felt where the cutfilm holder
rests against the back? &lt;strong&gt;Robert Peters&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had a problem with light leaks when I first started in 4 x 5. Do not
take the dark slide out until you are ready to shoot. Replace it
immediately after you shoot. I ran into my light leak problem by putting
just the corner of the dark slide in first. You have to put the slide in
perfectly straight, or you get a light leak. &lt;strong&gt;Rob&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have old wooden film holders that have been a great deal of trouble
with light leaks for the two years or so that I&amp;rsquo;ve been trying to use
them. I just came back from a trip and this time I kept the dark cloth
on the camera during exposures and guess what? No light leaks on any of
the film, a first! I thought that the leaks had ocurred in handling the
film holders or even carrying them around, but this seems to indicate
that the leaks ocurr only when opening and closing the dark slides.
&lt;strong&gt;Frank Kolwicz&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other possibilities that come to mind are: not getting the holder seated
before pulling the dark slide, shifting the holder when pulling the dark
slide. Basically anything that might pull the holder away from the
camera back. If you routinely shoot straight up, are those more likely
to be fogged? The weight of the holder might be pulling it away from the
back due to weakened springs. &lt;strong&gt;Paul Butzi&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;leaking-preloaded-film-systems&#34;&gt;Leaking preloaded film systems&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many people have reported problems with light leaks using preloaded
systems, especially the kodak readyloads and/or polaroid back. Look at
the &lt;a href=&#34;holders.html#readyloads&#34;&gt;diagnosis and tips to avoid problems&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;leaks-outside-of-the-camera&#34;&gt;Leaks outside of the camera&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How and where do you load your holders? Do you wear, perhaps, a
wristwatch with a luminescent face? (Yes, I *have* fogged film that
way). &lt;strong&gt;Paul Butzi&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the fogging happens on the unexposed-but-processed film, try a
different lab. If it still shows up, I&amp;rsquo;d say you&amp;rsquo;re handling it wrong
and you&amp;rsquo;ll have to look at your environment (Don Nelson&amp;rsquo;s point about
fluorescents being able to fog film after being turned off is correct,
in my experience). &lt;strong&gt;Pete Bergstrom&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two thoughts: 1) is the box you transport your exposed negative to the
film lab in light tight? 2) Are you sure these &amp;ldquo;blobs&amp;rdquo; are not
processing failures of some kind. I had a roll of 35mm E6 butchered on
me last year by a &amp;ldquo;professional&amp;rdquo; lab, and some of your blobs look a
little like what I had on my roll of film. Either that, or could there
be light leaks in the lab somewhere ? &lt;strong&gt;Joseph O&amp;rsquo;Neil&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;view-or-add-comments-http-www-greenspun-com-com-qtluong-photography-lf-leaks-html&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.greenspun.com/com/qtluong/photography/lf/leaks.html&#34;&gt;View or add comments&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>http://lflf.surge.sh/technical/merklinger-spreadsheet/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lflf.surge.sh/technical/merklinger-spreadsheet/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Spreadsheets to help the focussing process&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;spreadsheets-to-help-the-focussing-process&#34;&gt;Spreadsheets to help the focussing process&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Part of
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.largeformatphotography.info/&#34;&gt;largeformatphotography.info&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;an-spreadsheet-for-determining-plane-of-focus-and-depth-of-field-using-merklinger-s-method&#34;&gt;An spreadsheet for determining plane of focus and depth of field using Merklinger&amp;rsquo;s method&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;by &lt;a href=&#34;mailto:eirik.berger@lundblad.no&#34;&gt;Eirik Berger&lt;/a&gt; © 2002&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I made a spreadsheet (Excel) which helps you to determine the plane of
sharp focus. It also gives you information about areas where you have
acceptable sharpness at different apertures. This table is a perfect
tool in the field, print one table for each lens. You need to input:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the focal length of your lens (insert at top of the spreadsheet)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the estimate or measure of the distance J between lens and plane of
sharp focus.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The spreadsheet gives yo the plane of sharp focus at different lengths
(A) between lens and film. The little table at the bottom tells you in
what area you have acceptable focus. The &amp;ldquo;math&amp;rdquo; is based on the content
of Merklinger&amp;rsquo;s articles &amp;ldquo;The Scheimpflug rule&amp;rdquo; part 1-4 and &amp;ldquo;Depth of
field for view cameras&amp;rdquo; part 1-2.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is an example: the focal length is 90mm, and the distance (J) from
the lens to the &amp;ldquo;hinge line&amp;rdquo; where the plane of sharp focus meets the
&amp;ldquo;parallel to film&amp;rdquo; (PTF) plane is set to 175 cm. And then we want the
angle of the plane of sharp focus to be 60 degrees (0 degrees is upwards
along the film plane). The tilt-angle of the lens is 2,9 degrees (or 3
to make it simple) Then we can read out of the table that the lens to
film distance (A) must be 93 mm. The plane of sharp focus will &amp;ldquo;rotate&amp;rdquo;
around the hinge line beneath the lens. Then we decide to use aperture
f64, in the lower table we see that g=3,84mm (or 4mm to make it simple).
Then you count 4 mm up and down from 93 mm and determine the near limit
and far limit of the zone of acceptable focus. At aperture 64 the zone
of acceptable focus is between 36 and 104 degrees. If you use a
different aperture the outer limits of the zone will change accordingly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;excel/scheimpflugENG.xls&#34;&gt;Download the Excel file&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;spreadsheats-to-estimate-on-film-resolving-power&#34;&gt;Spreadsheats to estimate on-film resolving power&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;by &lt;a href=&#34;mailto:frank.loeffel@gmx.ch&#34;&gt;Frank Loeffel&lt;/a&gt; © 2003&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These spreadsheets try to estimate on-film resolving power based on
defocus, film resolution and lens resolution. The premise is that final
resolution is more interesting when focusing than resolution solely
based on a circle of confusion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are two versions. One is for large format work, where defocus can
be determined by the displacement at the ground glass. The other one is
for medium (and small) format work, where defocus can be determined by
displacement at the lenses&amp;rsquo; DOF scale.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;excel/LF-resolving.xls&#34;&gt;Download LF Excel file&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;excel/MF-resolving.xls&#34;&gt;Download MF Excel file&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>http://lflf.surge.sh/technical/scanning-glass-look/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lflf.surge.sh/technical/scanning-glass-look/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Generating classic glass negative look when scanning 4x5&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;generating-classic-glass-negative-look-when-scanning-4x5&#34;&gt;Generating classic glass negative look when scanning 4x5&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;By &lt;a href=&#34;mailto:Reinier.de.Vlaam@etm.ericsson.se&#34;&gt;Reinier de Vlaam&lt;/a&gt;, part
of
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.largeformatphotography.info/&#34;&gt;largeformatphotography.info&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I recently was looking for a cheap way to scan my B&amp;amp;W negatives into the
computer, mainly to verify if the composition was really good and the
neg worth spending time on in the darkroom. I searched for 2nd hand
scanners but best I could do was a Umax for 300 euro (=dollar), which
was out of my budget. I then ran into a guy who said he used an
ordinairy flatbed scanner and put a halogen building lamp with
milk-glass above it. The scan&amp;rsquo;s aren&amp;rsquo;t great but good enough for
analyzing. I used the same technique but rather than using milkglass I
covered the lamp with a piece of white printerpaper to make it more
flexible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently however I decided to put the paper on top of the negative, as
it was sunday and I ran out of printing paper accidently, and usally the
paper gets wrinkeled when I put it around the lamp. The result was
stunning. Together with some dirt on the scanners glass plate (caused by
dried moisture) and sepia toning it resulted in the scan that closely
resembled old glass negatives, much better than any PS old-style looks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;glass-negative-look.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.greenspun.com/com/qtluong/photography/lf/scanning-glass-look.html&#34;&gt;View or add
comments&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[](mailto:Reinier.de.Vlaam@etm.ericsson.se)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reinier.de.Vlaam@etm.ericsson.se&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>http://lflf.surge.sh/technical/sink-manufacturing/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lflf.surge.sh/technical/sink-manufacturing/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-to-make-a-custom-darkroom-sink-out-of-pvc&#34;&gt;How to make a custom darkroom sink out of PVC&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.mpr-photography.com/&#34;&gt;Mike Rosenberg&lt;/a&gt; © 2002, for
&lt;a href=&#34;.&#34;&gt;LFPhoto.info&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;sink/Sink7.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This sink is very easy to make, cheap relative to using epoxy paint or
fibroglass, and is odor free.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;materials&#34;&gt;Materials&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;8&lt;/sub&gt; inch Type I PVC (can be cut to specification by supplier). Comes in
4X8 ft sheets in white or dark gray, approx. \$43.00/sheet. The PVC can
be cut with an electric saw like plywood.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;X-15 adhesive for gluing the PVC to the plywood.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PVC pipe cement (any brand will do). There are three grades of cement
differing in viscosity and setting time. The high viscosity, which I
recommend for gluing the larger pieces to the underlayment will allow
time to position pieces. The gray medium viscosity will fill in gaps
better and is best for at the right-angle seams. The low viscosity clear
can be used on the edges of the bottom pan where you want it flat. Most
glue manufacturers have web sites that give specifications and
recommendations on glues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PVC pipe primer. This is put on the PVC before using the glue, and
softens the PVC allowing greater bonding&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PVC cleaner. This is used to clean the grease and dirt that may be on
the PVC and should be used prior to cementing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note: PVC adhesive is different from PVC cement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wood for pan sides and back splash — ABX plywood. It is sanded on one
side and is made with waterproof glue. Pressure treated lumber is
probably overkill in more ways than one, it does out-gas the wood
preservatives! Particle board is cheaper, but is not the best material
to use in wet areas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2X4 for legs and pan support.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;tools&#34;&gt;Tools&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Table saw.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Router.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Circular saw.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Block plane.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Belt sander or hand orbital sander.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Roller and paint pans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Straight edge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;instructions&#34;&gt;Instructions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Have the PVC cut for the dimensions of the sink, taking into account the
thickness of the material. You can cut the PVC with a table or circular
saw. Edges can be shaped with a router.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The pan for the sink should be designed to have suffucient strength to
hold the plastic and what-ever else you put in the sink. I used full
plywood sheets down the backsplash and attached to the legs to give
enough rigidity. A two by four frame was built for supporting the sink
pan (bottom) and attaching to legs, and an identical frame for a shelf
under the sink for storing pans. This gives great lateral strength. Cut
all the plywood and lay out. Measure and mark where a seam of two pieces
of PVC will occur. At these points you will use a thin strip of PVC
under the large pieces to overlap and reinforce the seams. Use a router
and cut a 1 inch or &lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; inch wide x &lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;8&lt;/sub&gt; inch deep groove to counter sink
this piece. At the vertical edges only one piece is necessary, but one
on each abutting piece can be used. Don&amp;rsquo;t forget to route out the seam
for the backsplash. It may take several passes with the router for the
full width. Go over the routed surfaces with a belt sander or other
alternative to ensure it is smooth. Avoid putting seam in bottom of pan
in the edge of the plywood that is the pan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The drain is a standard kitchen plastic drain, and needs to be recessed
for the water to drain. Use the appropriate size hole bit/drill for
cutting the drain where you want it to be — as close to the lowest side
of the sink. Again use the router to cut a &lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;8&lt;/sub&gt; deep X 6 in. X 6 in.
square - the drain will attach to this piece of PVC. Another hole needs
to be cut in the PVC of the under piece and top piece of the PVC. The
hole in the PVC of the pan should be large enough as to NOT overlap the
flange of the drain so that a proper leak proof seal is obtained when
cemented.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Assemble the wood of the sink. I recommend using glavanized decking
screws that will not rust. Adjust the pitch of the sink for &lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; fall
toward the drain - no more than that to avoid having your chemicals at
one side of the trays. It is amazing how well the water drains with this
little amount of slope. Brush the X-15 adhesive into the routed out
areas of the wood and then put in the PVC strip (note - shiny side up!).
Once this is completed brush or roll the X-15 to the rest of the wood.
Be careful not to get any on the PVC strips where it will contact PVC.
This is important because the PVC will be cemented to this strip. All
pieces of PVC to be cemented together must be free of dirt and grease
for the cement to work. Clean the surfaces to be cemented with the PVC
cleaner. Brush on the PVC primer to the strips of PVC one section at a
time just prior to putting on the cement. This will soften and roughen
the PVC for cementing. Then brush on an excess of the PVC cement and
position the PVC sheet - include edges where material will abut the edge
of another. You must work fast because it sets up quickly. The cement is
really a solvent, and will bond and fuse the material together. This is
what makes the sink permanent and water-proof. As you put vertical to
horizontal pieces together be sure edges are well glued. After all the
PVC is together and the glue has set to insure bonding at vertical and
horizontal edges, I recommend carefully applying a small amount of gray
medium viscosity cement with a syringe or similar applicator at the
edges for extra security — and to fill in gaps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can also put the PVC on the top of the plywood pan front and side
edges, and even down the outside to produce a better water proof
product. Bevel sharp edges of PVC at the tops of the sides with the
block plane.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Use poly-urethane to waterproof any surface of wood not covered with
PVC, like the legs and bottom shelf.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;additional-suggestions&#34;&gt;Additional suggestions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you feel the need to use a caulk you must use an appropriate caulk —
most will not adhere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A PVC two part putty, similar to an epoxy, could be used as a filler;
but this material is not considered permanent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Use wire shelving for over the sink. It is relatively cheap and strong.
It now comes in gray. It also has the additional advantage of that wet
items will drain into the sink.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Purchase an additional piece of white PVC sheeting for an easel to use
in the sink for bleaching and viewing prints.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Use all plastic CPVC spigots and plastic piping; this can easily be
mounted on the surface of the backsplash or the front inside edge of the
sink. This plastic requires the appropriate cement. The plastic will not
corrode and can easily be modified. Spigots can be plastic ball valves
or other valves — these are available at Lowes or Home Depot, and the
appropriate adaptor for threaded or barbed fittings can be used. I also
purchased a Hasse water tempering unit (the low volume unit costs
approx. \$450 and is suitable for the home darkroom), which I find to be
well worth the cost for insuring even temperature while washing film or
prints.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;pictures&#34;&gt;Pictures&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;sink/Sink1.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;sink/Sink2.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;sink/Sink3.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;sink/Sink4.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;sink/Sink5.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt; &lt;img src=&#34;sink/Sink6.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;view-add-comment-http-www-greenspun-com-com-qtluong-photography-lf-sink-manufacturing-html&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.greenspun.com/com/qtluong/photography/lf/sink-manufacturing.html&#34;&gt;View/Add comment&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[](mailto:mprosenberg@earthlink.net)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;mprosenberg@earthlink.net&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>http://lflf.surge.sh/technical/stability/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lflf.surge.sh/technical/stability/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Large Format Photography: View camera stability&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;view-camera-stability&#34;&gt;View camera stability&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Compiled by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.terragalleria.com/&#34;&gt;Q.-Tuan Luong&lt;/a&gt; for &lt;a href=&#34;.&#34;&gt;the
Large Format Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;By &lt;a href=&#34;mailto:ulformat@teleport.com&#34;&gt;Don Nelson&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I regularly use an Arca Swiss 8x10 with Nikor T1200 (that&amp;rsquo;s about a
meter of bellows at infinity!). You **can** make sharp
images.(exposures range upwards to many seconds with this system).
Perhaps the following suggestions will help those that are having
problems even with 360mm lenses:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1) Good Ball head (I prefer an Arca Swiss B-2 due to the mass of the
larger camera and the wonderful(IMHO) dual-ball design. YMMV- other
ballheads will probably work just as well)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2) Kirk Enterprises sells a neat tripod arm that attaches to a tripod
leg and *happens* to have a ball head on the other end with an Arca
plate (just happens to fit an extended rail on the Arca :-). This arm
extends from the tripod leg to the rail and gives a lot of additional
rigidity for just a little more weight in the tripod. This little tripod
arm can be built for any tripod, and you can put an Arca plate to tripod
thread (or other arrangement) on the other end. This arm was developed
for the folks in 35mm/120 using extremely long lenses without a second
tripod.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;3) Tripod (with ball head) goes under the lens. A monopod (with a little
ballhead for ease of use) goes under the rail at the ground glass end&amp;hellip;
so much easier than schlepping a second tripod.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;OK - you now have a stable platform that is easy to carry (OK, not as
easy as 4x5 but you get the point).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;4)Now you need to take care of the wind on the bellows. For this you
will need a large golf umbrella.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For shorter lenses I always use the Kirk Arm for additional support (and
the umbrella for the breeze regardless of focal length)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This system is adaptable to any camera-tripod that you may have. I have
used a similar setup with a Larger KBCanham as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;By &lt;a href=&#34;mailto:bjs@oes.amdahl.com&#34;&gt;Barry Sherman&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;gt; 1.If the wind is blowing, NO tripod is going to give you a sharp slow
&amp;gt; exposure, because the bellows will be vibrating, thus the camera will be
&amp;gt; vibrating.

&amp;gt; 2. If the wind is not blowing, any tripod strong enough not to fall down
&amp;gt; from the weight of the camera is just fine, so long as you use a very long
&amp;gt; (preferably one of the pneumatic ones with six feet of tube) cable
&amp;gt; release.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ll gently disagree with this. Wrt photographing in the wind: Yes, I&amp;rsquo;d
have agreed with Alan until I discovered my Handy Dandy Portable Semi-
Shelter From The Wind. (Umbrellas). I&amp;rsquo;ve been amazed at how much I can
shelter the camera from the wind by using an umbrella. Unless the wind
is coming from directly in front of the camera, I can almost always hold
an umbrella up real close to the camera body and minimize the breeze
enough to almost completely eliminate Readyload envelopes from moving.
And it doesn&amp;rsquo;t take much breeze to make Readyload envlopes sway. (I&amp;rsquo;ve
experimented and satisfied myself that some minimal movement of the
Readyload envelope will not be transmitted to the film, btw.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since I discovered the utility of carrying a small folding umbrella I&amp;rsquo;ve
been able to photograph under windy conditions which would have,
previously, had me seriously doubting whether to bother to set up.
However, the umbrella only shelters the camera. If the tripod is
insufficiently stiff then the wind will be making lots of vibration in
the tripod legs and this will negate the sheltering of the camera itself
by the umbrella.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wrt the second point, I&amp;rsquo;m just not so sure. I used to use two tripods:
mostly a Bogen 3221 and somewhat a much heavier Bogen 3236. Then one day
I started to see a correlation between sharpnes when using longer lenses
(300mm) and which tripod I was using. Even on breeze-free days.
Intellectually it seems to me that on a breeze-free day and provided
that great care is taken to allow vibration to damp out and with the
cable release then the sturdiness of the tripod shouldn&amp;rsquo;t matter. But
that really counts on idea conditions and I don&amp;rsquo;t think that I can count
on always providing ideal conditions. So I prefer a heavier tripod
(within my ability to carry it, of course.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.greenspun.com/com/qtluong/photography/lf/stability.html&#34;&gt;View or add
comments&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>